<WORK genre="play">
<iseHeader>
<META name="ISE.DocumentType" content="play"/>
<META name="ISE.comment" content="Edited for the Internet Shakespeare Editions by David Bevington." />
<META name="ISE.EditStatus" content="Edited" />
<META name="ISE.PeerReviewed" content="Yes" />
<META name="ISE.EditorialPrinciple" content="This edition is based on the Folio text of 1623." />
<META name="ISE.SectionDivision" content="scene" />
<META name="ISE.SectionDisplay" content="1" />
<META name="ISE.LineNumberInterval" content="5" />

<LINK rel="schema.DC" href="http://purl.org/dc"/>
<META name="DC.Title" content="As You Like It" />
<META name="DC.Title.Alternative" content="As You Like It (Modern)" />
<META name="DC.Creator" content="William Shakespeare" />
<META name="DC.Subject" content="As You Like It, Shakespeare, modern-spelling" />
<META name="DC.Description" content="A modernized edition of As You Like It edited by David Bevington for the Internet Shakespeare Editions." />
<META name="DC.Publisher" content="Internet Shakespeare Editions, University of Victoria" />
<META name="DC.Contributor.Editor" content="Bevington, David" />
<META name="DC.Contributor.Textual.Editor" content="Rasmussen, Eric" />
<META name="DC.Contributor.Coordinating.Editor" content="Best, Michael" />
<META name="DC.Date" scheme="W3CDTF" content="2006-11-01" />
<META name="DC.Date.Modified" scheme="W3CDTF" content="2007-04-19" />
<META name="DC.Type" content="text" />
<META name="DC.Format" content="text/sgml" />
<META name="DC.Identifier" scheme="MLA" content="AYL_M" />
<META name="DC.Identifier" scheme="ISBN" content="978-1-55058-369-4" />
<META name="DC.Source" content="Modern" />
<META name="DC.Language" scheme="RFC1766" content="en" />
<META name="DC.Relation" content="http://internetshakespeare.uvic.ca/" />
<META name="DC.Relation.IsFormatOf" content="Modern-spelling edition based on the First Folio of 1623." />
<META name="DC.Rights" content="Copyright David Bevington. This text may be freely used for educational, non-profit purposes; for all other uses contact the Editor." />
</iseHeader>

<TITLEHEAD>As You Like It</TITLEHEAD>
<ACT n="1">
<SCENE n="1">
<H2><TLN n="1"/>[1.1]</H2>

<TLN n="2"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Orlando and Adam.</SD>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="1"/><TLN n="3"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
<TLN n="4"/>As I remember, Adam, it was upon this fashion <TLN n="5"/>bequeathed me by will but poor a thousand <TLN n="6"/>crowns, and, as thou say'st, charged my brother, <TLN n="7"/>on his blessing, to breed me well; and <TLN n="8"/>there begins my sadness. My brother Jaques he keeps <TLN n="9"/>at school, and report speaks goldenly of his profit. <TLN n="10"/>For my part, he keeps me rustically at home, or, to speak <TLN n="11"/>more properly, stays me here at home unkept; for call <TLN n="12"/>you that "keeping" for a gentleman of my birth that differs <TLN n="13"/>not from the stalling of an ox? His horses are bred <TLN n="14"/>better, for, besides that they are fair with their feeding, <TLN n="15"/>they are taught their man{`e}ge, and to that end riders <TLN n="16"/>dearly hired; but I, his brother, gain nothing under <TLN n="17"/>him but growth, for the which his animals on his <TLN n="18"/>dunghills are as much bound to him as I. Besides this nothing <TLN n="19"/>that he so plentifully gives me, the something that <TLN n="20"/>nature gave me his countenance seems to take from <TLN n="21"/>me. He lets me feed with his hinds, bars me the <TLN n="22"/>place of a brother, and as much as in him lies, mines my <TLN n="23"/>gentility with my education. This is it, Adam, that <TLN n="24"/>grieves me; and the spirit of my father, which I think <TLN n="25"/>is within me, begins to mutiny against this servitude. <TLN n="26"/>I will no longer endure it, though yet I know no wise <TLN n="27"/>remedy how to avoid it.</S>

<TLN n="28"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Oliver.</SD>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="29"/><S><SP>Adam</SP>
Yonder comes my master, your brother.</S>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="30"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Go apart, Adam, and thou shalt hear how <TLN n="31"/>he will shake me up.</S>
<SD t="action">[Adam stands aside.]</SD>

<L n="4"/><TLN n="32"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Now, sir, what make you here?</S>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="33"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Nothing. I am not taught to make anything.</S>

<L n="6"/><TLN n="34"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
What mar you then, sir?</S>

<L n="7"/><TLN n="35"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Marry, sir, I am helping you to mar that which <TLN n="36"/>God made, a poor unworthy brother of yours, with <TLN n="37"/>idleness.</S>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="38"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Marry, sir, be better employed, and be naught awhile.<TLN n="39"/></S>

<L n="9"/><TLN n="40"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Shall I keep your hogs, and eat husks with <TLN n="41"/>them? What prodigal portion have I spent, that I should <TLN n="42"/>come to such penury?</S>

<L n="10"/><TLN n="43"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Know you where you are, sir?</S>

<L n="11"/><TLN n="44"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Oh, sir, very well: here in your orchard.</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="45"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Know you before whom, sir?</S>

<L n="13"/><TLN n="46"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Ay, better than him I am before knows me. I <TLN n="47"/>know you are my eldest brother, and in the gentle condition <TLN n="48"/>of blood you should so know me. The courtesy of nations<TLN n="49"/> allows you my better in that you are the first <TLN n="50"/>born; but the same tradition takes not away my blood, <TLN n="51"/>were there twenty brothers betwixt us. I have as much <TLN n="52"/>of my father in me as you, albeit I confess your coming <TLN n="53"/>before me is nearer to his reverence.</S>

<L n="14"/><TLN n="54"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
What, boy!</S>
<SD t="action">[He strikes Orlando.]</SD>

<L n="15"/><TLN n="55"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Come, come, elder brother, you are too young in this.</S>
<SD t="action">[He seizes Oliver by the throat.]</SD>

<L n="16"/><TLN n="56"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Wilt thou lay hands on me, villain?</S>

<L n="17"/><TLN n="57"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I am no villain. I am the youngest son of <TLN n="58"/>Sir Rowland de Boys. He was my father, and he is thrice a villain <TLN n="59"/>that says such a father begot villains. Wert thou <TLN n="60"/>not my brother, I would not take this hand from thy <TLN n="61"/>throat till this other had pulled out thy tongue for saying <TLN n="62"/>so. Thou hast railed on thyself.</S>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="63"/><S><SP>Adam</SP>
<SD t="action">[Coming forward]</SD>
Sweet masters, be patient! For your father's remembrance<TLN n="64"/>, be at accord.</S>

<L n="19"/><TLN n="65"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando]</SD>
Let me go, I say.</S>

<L n="20"/><TLN n="66"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I will not, till I please. You shall hear me. My <TLN n="67"/>father charged you in his will to give me good education. <TLN n="68"/>You have trained me like a peasant, obscuring and <TLN n="69"/>hiding from me all gentlemanlike qualities. The spirit <TLN n="70"/>of my father grows strong in me, and I will no longer <TLN n="71"/>endure it; therefore allow me such exercises as may become <TLN n="72"/>a gentleman, or give me the poor allottery my <TLN n="73"/>father left me by testament. With that I will go buy my <TLN n="74"/>fortunes.</S>
<SD t="action">[He releases Oliver.]</SD>

<L n="21"/><TLN n="75"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
And what wilt thou do? Beg, when that is spent? <TLN n="76"/>Well, sir, get you in. I will not long be troubled with <TLN n="77"/>you; you shall have some part of your will. I pray you <TLN n="78"/>leave me.</S>

<L n="22"/><TLN n="79"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I will no further offend you than becomes me <TLN n="80"/>for my good.</S>

<L n="23"/><TLN n="81"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Adam]</SD>
Get you with him, you old dog.</S>

<L n="24"/><TLN n="82"/><S><SP>Adam</SP>
Is "old dog" my reward? Most true, I have <TLN n="83"/>lost my teeth in your service. God be with my old master! <TLN n="84"/>He would not have spoke such a word.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt Orlando and Adam.</SD>

<L n="25"/><TLN n="85"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Is it even so? Begin you to grow upon me? I will <TLN n="86"/>physic your rankness, and yet give no thousand <TLN n="87"/>crowns neither. <SD t="action">[Calling]</SD>Holla, Dennis!</S>

<TLN n="88"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Dennis.</SD>

<L n="26"/><TLN n="89"/><S><SP>Dennis</SP>
Calls Your Worship?</S>

<L n="27"/><TLN n="90"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Was not Charles, the Duke's wrestler, here to <TLN n="91"/>speak with me?</S>

<L n="28"/><TLN n="92"/><S><SP>Dennis</SP>
So please you, he is here at the door and importunes <TLN n="93"/>access to you.</S>

<L n="29"/><TLN n="94"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Call him in.
<SD t="exit">[Exit Dennis.]</SD>
'Twill be a good way; and tomorrow <TLN n="95"/>the wrestling is.</S>

<TLN n="96"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Charles.</SD>

<L n="30"/><TLN n="97"/><S><SP>Charles</SP>
Good morrow to Your Worship.</S>

<L n="31"/><TLN n="98"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Good Monsieur Charles, what's the new news <TLN n="99"/>at the new court?</S>

<L n="32"/><TLN n="100"/><S><SP>Charles</SP>
There's no news at the court, sir, but the <TLN n="101"/>old news: that is, the old Duke is banished by his younger <TLN n="102"/>brother the new Duke, and three or four loving <TLN n="103"/>lords have put themselves into voluntary exile with <TLN n="104"/>him, whose lands and revenues enrich the new Duke; <TLN n="105"/>therefore he gives them good leave to wander.</S>

<L n="33"/><TLN n="106"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Can you tell if Rosalind, the Duke's daughter, be <TLN n="107"/>banished with her father?</S>

<L n="34"/><TLN n="108"/><S><SP>Charles</SP>
Oh, no; for the Duke's daughter, her cousin, so <TLN n="109"/>loves her, being ever from their cradles bred together, <TLN n="110"/>that she would have followed her exile or have died to <TLN n="111"/>stay behind her. She is at the court, and no less beloved <TLN n="112"/>of her uncle than his own daughter; and never two ladies <TLN n="113"/>loved as they do.</S>

<L n="35"/><TLN n="114"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Where will the old Duke live?</S>

<L n="36"/><TLN n="115"/><S><SP>Charles</SP>
They say he is already in the Forest of Arden, <TLN n="116"/>and a many merry men with him; and there they live <TLN n="117"/>like the old Robin Hood of England. They say many young <TLN n="118"/>gentlemen flock to him every day, and fleet the time <TLN n="119"/>carelessly, as they did in the golden world.</S>

<L n="37"/><TLN n="120"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
What, you wrestle tomorrow before the new <TLN n="121"/>Duke?</S>

<L n="38"/><TLN n="122"/><S><SP>Charles</SP>
Marry, do I, sir; and I came to acquaint you <TLN n="123"/>with a matter. I am given, sir, secretly to understand that <TLN n="124"/>your younger brother, Orlando, hath a disposition to come <TLN n="125"/>in disguised against me to try a fall. Tomorrow, sir, <TLN n="126"/>I wrestle for my credit; and he that escapes me without <TLN n="127"/>some broken limb shall acquit him well. Your brother <TLN n="128"/>is but young and tender; and, for your love, I would be <TLN n="129"/>loath to foil him, as I must, for my own honor, if he <TLN n="130"/>come in. Therefore, out of my love to you, I came hither <TLN n="131"/>to acquaint you withal, that either you might stay him <TLN n="132"/>from his intendment, or brook such disgrace well as he <TLN n="133"/>shall run into, in that it is a thing of his own search <TLN n="134"/>and altogether against my will.</S>

<L n="39"/><TLN n="135"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Charles, I thank thee for thy love to me, which <TLN n="136"/>thou shalt find I will most kindly requite. I had myself <TLN n="137"/>notice of my brother's purpose herein, and have by <TLN n="138"/>underhand means labored to dissuade him from it; <TLN n="139"/>but he is resolute. I'll tell thee, Charles, it is the stubbornest <TLN n="140"/>young fellow of France, full of ambition, an envious emulator <TLN n="141"/>of every man's good parts, a secret and villainous <TLN n="142"/>contriver against me his natural brother. Therefore use <TLN n="143"/>thy discretion. I had as lief thou didst break his neck <TLN n="144"/>as his finger. And thou wert best look to't; for if thou <TLN n="145"/>dost him any slight disgrace, or if he do not mightily <TLN n="146"/>grace himself on thee, he will practice against thee by <TLN n="147"/>poison, entrap thee by some treacherous device, and never <TLN n="148"/>leave thee till he hath ta'en thy life by some indirect <TLN n="149"/>means or other; for, I assure thee, and almost with <TLN n="150"/>tears I speak it, there is not one so young and so villainous <TLN n="151"/>this day living. I speak but brotherly of him, <TLN n="152"/>but should I anatomize him to thee as he is, I must <TLN n="153"/>blush and weep, and thou must look pale and <TLN n="154"/>wonder.</S>

<L n="40"/><TLN n="155"/><S><SP>Charles</SP>
I am heartily glad I came hither to you. If he <TLN n="156"/>come tomorrow I'll give him his payment. If ever he <TLN n="157"/>go alone again, I'll never wrestle for prize more. And <TLN n="158"/>so, God keep Your Worship!</S>
<SD t="exit">Exit.</SD>

<L n="41"/><TLN n="159"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Farewell, good Charles. Now will I stir this gamester. <TLN n="160"/>I hope I shall see an end of him; for my soul, yet <TLN n="161"/>I know not why, hates nothing more than he. Yet he's <TLN n="162"/>gentle, never schooled and yet learned, full of noble <TLN n="163"/>device, of all sorts enchantingly beloved, and indeed <TLN n="164"/>so much in the heart of the world, and especially of my <TLN n="165"/>own people, who best know him, that I am altogether <TLN n="166"/>misprized. But it shall not be so long; this wrestler shall <TLN n="167"/>clear all. Nothing remains but that I kindle the boy <TLN n="168"/>thither, which now I'll go about.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exit.</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="2">
<H2><TLN n="169"/>[1.2]</H2>
<TLN n="170"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Rosalind and Celia.</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="171"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
I pray thee, Rosalind, sweet my coz, be merry.</S>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="172"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Dear Celia, I show more mirth than I am mistress of; <TLN n="173"/><!--TLN moved +1 -->and would you yet I were merrier? Unless you <TLN n="174"/>could teach me to forget a banished father, you must not <TLN n="175"/>learn me how to remember any extraordinary <TLN n="176"/>pleasure.</S>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="177"/><S><SP> Celia</SP>
Herein I see thou lov'st me not with the full <TLN n="178"/>weight that I love thee. If my uncle, thy banished father, <TLN n="179"/>had banished thy uncle, the Duke my father, so thou <TLN n="180"/>hadst been still with me, I could have taught my love <TLN n="181"/>to take thy father for mine; so wouldst thou, if the truth <TLN n="182"/>of thy love to me were so righteously tempered as mine <TLN n="183"/>is to thee.</S>

<L n="4"/><TLN n="184"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Well, I will forget the condition of my estate, <TLN n="185"/>to rejoice in yours.</S>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="186"/><S><SP> Celia</SP>
You know my father hath no child but I, nor <TLN n="187"/>none is like to have; and, truly, when he dies thou shalt <TLN n="188"/>be his heir, for what he hath taken away from thy father <TLN n="189"/>perforce I will render thee again in affection. By <TLN n="190"/>mine honor, I will; and when I break that oath, let me <TLN n="191"/>turn monster. Therefore, my sweet Rose, my dear Rose, <TLN n="192"/>be merry.</S>

<L n="6"/><TLN n="193"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
From henceforth I will, coz, and devise sports. <TLN n="194"/>Let me see, what think you of falling in love?</S>

<L n="7"/><TLN n="195"/><S><SP> Celia</SP>
Marry, I prithee, do, to make sport withal; but <TLN n="196"/>love no man in good earnest, nor no further in sport neither <TLN n="197"/>than with safety of a pure blush thou mayst in honor <TLN n="198"/>come off again.</S>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="199"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
What shall be our sport, then?</S>

<L n="9"/><TLN n="200"/><S><SP> Celia</SP>
Let us sit and mock the good housewife Fortune <TLN n="201"/>from her wheel, that her gifts may henceforth be <TLN n="202"/>bestowed equally.</S>

<L n="10"/><TLN n="203"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I would we could do so, for her benefits are <TLN n="204"/>mightily misplaced, and the bountiful blind woman <TLN n="205"/>doth most mistake in her gifts to women.</S>

<L n="11"/><TLN n="206"/><S><SP> Celia</SP>
'Tis true, for those that she makes fair she scarce <TLN n="207"/>makes honest, and those that she makes honest she makes <TLN n="208"/>very ill-favoredly.</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="209"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Nay, now thou goest from Fortune's office to Nature's: <TLN n="210"/>Fortune reigns in gifts of the world, not in the <TLN n="211"/>lineaments of Nature.</S>

<TLN n="212"/><SD t="entrance">Enter [Touchstone the] Clown.</SD>

<L n="13"/><TLN n="213"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
No? When Nature hath made a fair creature, <TLN n="214"/>may she not by Fortune fall into the fire? Though Nature <TLN n="215"/>hath given us wit to flout at Fortune, hath not Fortune <TLN n="216"/>sent in this fool to cut off the argument?</S>

<L n="14"/><TLN n="217"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Indeed, there is Fortune too hard for Nature, when <TLN n="218"/>Fortune makes Nature's natural the cutter-off of Nature's wit.<TLN n="219"/><!--TLN moved +1 --></S>

<L n="15"/><TLN n="220"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Peradventure this is not Fortune's work neither, <TLN n="221"/>but Nature's, who perceiveth our natural wits too dull <TLN n="222"/>to reason of such goddesses, and hath sent this natural for <TLN n="223"/>our whetstone; for always the dullness of the fool is <TLN n="224"/>the whetstone of the wits. -- How now, wit, whither wander you?<TLN n="225"/><!--TLN moved +2 --></S>

<L n="16"/><TLN n="226"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Mistress, you must come away to your father.</S>

<L n="17"/><TLN n="227"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Were you made the messenger?</S>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="228"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
No, by mine honor, but I was bid to come for you.</S>

<L n="19"/><TLN n="229"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Where learned you that oath, fool?</S>

<L n="20"/><TLN n="230"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Of a certain knight that swore by his honor <TLN n="231"/>they were good pancakes, and swore by his honor the <TLN n="232"/>mustard was naught. Now I'll stand to it, the pancakes <TLN n="233"/>were naught and the mustard was good, and yet was <TLN n="234"/>not the knight forsworn.</S>

<L n="21"/><TLN n="235"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
How prove you that, in the great heap of your <TLN n="236"/>knowledge?</S>

<L n="22"/><TLN n="237"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Ay, marry, now unmuzzle your wisdom.</S>

<L n="23"/><TLN n="238"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Stand you both forth now. Stroke your chins, <TLN n="239"/>and swear by your beards that I am a knave.</S>

<L n="24"/><TLN n="240"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
By our beards, if we had them, thou art.</S>

<L n="25"/><TLN n="241"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
By my knavery, if I had it, then I were; but if <TLN n="242"/>you swear by that that is not, you are not forsworn. No <TLN n="243"/>more was this knight, swearing by his honor, for he never <TLN n="244"/>had any; or if he had, he had sworn it away before <TLN n="245"/>ever he saw those pancakes or that mustard.</S>

<L n="26"/><TLN n="246"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Prithee, who is't that thou mean'st?</S>

<L n="27"/><TLN n="247"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
One that old Frederick, your father, loves.</S>

<L n="28"/><TLN n="248"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
My father's love is enough to honor him. Enough, <TLN n="249"/>speak no more of him; you'll be whipped for taxation one <TLN n="250"/>of these days.</S>

<L n="29"/><TLN n="251"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
The more pity that fools may not speak wisely<TLN n="252"/>what wise men do foolishly.</S>

<L n="30"/><TLN n="253"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
By my troth, thou sayest true; for since the little <TLN n="254"/>wit that fools have was silenced, the little foolery that <TLN n="255"/>wise men have makes a great show. Here comes Monsieur <TLN n="256"/>Le Beau.</S>

<TLN n="257"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Le Beau.</SD>

<L n="31"/><TLN n="258"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
With his mouth full of news.</S>

<L n="32"/><TLN n="259"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Which he will put on us as pigeons feed their <TLN n="260"/>young.</S>

<L n="33"/><TLN n="261"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Then shall we be news-crammed.</S>

<L n="34"/><TLN n="262"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
All the better; we shall be the more marketable. -- <TLN n="263"/><FOREIGN lang="French">Bonjour</FOREIGN>, Monsieur Le Beau. What's the news?</S>

<L n="35"/><TLN n="264"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
Fair princess, <TLN n="265"/>you have lost much good sport.</S>

<L n="36"/><TLN n="266"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Sport? Of what color?</S>

<L n="37"/><TLN n="267"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
What color, madam? How shall I answer <TLN n="268"/>you?</S>

<L n="38"/><TLN n="269"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
As wit and fortune will.</S>

<L n="39"/><TLN n="270"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Or as the Destinies decrees.</S>

<L n="40"/><TLN n="271"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Well said. That was laid on with a trowel.</S>

<L n="41"/><TLN n="272"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Nay, if I keep not my rank --</S>

<L n="42"/><TLN n="273"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Thou loosest thy old smell.</S>

<L n="43"/><TLN n="274"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
You amaze me, ladies. I would have told <TLN n="275"/>you of good wrestling, which you have lost the sight of.</S>

<L n="44"/><TLN n="276"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Yet tell us the manner of the wrestling.</S>

<L n="45"/><TLN n="277"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
I will tell you the beginning, and, if it please <TLN n="278"/>Your Ladyships, you may see the end, for the best is yet to do, <TLN n="279"/><!--TLN moved +2 -->and here, where you are, they are coming to <TLN n="280"/>perform it.</S>

<L n="46"/><TLN n="281"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Well, the beginning, that is dead and buried.</S>

<L n="47"/><TLN n="282"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
There comes an old man and his three sons --</S>

<L n="48"/><TLN n="283"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
I could match this beginning with an old tale.</S>

<L n="49"/><TLN n="284"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
Three proper young men, of excellent growth <TLN n="285"/>and presence.</S>

<L n="50"/><TLN n="286"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
With bills on their necks: "Be it known unto <TLN n="287"/>all men by these presents --"</S>

<L n="51"/><TLN n="288"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
The eldest of the three wrestled with Charles, <TLN n="289"/>the Duke's wrestler, which Charles in a moment threw <TLN n="290"/>him and broke three of his ribs, that there is little <TLN n="291"/>hope of life in him. So he served the second, and so the <TLN n="292"/>third. Yonder they lie, the poor old man their father <TLN n="293"/>making such pitiful dole over them that all the beholders <TLN n="294"/>take his part with weeping.</S>

<L n="52"/><TLN n="295"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Alas!</S>

<L n="53"/><TLN n="296"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
But what is the sport, monsieur, that the ladies <TLN n="297"/>have lost?</S>

<L n="54"/><TLN n="298"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
Why, this that I speak of.</S>

<L n="55"/><TLN n="299"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Thus men may grow wiser every day. It is the <TLN n="300"/>first time that ever I heard breaking of ribs was sport <TLN n="301"/>for ladies.</S>

<L n="56"/><TLN n="302"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Or I, I promise thee.</S>

<L n="57"/><TLN n="303"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
But is there any else longs to see this broken music <TLN n="304"/><!--TLN moved +1 -->in his sides? Is there yet another dotes upon <TLN n="305"/>rib-breaking? -- Shall we see this wrestling, cousin?</S>

<L n="58"/><TLN n="306"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>You must, if you stay here, for here is the <TLN n="307"/>place appointed for the wrestling, and they are ready to <TLN n="308"/>perform it.</S>

<L n="59"/><TLN n="309"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Yonder, sure, they are coming. Let us now stay <TLN n="310"/>and see it.</S>

<TLN n="311"/><SD t="sound"> Flourish.</SD><SD t="entrance"> Enter Duke [Frederick], Lords, Orlando, Charles, <TLN n="312"/>and Attendants</SD>

<L n="60"/><TLN n="313"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
Come on. Since the youth will not be entreated, <TLN n="314"/>his own peril on his forwardness.</S>

<L n="61"/><TLN n="315"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Le Beau]</SD>
Is yonder the man?</S>

<L n="62"/><TLN n="316"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
Even he, madam.</S>

<L n="63"/><TLN n="317"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Alas, he is too young; yet he looks successfully.</S>

<L n="64"/><TLN n="318"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
How now, daughter and cousin? <TLN n="319"/>Are you crept hither to see the wrestling?</S>

<L n="65"/><TLN n="320"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Ay, my liege, so please you give us leave.</S>

<L n="66"/><TLN n="321"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
You will take little delight in it, I can tell you, <TLN n="322"/>there is such odds in the man. In pity of the challenger's <TLN n="323"/> youth I would fain dissuade him, but he will not <TLN n="324"/>be entreated. Speak to him, ladies; see if you can <TLN n="325"/>move him.</S>

<L n="67"/><TLN n="326"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Call him hither, good Monsieur Le Beau.</S>

<L n="68"/><TLN n="327"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
Do so. I'll not be by.</S>
<SD t="action">[Duke Frederick stands aside.]</SD>

<L n="69"/><TLN n="328"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando]</SD> 
Monsieur the Challenger, the Princess calls <TLN n="329"/>for you.</S>

<L n="70"/><TLN n="330"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
<SD t="action">[Approaching Rosalind and Celia]</SD>
I attend them with all respect and duty.</S>

<L n="71"/><TLN n="331"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Young man, have you challenged Charles the <TLN n="332"/>wrestler?</S>

<L n="72"/><TLN n="333"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
No, fair princess, he is the general challenger. <TLN n="334"/>I come but in, as others do, to try with him the strength <TLN n="335"/>of my youth.</S>

<L n="73"/><TLN n="336"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Young gentleman, your spirits are too bold for <TLN n="337"/>your years. You have seen cruel proof of this man's <TLN n="338"/>strength. If you saw yourself with your eyes, or knew <TLN n="339"/>yourself with your judgment, the fear of your adventure <TLN n="340"/>would counsel you to a more equal enterprise. We <TLN n="341"/>pray you, for your own sake, to embrace your own safety <TLN n="342"/> and give over this attempt.</S>

<L n="74"/><TLN n="343"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Do, young sir. Your reputation shall not therefore <TLN n="344"/>be misprized. We will make it our suit to the Duke that <TLN n="345"/>the wrestling might not go forward.</S>

<L n="75"/><TLN n="346"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I beseech you, punish me not with your hard <TLN n="347"/>thoughts, wherein I confess me much guilty to deny <TLN n="348"/>so fair and excellent ladies anything. But let your <TLN n="349"/>fair eyes and gentle wishes go with me to my trial, <TLN n="350"/>wherein if I be foiled, there is but one shamed that was <TLN n="351"/>never gracious; if killed, but one dead that is willing to <TLN n="352"/>be so. I shall do my friends no wrong, for I have none to <TLN n="353"/>lament me; the world no injury, for in it I have nothing. <TLN n="354"/>Only in the world I fill up a place, which may be better <TLN n="355"/>supplied when I have made it empty.</S>

<L n="76"/><TLN n="356"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
The little strength that I have, I would it were <TLN n="357"/>with you.</S>

<L n="77"/><TLN n="358"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
And mine, to eke out hers.</S>

<L n="78"/><TLN n="359"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Fare you well. Pray heaven I be deceived in you!</S>

<L n="79"/><TLN n="360"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Your heart's desires be with you!</S>

<L n="80"/><TLN n="361"/><S><SP>Charles</SP>
Come, where is this young gallant that is so <TLN n="362"/>desirous to lie with his mother earth?</S>

<L n="81"/><TLN n="363"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Ready, sir, but his will hath in it a more modest <TLN n="364"/>working.</S>

<L n="82"/><TLN n="365"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
You shall try but one fall.</S>

<L n="83"/><TLN n="366"/><S><SP>Charles</SP>
No, I warrant Your Grace you shall not entreat <TLN n="367"/>him to a second, that have so mightily persuaded him <TLN n="368"/>from a first.</S>

<L n="84"/><TLN n="369"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
You mean to mock me after; you should not <TLN n="370"/>have mocked me before. But come your ways.</S>

<L n="85"/><TLN n="371"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Now, Hercules be thy speed, young man!</S>

<L n="86"/><TLN n="372"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
I would I were invisible, to catch the strong fellow <TLN n="373"/>by the leg.</S>
<SD t="action">[Orlando and Charles] wrestle.</SD>

<L n="87"/><TLN n="374"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Oh, excellent young man!</S>

<L n="88"/><TLN n="375"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
If I had a thunderbolt in mine eye, I can tell who <TLN n="376"/>should down.</S>
<SD t="action">[Charles is thrown.]</SD> <SD t="sound">Shout.</SD>

<L n="89"/><TLN n="377"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
No more, no more.</S>

<L n="90"/><TLN n="378"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Yes, I beseech Your Grace. I am not yet <TLN n="379"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->well breathed.</S>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="91" part="i"/><TLN n="380"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
How dost thou, Charles?</S>

<L n="91" part="f"><TLN n="381"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
He cannot speak, my lord.</S>

<L n="92"/><TLN n="382"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
Bear him away.
<SD t="action">[Charles is carried out.]</SD>
<TLN n="383"/> 
What is thy name, young man?</S>

<L n="93"/><TLN n="384"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">
Orlando, my liege, the youngest son of Sir Rowland <TLN n="385"/>de Boys.</S>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="94"><TLN n="386"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
I would thou hadst been son to some man else.
<L n="95"><TLN n="387"/>The world esteemed thy father honorable,
<L n="96"><TLN n="388"/>But I did find him still mine enemy.
<L n="97"><TLN n="389"/>Thou shouldst have better pleased me with this deed
<L n="98"><TLN n="390"/>Hadst thou descended from another house.
<L n="99"><TLN n="391"/>But fare thee well; thou art a gallant youth.
<L n="100"><TLN n="392"/>I would thou hadst told me of another father.</S>
<TLN n="393"/><SD t="exit">Exit Duke [with train, and Le Beau. Rosalind and Celia remain, standing apart from Orlando].</SD>

<L n="101"><TLN n="394"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Rosalind]</SD>
Were I my father, coz, would I do this?</S>

<L n="102"/><TLN n="395"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[Talking to himself]</SD>
I am more proud to be Sir Rowland's son,
<L n="103"/><TLN n="396"/>His youngest son, and would not change that calling
<L n="104"/><TLN n="397"/>To be adopted heir to Frederick.</S>

<L n="105"/><TLN n="398"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Celia]</SD>
My father loved Sir Rowland as his soul,
<L n="106"/><TLN n="399"/>And all the world was of my father's mind.
<L n="107"/><TLN n="400"/>Had I before known this young man his son,
<L n="108"/><TLN n="401"/>I should have given him tears unto entreaties
<L n="109" part="i"/><TLN n="402"/>Ere he should thus have ventured.</S>

<L n="109" part="f"/><TLN n="403"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Gentle cousin,
<L n="110"/><TLN n="404"/>Let us go thank him, and encourage him.
<L n="111"/><TLN n="405"/>My father's rough and envious disposition
<L n="112"/><TLN n="406"/>Sticks me at heart.<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando]</SD>Sir, you have well deserved.
<L n="113"/><TLN n="407"/>If you do keep your promises in love
<L n="114"/><TLN n="408"/>But justly as you have exceeded all promise,
<L n="115" part="i"/><TLN n="409"/>Your mistress shall be happy.</S>

<L n="115" part="f"/><TLN n="410"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Gentleman,
<SD t="action">[Giving him a chain from her neck]</SD>
<L n="116"/><TLN n="411"/>Wear this for me, one out of suits with fortune,
<L n="117"/><TLN n="412"/>That could give more, but that her hand lacks means.
<SD t="whoto">[To Celia]</SD>
<L n="118"/><TLN n="413"/>Shall we go, coz?</S>

<L n="119"/><TLN n="414"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Ay. Fare you well, fair gentleman.</S>
<SD t="action">[Rosalind and Celia start to leave.]</SD>

<L n="120"/><TLN n="415"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[Aside]</SD>
Can I not say "I thank you"? My better parts
<L n="121"/><TLN n="416"/>Are all thrown down, and that which here stands up
<L n="122"/><TLN n="417"/>Is but a quintain, a mere lifeless block.</S>

<L n="123"/><TLN n="418"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Celia]</SD>
He calls us back. My pride fell with my fortunes;
<L n="124"/><TLN n="419"/>I'll ask him what he would. -- Did you call, sir?
<L n="125"/><TLN n="420"/>Sir, you have wrestled well, and overthrown
<L n="126"/><TLN n="421"/>More than your enemies.</S>

<L n="127"/><TLN n="422"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Will you go, coz?</S>

<L n="128"/><TLN n="423"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Have with you. -- Fare you well.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exit [with Celia].</SD>

<L n="129"/><TLN n="424"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
What passion hangs these weights upon my tongue?
<L n="130"/><TLN n="425"/>I cannot speak to her, yet she urged conference.

<TLN n="426"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Le Beau.</SD>

<L n="131"/><TLN n="427"/>O poor Orlando, thou art overthrown!
<L n="132"/><TLN n="428"/>Or Charles or something weaker masters thee.</S>

<L n="133"/><TLN n="429"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
Good sir, I do in friendship counsel you
<L n="134"/><TLN n="430"/>To leave this place. Albeit you have deserved
<L n="135"/><TLN n="431"/>High commendation, true applause, and love,
<L n="136"/><TLN n="432"/>Yet such is now the Duke's condition
<L n="137"/><TLN n="433"/>That he misconsters all that you have done.
<L n="138"/><TLN n="434"/>The Duke is humorous. What he is indeed
<L n="139"/><TLN n="435"/>More suits you to conceive than I to speak of.</S>

<L n="140"/><TLN n="436"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I thank you, sir. And pray you tell me this:
<L n="141"/><TLN n="437"/>Which of the two was daughter of the Duke
<L n="142"/><TLN n="438"/>That here was at the wrestling?</S>

<L n="143"/><TLN n="439"/><S><SP>Le Beau</SP>
Neither his daughter, if we judge by manners,
<L n="144"/><TLN n="440"/>But yet indeed the taller is his daughter.
<L n="145"/><TLN n="441"/>The other is daughter to the banished Duke,
<L n="146"/><TLN n="442"/>And here detained by her usurping uncle
<L n="147"/><TLN n="443"/>To keep his daughter company, whose loves
<L n="148"/><TLN n="444"/>Are dearer than the natural bond of sisters.
<L n="149"/><TLN n="445"/>But I can tell you that of late this Duke
<L n="150"/><TLN n="446"/>Hath ta'en displeasure 'gainst his gentle niece,
<L n="151"/><TLN n="447"/>Grounded upon no other argument
<L n="152"/><TLN n="448"/>But that the people praise her for her virtues
<L n="153"/><TLN n="449"/>And pity her for her good father's sake;
<L n="154"/><TLN n="450"/>And, on my life, his malice 'gainst the lady
<L n="155"/><TLN n="451"/>Will suddenly break forth. Sir, fare you well.
<L n="156"/><TLN n="452"/>Hereafter, in a better world than this,
<L n="157"/><TLN n="453"/>I shall desire more love and knowledge of you.</S>

<L n="158"/><TLN n="454"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I rest much bounden to you. Fare you well.
<SD t="exit">[Exit Le Beau.]</SD>

<L n="159"/><TLN n="455"/>Thus must I from the smoke into the smother;
<L n="160"/><TLN n="456"/>From tyrant Duke unto a tyrant brother.
<L n="161"/><TLN n="457"/>But heavenly Rosalind!</S>
<SD t="exit">Exit.</SD>

</MODE>
</SCENE>
<SCENE n="3">
<H2><TLN n="458"/>[1.3]</H2>
<TLN n="459"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Celia and Rosalind.</SD>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="1"/><TLN n="460"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Why, cousin, why, Rosalind! Cupid have mercy! <TLN n="461"/>Not a word?</S>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="462"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Not one to throw at a dog.</S>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="463"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
No, thy words are too precious to be cast away <TLN n="464"/>upon curs. Throw some of them at me. Come, lame me <TLN n="465"/>with reasons.</S>

<L n="4"/><TLN n="466"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Then there were two cousins laid up, when the <TLN n="467"/>one should be lamed with reasons and the other <TLN n="468"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->mad without any.</S>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="469"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
But is all this for your father?</S>

<L n="6"/><TLN n="470"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
No, some of it is for my child's father. Oh, <TLN n="471"/>how full of briers is this working-day world!</S>

<L n="7"/><TLN n="472"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
They are but burs, cousin, thrown upon thee <TLN n="473"/>in holiday foolery. If we walk not in the trodden paths, <TLN n="474"/>our very petticoats will catch them.</S>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="475"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I could shake them off my coat. These burs are <TLN n="476"/>in my heart.</S>

<L n="9"/><TLN n="477"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Hem them away.</S>

<L n="10"/><TLN n="478"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I would try, if I could cry "hem" and have him.</S>

<L n="11"/><TLN n="479"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Come, come, wrestle with thy affections.</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="480"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Oh, they take the part of a better wrestler than <TLN n="481"/>myself.</S>

<L n="13"/><TLN n="482"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Oh, a good wish upon you! You will try in time, <TLN n="483"/>in despite of a fall. But, turning these jests out of service, <TLN n="484"/>let us talk in good earnest. Is it possible, on such a sudden, <TLN n="485"/>you should fall into so strong a liking with old Sir <TLN n="486"/>Rowland's youngest son?</S>

<L n="14"/><TLN n="487"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
The Duke my father loved his father dearly.</S>

<L n="15"/><TLN n="488"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Doth it therefore ensue that you should love his <TLN n="489"/>son dearly? By this kind of chase, I should hate <TLN n="490"/>him, for my father hated his father dearly; yet I hate <TLN n="491"/>not Orlando.</S>

<L n="16"/><TLN n="492"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
No, faith, hate him not, for my sake.</S>

<L n="17"/><TLN n="493"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Why should I not? Doth he not deserve well?</S>

<TLN n="494"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Duke [Frederick], with Lords.</SD>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="495"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Let me love him for that, and do you love him <TLN n="496"/>because I do. Look, here comes the Duke.</S>

<L n="19"/><TLN n="497"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
With his eyes full of anger.</S>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="20"/><TLN n="498"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Rosalind]</SD>
Mistress, dispatch you with your safest haste,
<L n="21" part="i"/><TLN n="499"/>And get you from our court.</S>

<L n="21" part="m"/><TLN n="500"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Me, uncle?</S>

<L n="21" part="f"/><TLN n="501"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
You, cousin.
<L n="22"/><TLN n="502"/>Within these ten days if that thou be'st found
<L n="23"/><TLN n="503"/>So near our public court as twenty miles,
<L n="24" part="i"/><TLN n="504"/>Thou diest for it.</S>

<L n="24" part="f"/><TLN n="505"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I do beseech Your Grace,
<L n="25"/><TLN n="506"/>Let me the knowledge of my fault bear with me.
<L n="26"/><TLN n="507"/>If with myself I hold intelligence
<L n="27"/><TLN n="508"/>Or have acquaintance with mine own desires,
<L n="28"/><TLN n="509"/>If that I do not dream, or be not frantic --
<L n="29"/><TLN n="510"/>As I do trust I am not -- then, dear uncle,
<L n="30"/><TLN n="511"/>Never so much as in a thought unborn
<L n="31" part="i"/><TLN n="512"/>Did I offend Your Highness.</S>

<L n="31" part="f"/><TLN n="513"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
Thus do all traitors.
<L n="32"/><TLN n="514"/>If their purgation did consist in words,
<L n="33"/><TLN n="515"/>They are as innocent as grace itself.
<L n="34"/><TLN n="516"/>Let it suffice thee that I trust thee not.</S>

<L n="35"/><TLN n="517"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Yet your mistrust cannot make me a traitor.
<L n="36"/><TLN n="518"/>Tell me whereon the likelihood depends.</S>

<L n="37"/><TLN n="519"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
Thou art thy father's daughter; there's enough.</S>

<L n="38"/><TLN n="520"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
So was I when Your Highness took his dukedom;
<L n="39"/><TLN n="521"/>So was I when Your Highness banished him.
<L n="40"/><TLN n="522"/>Treason is not inherited, my lord;
<L n="41"/><TLN n="523"/>Or, if we did derive it from our friends,
<L n="42"/><TLN n="524"/>What's that to me? My father was no traitor.
<L n="43"/><TLN n="525"/>Then, good my liege, mistake me not so much
<L n="44"/><TLN n="526"/>To think my poverty is treacherous.</S>

<L n="45"/><TLN n="527"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Dear sovereign, hear me speak.</S>

<L n="46"/><TLN n="528"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
Ay, Celia, we stayed her for your sake,
<L n="47"/><TLN n="529"/>Else had she with her father ranged along.</S>

<L n="48"/><TLN n="530"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
I did not then entreat to have her stay;
<L n="49"/><TLN n="531"/>It was your pleasure, and your own remorse.
<L n="50"/><TLN n="532"/>I was too young that time to value her,
<L n="51"/><TLN n="533"/>But now I know her. If she be a traitor,
<L n="52"/><TLN n="534"/>Why so am I. We still have slept together,
<L n="53"/><TLN n="535"/>Rose at an instant, learned, played, eat together,
<L n="54"/><TLN n="536"/>And wheresoe'er we went, like Juno's swans
<L n="55"/><TLN n="537"/>Still we went coupled and inseparable.</S>

<L n="56"/><TLN n="538"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
She is too subtle for thee; and her smoothness,
<L n="57"/><TLN n="539"/>Her very silence and her patience,
<L n="58"/><TLN n="540"/>Speak to the people, and they pity her.
<L n="59"/><TLN n="541"/>Thou art a fool. She robs thee of thy name,
<L n="60"/><TLN n="542"/>And thou wilt show more bright and seem more virtuous
<L n="61"/><TLN n="543"/>When she is gone. Then open not thy lips.
<L n="62"/><TLN n="544"/>Firm and irrevocable is my doom
<L n="63"/><TLN n="545"/>Which I have passed upon her; she is banished.</S>

<L n="64"/><TLN n="546"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Pronounce that sentence, then, on me, my liege!
<L n="65"/><TLN n="547"/>I cannot live out of her company.</S>

<L n="66"/><TLN n="548"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
You are a fool. -- You, niece, provide yourself.
<L n="67"/><TLN n="549"/>If you outstay the time, upon mine honor,
<L n="68"/><TLN n="550"/>And in the greatness of my word, you die.</S>
<TLN n="551"/><SD t="exit">Exit Duke, &amp;c. [with Lords].</SD>

<L n="69"/><TLN n="552"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
O my poor Rosalind, whither wilt thou go?
<L n="70"/><TLN n="553"/>Wilt thou change fathers? I will give thee mine.
<L n="71"/><TLN n="554"/>I charge thee, be not thou more grieved than I am.</S>

<L n="72" part="i"/><TLN n="555"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I have more cause.</S>

<L n="72" part="f"/><TLN n="556"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Thou hast not, cousin.
<L n="73"/><TLN n="557"/>Prithee be cheerful. Know'st thou not the Duke
<L n="74" part="i"/><TLN n="558"/>Hath banished me, his daughter?</S>

<L n="74" part="f"/><TLN n="559"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
That he hath not.</S>

<L n="75"/><TLN n="560"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
No? "Hath not"? Rosalind lacks, then, the love
<L n="76"/><TLN n="561"/>Which teacheth thee that thou and I am one.
<L n="77"/><TLN n="562"/>Shall we be sundered? Shall we part, sweet girl?
<L n="78"/><TLN n="563"/>No; let my father seek another heir.
<L n="79"/><TLN n="564"/>Therefore devise with me how we may fly,
<L n="80"/><TLN n="565"/>Whither to go, and what to bear with us.
<L n="81"/><TLN n="566"/>And do not seek to take your change upon you,
<L n="82"/><TLN n="567"/>To bear your griefs yourself, and leave me out;
<L n="83"/><TLN n="568"/>For, by this heaven, now at our sorrows pale,
<L n="84"/><TLN n="569"/>Say what thou canst, I'll go along with thee.</S>

<L n="85"/><TLN n="570"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Why, whither shall we go?</S>

<L n="86"/><TLN n="571"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
To seek my uncle in the Forest of Arden.</S>

<L n="87"/><TLN n="572"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Alas, what danger will it be to us,
<L n="88"/><TLN n="573"/>Maids as we are, to travel forth so far!
<L n="89"/><TLN n="574"/>Beauty provoketh thieves sooner than gold.</S>

<L n="90"/><TLN n="575"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
I'll put myself in poor and mean attire,
<L n="91"/><TLN n="576"/>And with a kind of umber smirch my face;
<L n="92"/><TLN n="577"/>The like do you. So shall we pass along,
<L n="93" part="i"/><TLN n="578"/>And never stir assailants.</S>

<L n="93" part="f"/><TLN n="579"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Were it not better,
<L n="94"/><TLN n="580"/>Because that I am more than common tall,
<L n="95"/><TLN n="581"/>That I did suit me all points like a man?
<L n="96"/><TLN n="582"/>A gallant curtal-ax upon my thigh,
<L n="97"/><TLN n="583"/>A boar-spear in my hand, and -- in my heart
<L n="98"/><TLN n="584"/>Lie there what hidden woman's fear there will --
<L n="99"/><TLN n="585"/>We'll have a swashing and a martial outside,
<L n="100"/><TLN n="586"/>As many other mannish cowards have
<L n="101"/><TLN n="587"/>That do outface it with their semblances.</S>

<L n="102"/><TLN n="588"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
What shall I call thee when thou art a man?</S>

<L n="103"/><TLN n="589"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I'll have no worse a name than Jove's own page,
<L n="104"/><TLN n="590"/>And therefore look you call me Ganymede.
<L n="105"/><TLN n="591"/>But what will you be called?</S>

<L n="106"/><TLN n="592"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Something that hath a reference to my state:
<L n="107"/><TLN n="593"/>No longer Celia, but Aliena.</S>

<L n="108"/><TLN n="594"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
But, cousin, what if we assayed to steal
<L n="109"/><TLN n="595"/>The clownish fool out of your father's court?
<L n="110"/><TLN n="596"/>Would he not be a comfort to our travel?</S>

<L n="111"/><TLN n="597"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
He'll go along o'er the wide world with me.
<L n="112"/><TLN n="598"/>Leave me alone to woo him. Let's away,
<L n="113"/><TLN n="599"/>And get our jewels and our wealth together,
<L n="114"/><TLN n="600"/>Devise the fittest time and safest way
<L n="115"/><TLN n="601"/>To hide us from pursuit that will be made
<L n="116"/><TLN n="602"/>After my flight. Now go we in content
<L n="117"/><TLN n="603"/>To liberty, and not to banishment.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>

</SCENE>
</ACT>
<ACT n="2">
<SCENE n="1">
<H2><TLN n="604"/>[2.1]</H2>
<TLN n="605"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Duke Senior, Amiens, and two or three Lords, <TLN n="606"/>like foresters.</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="607"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Now, my co-mates and brothers in exile,
<L n="2"/><TLN n="608"/>Hath not old custom made this life more sweet
<L n="3"/><TLN n="609"/>Than that of painted pomp? Are not these woods
<L n="4"/><TLN n="610"/>More free from peril than the envious court?
<L n="5"/><TLN n="611"/>Here feel we not the penalty of Adam,
<L n="6"/><TLN n="612"/>The seasons' difference, as the icy fang
<L n="7"/><TLN n="613"/>And churlish chiding of the winter's wind,
<L n="8"/><TLN n="614"/>Which when it bites and blows upon my body
<L n="9"/><TLN n="615"/>Even till I shrink with cold, I smile and say
<L n="10"/><TLN n="616"/>"This is no flattery; these are counselors
<L n="11"/><TLN n="617"/>That feelingly persuade me what I am."
<L n="12"/><TLN n="618"/>Sweet are the uses of adversity,
<L n="13"/><TLN n="619"/>Which, like the toad, ugly and venomous,
<L n="14"/><TLN n="620"/>Wears yet a precious jewel in his head;
<L n="15"/><TLN n="621"/>And this our life, exempt from public haunt,
<L n="16"/><TLN n="622"/>Finds tongues in trees, books in the running brooks,
<L n="17"/><TLN n="623"/>Sermons in stones, and good in everything.</S>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="624"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
I would not change it. Happy is Your Grace,
<L n="19"/><TLN n="625"/>That can translate the stubbornness of fortune
<L n="20"/><TLN n="626"/>Into so quiet and so sweet a style.</S>

<L n="21"/><TLN n="627"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Come, shall we go and kill us venison?
<L n="22"/><TLN n="628"/>And yet it irks me the poor dappled fools,
<L n="23"/><TLN n="629"/>Being native burghers of this desert city,
<L n="24"/><TLN n="630"/>Should in their own confines with fork{`e}d heads
<L n="25" part="i"/><TLN n="631"/>Have their round haunches gored.</S>

<L n="25" part="f"/><TLN n="632"/><S><SP>First Lord</SP>
Indeed, my lord,
<L n="26"/><TLN n="633"/>The melancholy Jaques grieves at that,
<L n="27"/><TLN n="634"/>And in that kind swears you do more usurp
<L n="28"/><TLN n="635"/>Than doth your brother that hath banished you.
<L n="29"/><TLN n="636"/>Today my Lord of Amiens and myself
<L n="30"/><TLN n="637"/>Did steal behind him as he lay along
<L n="31"/><TLN n="638"/>Under an oak whose antique root peeps out
<L n="32"/><TLN n="639"/>Upon the brook that brawls along this wood,
<L n="33"/><TLN n="640"/>To the which place a poor sequestered stag
<L n="34"/><TLN n="641"/>That from the hunter's aim had ta'en a hurt
<L n="35"/><TLN n="642"/>Did come to languish. And indeed, my lord,
<L n="36"/><TLN n="643"/>The wretched animal heaved forth such groans
<L n="37"/><TLN n="644"/>That their discharge did stretch his leathern coat
<L n="38"/><TLN n="645"/>Almost to bursting, and the big round tears
<L n="39"/><TLN n="646"/>Coursed one another down his innocent nose
<L n="40"/><TLN n="647"/>In piteous chase. And thus the hairy fool,
<L n="41"/><TLN n="648"/>Much mark{`e}d of the melancholy Jaques,
<L n="42"/><TLN n="649"/>Stood on th'extremest verge of the swift brook,
<L n="43" part="i"/><TLN n="650"/>Augmenting it with tears.</S>

<L n="43" part="f"/><TLN n="651"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
But what said Jaques?
<L n="44"/><TLN n="652"/>Did he not moralize this spectacle?</S>

<L n="45"/><TLN n="653"/><S><SP>First Lord</SP>
Oh, yes, into a thousand similes.
<L n="46"/><TLN n="654"/>First, for his weeping into the needless stream:
<L n="47"/><TLN n="655"/>"Poor deer," quoth he, "thou mak'st a testament
<L n="48"/><TLN n="656"/>As worldlings do, giving thy sum of more
<L n="49"/><TLN n="657"/>To that which had too much." Then, being there alone,
<L n="50"/><TLN n="658"/>Left and abandoned of his velvet friends:
<L n="51"/><TLN n="659"/>"'Tis right," quoth he, "thus misery doth part
<L n="52"/><TLN n="660"/>The flux of company." Anon, a careless herd,
<L n="53"/><TLN n="661"/>Full of the pasture, jumps along by him
<L n="54"/><TLN n="662"/>And never stays to greet him. "Ay," quoth Jaques,
<L n="55"/><TLN n="663"/>"Sweep on, you fat and greasy citizens;
<L n="56"/><TLN n="664"/>'Tis just the fashion. Wherefore do you look
<L n="57"/><TLN n="665"/>Upon that poor and broken bankrupt there?"
<L n="58"/><TLN n="666"/>Thus most invectively he pierceth through
<L n="59"/><TLN n="667"/>The body of the country, city, court,
<L n="60"/><TLN n="668"/>Yea, and of this our life, swearing that we
<L n="61"/><TLN n="669"/>Are mere usurpers, tyrants, and what's worse,
<L n="62"/><TLN n="670"/>To fright the animals and to kill them up
<L n="63"/><TLN n="671"/>In their assigned and native dwelling place.</S>

<L n="64"/><TLN n="672"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
And did you leave him in this contemplation?</S>

<L n="65"/><TLN n="673"/><S><SP>Second Lord</SP>
We did, my lord, weeping and commenting
<L n="66" part="i"/><TLN n="674"/>Upon the sobbing deer.</S>

<L n="66" part="f"/><TLN n="675"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Show me the place.
<L n="67"/><TLN n="676"/>I love to cope him in these sullen fits,
<L n="68"/><TLN n="677"/>For then he's full of matter.</S>

<L n="69"/><TLN n="678"/><S><SP>First Lord</SP>
I'll bring you to him straight.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="2">
<H2><TLN n="679"/>[2.2]</H2>
<TLN n="680"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Duke [Frederick], with Lords.</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="681"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
Can it be possible that no man saw them?
<L n="2"/><TLN n="682"/>It cannot be. Some villains of my court
<L n="3"/><TLN n="683"/>Are of consent and sufferance in this.</S>

<L n="4"/><TLN n="684"/><S><SP>First Lord</SP>
I cannot hear of any that did see her.
<L n="5"/><TLN n="685"/>The ladies, her attendants of her chamber,
<L n="6"/><TLN n="686"/>Saw her abed, and in the morning early
<L n="7"/><TLN n="687"/>They found the bed untreasured of their mistress.</S>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="688"/><S><SP>Second Lord</SP>
My lord, the roinish clown, at whom so oft
<L n="9"/><TLN n="689"/>Your Grace was wont to laugh, is also missing.
<L n="10"/><TLN n="690"/>Hisperia, the princess' gentlewoman,
<L n="11"/><TLN n="691"/>Confesses that she secretly o'erheard
<L n="12"/><TLN n="692"/>Your daughter and her cousin much commend
<L n="13"/><TLN n="693"/>The parts and graces of the wrestler
<L n="14"/><TLN n="694"/>That did but lately foil the sinewy Charles,
<L n="15"/><TLN n="695"/>And she believes, wherever they are gone,
<L n="16"/><TLN n="696"/>That youth is surely in their company.</S>

<L n="17"/><TLN n="697"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
Send to his brother; fetch that gallant hither.
<L n="18"/><TLN n="698"/>If he be absent, bring his brother to me;
<L n="19"/><TLN n="699"/>I'll make him find him. Do this suddenly,
<L n="20"/><TLN n="700"/>And let not search and inquisition quail
<L n="21"/><TLN n="701"/>To bring again these foolish runaways.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="3">
<H2><TLN n="702"/>[2.3]</H2>
<TLN n="703"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Orlando and Adam,[ meeting].</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="704"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Who's there?</S>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="705"/><S><SP>Adam</SP>
What, my young master? Oh, my gentle master!
<L n="3"/><TLN n="706"/>Oh, my sweet master, oh, you memory
<L n="4"/><TLN n="707"/>Of old Sir Rowland! Why, what make you here?
<L n="5"/><TLN n="708"/>Why are you virtuous? Why do people love you?
<L n="6"/><TLN n="709"/>And wherefore are you gentle, strong, and valiant?
<L n="7"/><TLN n="710"/>Why would you be so fond to overcome
<L n="8"/><TLN n="711"/>The bonny prizer of the humorous Duke?
<L n="9"/><TLN n="712"/>Your praise is come too swiftly home before you.
<L n="10"/><TLN n="713"/>Know you not, master, to some kind of men
<L n="11"/><TLN n="714"/>Their graces serve them but as enemies?
<L n="12"/><TLN n="715"/>No more do yours. Your virtues, gentle master,
<L n="13"/><TLN n="716"/>Are sanctified and holy traitors to you.
<L n="14"/><TLN n="717"/>Oh, what a world is this, when what is comely
<L n="15"/><TLN n="718"/>Envenoms him that bears it!</S>

<L n="16" part="i"/><TLN n="719"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Why, what's the matter?</S>

<L n="16" part="f"/><TLN n="720"/><S><SP>Adam</SP>
O unhappy youth,
<L n="17"/><TLN n="721"/>Come not within these doors! Within this roof
<L n="18"/><TLN n="722"/>The enemy of all your graces lives.
<L n="19"/><TLN n="723"/>Your brother -- no, no brother; yet the son --
<L n="20"/><TLN n="724"/>Yet not the son; I will not call him son
<L n="21"/><TLN n="725"/>Of him I was about to call his father --
<L n="22"/><TLN n="726"/>Hath heard your praises, and this night he means
<L n="23"/><TLN n="727"/>To burn the lodging where you use to lie,
<L n="24"/><TLN n="728"/>And you within it. If he fail of that,
<L n="25"/><TLN n="729"/>He will have other means to cut you off.
<L n="26"/><TLN n="730"/>I overheard him and his practices.
<L n="27"/><TLN n="731"/>This is no place; this house is but a butchery.
<L n="28"/><TLN n="732"/>Abhor it, fear it, do not enter it.</S>

<L n="29"/><TLN n="733"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Why, whither, Adam, wouldst thou have me go?</S>

<L n="30"/><TLN n="734"/><S><SP>Adam</SP>
No matter whither, so you come not here.</S>

<L n="31"/><TLN n="735"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
What, wouldst thou have me go and beg my food,
<L n="32"/><TLN n="736"/>Or with a base and boist'rous sword enforce
<L n="33"/><TLN n="737"/>A thievish living on the common road?
<L n="34"/><TLN n="738"/>This I must do, or know not what to do;
<L n="35"/><TLN n="739"/>Yet this I will not do, do how I can.
<L n="36"/><TLN n="740"/>I rather will subject me to the malice
<L n="37"/><TLN n="741"/>Of a diverted blood and bloody brother.</S>

<L n="38"/><TLN n="742"/><S><SP>Adam</SP>
But do not so. I have five hundred crowns,
<L n="39"/><TLN n="743"/>The thrifty hire I saved under your father,
<L n="40"/><TLN n="744"/>Which I did store to be my foster nurse
<L n="41"/><TLN n="745"/>When service should in my old limbs lie lame
<L n="42"/><TLN n="746"/>And unregarded age in corners thrown.
<L n="43"/><TLN n="747"/>Take that, and He that doth the ravens feed,
<L n="44"/><TLN n="748"/>Yea, providently caters for the sparrow,
<L n="45"/><TLN n="749"/>Be comfort to my age! Here is the gold;
<SD t="action">[Offering money]</SD>
<L n="46"/><TLN n="750"/>All this I give you. Let me be your servant.
<L n="47"/><TLN n="751"/>Though I look old, yet I am strong and lusty,
<L n="48"/><TLN n="752"/>For in my youth I never did apply
<L n="49"/><TLN n="753"/>Hot and rebellious liquors in my blood,
<L n="50"/><TLN n="754"/>Nor did not with unbashful forehead woo
<L n="51"/><TLN n="755"/>The means of weakness and debility;
<L n="52"/><TLN n="756"/>Therefore my age is as a lusty winter,
<L n="53"/><TLN n="757"/>Frosty, but kindly. Let me go with you;
<L n="54"/><TLN n="758"/>I'll do the service of a younger man
<L n="55"/><TLN n="759"/>In all your business and necessities.</S>

<L n="56"/><TLN n="760"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Oh, good old man, how well in thee appears
<L n="57"/><TLN n="761"/>The constant service of the antique world,
<L n="58"/><TLN n="762"/>When service sweat for duty, not for meed!
<L n="59"/><TLN n="763"/>Thou art not for the fashion of these times,
<L n="60"/><TLN n="764"/>Where none will sweat but for promotion,
<L n="61"/><TLN n="765"/>And having that do choke their service up
<L n="62"/><TLN n="766"/>Even with the having. It is not so with thee.
<L n="63"/><TLN n="767"/>But, poor old man, thou prun'st a rotten tree
<L n="64"/><TLN n="768"/>That cannot so much as a blossom yield
<L n="65"/><TLN n="769"/>In lieu of all thy pains and husbandry.
<L n="66"/><TLN n="770"/>But come thy ways. We'll go along together,
<L n="67"/><TLN n="771"/>And ere we have thy youthful wages spent
<L n="68"/><TLN n="772"/>We'll light upon some settled low content.</S>

<L n="69"/><TLN n="773"/><S><SP>Adam</SP>
Master, go on, and I will follow thee
<L n="70"/><TLN n="774"/>To the last gasp, with truth and loyalty.
<L n="71"/><TLN n="775"/>From seventeen years till now almost fourscore
<L n="72"/><TLN n="776"/>Here liv{`e}d I, but now live here no more.
<L n="73"/><TLN n="777"/>At seventeen years many their fortunes seek,
<L n="74"/><TLN n="778"/>But at fourscore it is too late a week;
<L n="75"/><TLN n="779"/>Yet fortune cannot recompense me better
<L n="76"/><TLN n="780"/>Than to die well and not my master's debtor.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>
</MODE>
</SCENE>
<SCENE n="4">
<H2><TLN n="781"/>[2.4]</H2>
<TLN n="782"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Rosalind for Ganymede, Celia for Aliena, and <TLN n="783"/>Clown, alias Touchstone.</SD>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="1"/><TLN n="784"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Oh, Jupiter, how weary are my spirits!</S>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="785"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
I care not for my spirits, if my legs were not <TLN n="786"/>weary.</S>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="787"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I could find in my heart to disgrace my man's <TLN n="788"/>apparel and to cry like a woman; but I must comfort <TLN n="789"/>the weaker vessel, as doublet and hose ought to show itself <TLN n="790"/>courageous to petticoat. Therefore, courage, good <TLN n="791"/>Aliena!</S>

<L n="4"/><TLN n="792"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
I pray you, bear with me; I cannot go no further.<TLN n="793"/><!--TLN moved +1 --></S>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="794"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
For my part, I had rather bear with you than <TLN n="795"/>bear you; yet I should bear no cross if I did bear <TLN n="796"/>you, for I think you have no money in your purse.</S>

<L n="6"/><TLN n="797"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Well, this is the Forest of Arden.</S>

<L n="7"/><TLN n="798"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Ay, now am I in Arden; the more fool I. When I <TLN n="799"/>was at home I was in a better place, but travelers must <TLN n="800"/>be content.</S>

<TLN n="801"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Corin and Silvius.</SD>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="802"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Ay, be so, good Touchstone. -- Look you, who comes <TLN n="803"/>here, a young man and an old in solemn talk.</S>
</MODE>
<SD t="action">[They stand aside and listen.]</SD>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="9"/><TLN n="804"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Silvius]</SD>
That is the way to make her scorn you still.</S>

<L n="10"/><TLN n="805"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
Oh, Corin, that thou knew'st how I do love her!</S>

<L n="11"/><TLN n="806"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
I partly guess; for I have loved ere now.</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="807"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
No, Corin, being old, thou canst not guess,
<L n="13"/><TLN n="808"/>Though in thy youth thou wast as true a lover
<L n="14"/><TLN n="809"/>As ever sighed upon a midnight pillow.
<L n="15"/><TLN n="810"/>But if thy love were ever like to mine --
<L n="16"/><TLN n="811"/>As sure I think did never man love so --
<L n="17"/><TLN n="812"/>How many actions most ridiculous
<L n="18"/><TLN n="813"/>Hast thou been drawn to by thy fantasy?</S>

<L n="19"/><TLN n="814"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Into a thousand that I have forgotten.</S>

<L n="20"/><TLN n="815"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
Oh, thou didst then never love so heartily!
<L n="21"/><TLN n="816"/>If thou rememb'rest not the slightest folly
<L n="22"/><TLN n="817"/>That ever love did make thee run into,
<L n="23"/><TLN n="818"/>Thou hast not loved.
<L n="24"/><TLN n="819"/>Or if thou hast not sat as I do now,
<L n="25"/><TLN n="820"/>Wearing thy hearer in thy mistress' praise,
<L n="26"/><TLN n="821"/>Thou hast not loved.
<L n="27"/><TLN n="822"/>Or if thou hast not broke from company
<L n="28"/><TLN n="823"/>Abruptly, as my passion now makes me,
<L n="29"/><TLN n="824"/>Thou hast not loved.
<L n="30"/><TLN n="825"/>O Phoebe, Phoebe, Phoebe!</S>
<SD t="exit">Exit Silvius</SD>

<L n="31"/><TLN n="826"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Alas, poor shepherd! Searching of thy wound,
<L n="32"/><TLN n="827"/>I have by hard adventure found mine own.</S>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="33"/><TLN n="828"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
And I mine. I remember, when I was in love, <TLN n="829"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->I broke my sword upon a stone, and bid him take that for <TLN n="830"/>coming a-night to Jane Smile; and I remember the kissing <TLN n="831"/>of her batler, and the cow's dugs that her pretty <TLN n="832"/>chapped hands had milked; and I remember the <TLN n="833"/>wooing of a peascod instead of her, from whom I took two <TLN n="834"/>cods, and giving her them again, said with weeping <TLN n="835"/>tears, "Wear these for my sake." We that are true lovers <TLN n="836"/>run into strange capers; but as all is mortal in <TLN n="837"/>nature, so is all nature in love mortal in folly.</S>

<L n="34"/><TLN n="838"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Thou speak'st wiser than thou art ware of.</S>

<L n="35"/><TLN n="839"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Nay, I shall ne'er be ware of mine own wit till <TLN n="840"/>I break my shins against it.</S>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="36"/><TLN n="841"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Jove, Jove! This shepherd's passion
<L n="37"/><TLN n="842"/>Is much upon my fashion.</S>

<L n="38"/><TLN n="843"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
And mine; but it grows something stale with <TLN n="844"/>me.</S>

<L n="39"/><TLN n="845"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
I pray you, one of you question yond man
<L n="40"/><TLN n="846"/>If he for gold will give us any food.
<L n="41" part="i"/><TLN n="847"/>I faint almost to death.</S>

<L n="41" part="f"/><TLN n="848"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Corin]</SD>
Holla, you clown!</S>

<L n="42" part="i"/><TLN n="849"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Peace, fool! He's not thy kinsman.</S>

<L n="42" part="f"/><TLN n="850"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Who calls?</S>

<L n="43" part="i"/><TLN n="851"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Your betters, sir.</S>

<L n="43" part="f"/><TLN n="852"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Else are they very wretched.</S>

<L n="44"/><TLN n="853"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Peace, I say. -- Good even to you, friend.</S>

<L n="45"/><TLN n="854"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
And to you, gentle sir, and to you all.</S>

<L n="46"/><TLN n="855"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I prithee, shepherd, if that love or gold
<L n="47"/><TLN n="856"/>Can in this desert place buy entertainment,
<L n="48"/><TLN n="857"/>Bring us where we may rest ourselves and feed.
<L n="49"/><TLN n="858"/>Here's a young maid with travel much oppressed,
<L n="50" part="i"/><TLN n="859"/>And faints for succor.</S>

<L n="50" part="f"/><TLN n="860"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Fair sir, I pity her,
<L n="51"/><TLN n="861"/>And wish, for her sake more than for mine own,
<L n="52"/><TLN n="862"/>My fortunes were more able to relieve her;
<L n="53"/><TLN n="863"/>But I am shepherd to another man,
<L n="54"/><TLN n="864"/>And do not shear the fleeces that I graze.
<L n="55"/><TLN n="865"/>My master is of churlish disposition,
<L n="56"/><TLN n="866"/>And little recks to find the way to heaven
<L n="57"/><TLN n="867"/>By doing deeds of hospitality.
<L n="58"/><TLN n="868"/>Besides, his cote, his flocks, and bounds of feed
<L n="59"/><TLN n="869"/>Are now on sale, and at our sheepcote now,
<L n="60"/><TLN n="870"/>By reason of his absence, there is nothing
<L n="61"/><TLN n="871"/>That you will feed on. But what is, come see,
<L n="62"/><TLN n="872"/>And in my voice most welcome shall you be.</S>

<L n="63"/><TLN n="873"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
What is he that shall buy his flock and pasture?</S>

<L n="64"/><TLN n="874"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
That young swain that you saw here <TLN n="875"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->but erewhile,
<L n="65"/><TLN n="876"/>That little cares for buying anything.</S>

<L n="66"/><TLN n="877"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I pray thee, if it stand with honesty,
<L n="67"/><TLN n="878"/>Buy thou the cottage, pasture, and the flock,
<L n="68"/><TLN n="879"/>And thou shalt have to pay for it of us.</S>

<L n="69"/><TLN n="880"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
And we will mend thy wages. <TLN n="881"/>I like this place,
<L n="70"/>And willingly could <TLN n="882"/>waste my time in it.</S>

<L n="71"/><TLN n="883"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Assuredly the thing is to be sold.
<L n="72"/><TLN n="884"/>Go with me. If you like upon report
<L n="73"/><TLN n="885"/>The soil, the profit, and this kind of life,
<L n="74"/><TLN n="886"/>I will your very faithful feeder be,
<L n="75"/><TLN n="887"/>And buy it with your gold right suddenly.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="5">
<H2><TLN n="888"/>[2.5]</H2>
<TLN n="889"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Amiens, Jaques, and others.</SD>
<SD t="action">[A table is set out.]</SD>
<TLN n="890"/><LD>Song</LD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="891"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
<SD t="sound">[Sings]</SD>
<VERSEQUOTE>
Under the greenwood tree
<L n="2"/><TLN n="892"/>Who loves to lie with me,
<L n="3"/><TLN n="893"/>And turn his merry note
<L n="4"/><TLN n="894"/>Unto the sweet bird's throat,
<L n="5"/><TLN n="895"/>Come hither, come hither, come hither.
<L n="6"/><TLN n="896"/><SPACE n="3"/>Here shall he see
<L n="7"/><SPACE n="3"/>No enemy
<L n="8"/><TLN n="897"/>But winter and rough weather.</S>
</VERSEQUOTE>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="9"/><TLN n="898"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
More, more, I prithee, more.</S>

<L n="10"/><TLN n="899"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
It will make you melancholy, Monsieur Jaques.</S>

<L n="11"/><TLN n="900"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
I thank it. More, I prithee, more. <TLN n="901"/>I can suck melancholy out of a song <TLN n="902"/>as a weasel sucks eggs. More, I prithee, more.</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="903"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
My voice is ragged. I know I cannot please<TLN n="904"/> you.</S>

<L n="13"/><TLN n="905"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
I do not desire you to please me, <TLN n="906"/>I do desire you to sing. <TLN n="907"/>Come, more; another stanzo. Call you 'em "stanzos"?</S>

<L n="14"/><TLN n="908"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
What you will, Monsieur Jaques.</S>

<L n="15"/><TLN n="909"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Nay, I care not for their names; they owe me <TLN n="910"/>nothing. Will you sing?</S>

<L n="16"/><TLN n="911"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
More at your request than to please myself.</S>

<L n="17"/><TLN n="912"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Well then, if ever I thank any man, I'll thank <TLN n="913"/>you. But that they call "compliment" is like th'encounter <TLN n="914"/>of two dog-apes; and when a man thanks me heartily, <TLN n="915"/>methinks I have given him a penny, and he renders me <TLN n="916"/>the beggarly thanks. Come, sing; and you that will not, <TLN n="917"/>hold your tongues.</S>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="918"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
Well, I'll end the song. -- Sirs, cover the while; <TLN n="919"/>the Duke will drink under this tree. -- He hath been all this <TLN n="920"/>day to look you.</S>
<SD t="setting">[Food and drink are set out.]</SD>

<L n="19"/><TLN n="921"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
And I have been all this day to avoid him. <TLN n="922"/>He is too disputable for my company. <TLN n="923"/>I think of as many matters as he, but I give <TLN n="924"/>heaven thanks and make no boast of them. <TLN n="925"/>Come, warble, come.</S>

<TLN n="926"/><LD>Song</LD>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">
<VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="20"/><TLN n="927"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
<SD t="sound">[Sings]</SD>
Who doth ambition shun,
<L n="21"/><TLN n="928"/>And loves to live i'th' sun,
<L n="22"/><TLN n="929"/>Seeking the food he eats,
<L n="23"/><TLN n="930"/>And pleased with what he gets,
<SD t="sound">All together here</SD>
<L n="24"/><TLN n="931"/>Come hither, come hither, come hither.
<L n="25"/><TLN n="932"/><SPACE n="3"/>Here shall he see
<L n="26"/><SPACE n="3"/>No enemy
<L n="27"/>But winter and rough weather.</S>
</VERSEQUOTE>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="28"/><TLN n="933"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
I'll give you a verse to this note <TLN n="934"/>that I made yesterday in despite of my invention.</S>

<L n="29"/><TLN n="935"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
And I'll sing it.</S>

<L n="30"/><TLN n="936"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Thus it goes:
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">
<VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="31"/><TLN n="937"/>If it do come to pass
<L n="32"/>That any man turn ass,
<L n="33"/><TLN n="938"/>Leaving his wealth and ease
<L n="34"/><TLN n="939"/>A stubborn will to please,
<L n="35"/><TLN n="940"/>Ducdame, ducdame, ducdame.
<L n="36"/><TLN n="941"/><SPACE n="3"/>Here shall he see
<L n="37"/><SPACE n="3"/>Gross fools as he,
<L n="38"/><TLN n="942"/>An if he will come to me.</S>
</VERSEQUOTE>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="39"/><TLN n="943"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
What's that "ducdame"?</S>

<L n="40"/><TLN n="944"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
'Tis a Greek invocation, to call fools into a circle. <TLN n="945"/>I'll go sleep, if I can; if I cannot, I'll rail against all <TLN n="946"/>the first-born of Egypt.</S>

<L n="41"/><TLN n="947"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
And I'll go seek the Duke. <TLN n="948"/>His banquet is prepared.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt [separately].</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="6">
<H2><TLN n="949"/>[2.6]</H2>
<TLN n="950"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Orlando and Adam.</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="951"/><S><SP>Adam</SP>
Dear master, I can go no further. <TLN n="952"/>Oh, I die for food! Here lie I down, <TLN n="953"/>and measure out my grave. Farewell, kind master.</S>
<SD t="action">[He lies down.]</SD>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="954"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Why, how now, Adam? No greater heart in thee? <TLN n="955"/>Live a little, comfort a little, cheer thyself a little. <TLN n="956"/>If this uncouth forest yield anything savage, <TLN n="957"/>I will either be food for it or bring it for food to thee. <TLN n="958"/>Thy conceit is nearer death than thy powers. <TLN n="959"/>For my sake be comfortable; hold death awhile <TLN n="960"/>at the arm's end. I will here be with thee presently, <TLN n="961"/>and if I bring thee not something to eat, <TLN n="962"/>I will give thee leave to die; but if thou diest <TLN n="963"/>before I come, thou art a mocker of my labor. <TLN n="964"/>Well said! Thou look'st cheerly, <TLN n="965"/>and I'll be with thee quickly. Yet thou liest <TLN n="966"/>in the bleak air. Come, I will bear thee <TLN n="967"/>to some shelter; and thou shalt not die <TLN n="968"/>for lack of a dinner, <TLN n="969"/>if there live anything in this desert.
<SD t="action">[He picks up Adam.]</SD>
<TLN n="970"/>Cheerly, good Adam!</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="7">
<H2><TLN n="971"/>[2.7]</H2>
<TLN n="972"/><SD t="entrance"> Enter Duke Senior, [Amiens], and Lords, like outlaws</SD>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="1"/><TLN n="973"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
I think he be transformed into a beast,
<L n="2"/><TLN n="974"/>For I can nowhere find him like a man.</S>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="975"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
My lord, he is but even now gone hence.
<L n="4"/><TLN n="976"/>Here was he merry, hearing of a song.</S>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="977"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
If he, compact of jars, grow musical,
<L n="6"/><TLN n="978"/>We shall have shortly discord in the spheres.
<L n="7"/><TLN n="979"/>Go seek him. Tell him I would speak with him.</S>

<TLN n="980"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Jaques.</SD>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="981"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
He saves my labor by his own approach.</S>

<L n="9"/><TLN n="982"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Why, how now, monsieur, what a life is this,
<L n="10"/><TLN n="983"/>That your poor friends must woo your company?
<L n="11"/><TLN n="984"/>What, you look merrily.</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="985"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
A fool, a fool! I met a fool i'th'forest,
<L n="13"/><TLN n="986"/>A motley fool. A miserable world!
<L n="14"/><TLN n="987"/>As I do live by food, I met a fool,
<L n="15"/><TLN n="988"/>Who laid him down and basked him in the sun,
<L n="16"/><TLN n="989"/>And railed on Lady Fortune in good terms,
<L n="17"/><TLN n="990"/>In good set terms, and yet a motley fool.
<L n="18"/><TLN n="991"/>"Good morrow, fool," quoth I; "No, sir," quoth he,
<L n="19"/><TLN n="992"/>"Call me not fool till heaven hath sent me fortune."
<L n="20"/><TLN n="993"/>And then he drew a dial from his poke,
<L n="21"/><TLN n="994"/>And, looking on it with lack-luster eye,
<L n="22"/><TLN n="995"/>Says very wisely, "It is ten o'clock.
<L n="23"/><TLN n="996"/>Thus we may see," quoth he, "how the world wags:
<L n="24"/><TLN n="997"/>'Tis but an hour ago since it was nine,
<L n="25"/><TLN n="998"/>And after one hour more 'twill be eleven;
<L n="26"/><TLN n="999"/>And so, from hour to hour, we ripe and ripe,
<L n="27"/><TLN n="1000"/>And then, from hour to hour, we rot and rot,
<L n="28"/><TLN n="1001"/>And thereby hangs a tale." When I did hear
<L n="29"/><TLN n="1002"/>The motley fool thus moral on the time,
<L n="30"/><TLN n="1003"/>My lungs began to crow like Chanticleer
<L n="31"/><TLN n="1004"/>That fools should be so deep-contemplative,
<L n="32"/><TLN n="1005"/>And I did laugh sans intermission
<L n="33"/><TLN n="1006"/>An hour by his dial. Oh, noble fool!
<L n="34"/><TLN n="1007"/>A worthy fool! Motley's the only wear.</S>

<L n="35"/><TLN n="1008"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
What fool is this?</S>

<L n="36"/><TLN n="1009"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Oh, worthy fool! One that hath been a courtier,
<L n="37"/><TLN n="1010"/>And says, if ladies be but young and fair,
<L n="38"/><TLN n="1011"/>They have the gift to know it. And in his brain,
<L n="39"/><TLN n="1012"/>Which is as dry as the remainder biscuit
<L n="40"/><TLN n="1013"/>After a voyage, he hath strange places crammed
<L n="41"/><TLN n="1014"/>With observation, the which he vents
<L n="42"/><TLN n="1015"/>In mangled forms. Oh, that I were a fool!
<L n="43"/><TLN n="1016"/>I am ambitious for a motley coat.</S>

<L n="44" part="i"/><TLN n="1017"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Thou shalt have one.</S>

<L n="44" part="f"/><TLN n="1018"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
It is my only suit,
<L n="45"/><TLN n="1019"/>Provided that you weed your better judgments
<L n="46"/><TLN n="1020"/>Of all opinion that grows rank in them
<L n="47"/><TLN n="1021"/>That I am wise. I must have liberty
<L n="48"/><TLN n="1022"/>Withal, as large a charter as the wind,
<L n="49"/><TLN n="1023"/>To blow on whom I please, for so fools have.
<L n="50"/><TLN n="1024"/>And they that are most gall{`e}d with my folly,
<L n="51"/><TLN n="1025"/>They most must laugh. And why, sir, must they so?
<L n="52"/><TLN n="1026"/>The "why" is plain as way to parish church:
<L n="53"/><TLN n="1027"/>He that a fool doth very wisely hit
<L n="54"/><TLN n="1028"/>Doth very foolishly, although he smart,
<L n="55"/><TLN n="1029"/>Not to seem senseless of the bob; if not,
<L n="56"/><TLN n="1030"/>The wise man's folly is anatomized
<L n="57"/><TLN n="1031"/>Even by the squand'ring glances of the fool.
<L n="58"/><TLN n="1032"/>Invest me in my motley; give me leave
<L n="59"/><TLN n="1033"/>To speak my mind, and I will through and through
<L n="60"/><TLN n="1034"/>Cleanse the foul body of th'infected world,
<L n="61"/><TLN n="1035"/>If they will patiently receive my medicine.</S>

<L n="62"/><TLN n="1036"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Fie on thee! I can tell what thou wouldst do.</S>

<L n="63"/><TLN n="1037"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
What, for a counter, would I do but good?</S>

<L n="64"/><TLN n="1038"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Most mischievous foul sin, in chiding sin.
<L n="65"/><TLN n="1039"/>For thou thyself hast been a libertine,
<L n="66"/><TLN n="1040"/>As sensual as the brutish sting itself;
<L n="67"/><TLN n="1041"/>And all th'emboss{`e}d sores and headed evils
<L n="68"/><TLN n="1042"/>That thou with license of free foot hast caught
<L n="69"/><TLN n="1043"/>Wouldst thou disgorge into the general world.</S>

<L n="70"/><TLN n="1044"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Why, who cries out on pride
<L n="71"/><TLN n="1045"/>That can therein tax any private party?
<L n="72"/><TLN n="1046"/>Doth it not flow as hugely as the sea,
<L n="73"/><TLN n="1047"/>Till that the weary very means do ebb?
<L n="74"/><TLN n="1048"/>What woman in the city do I name
<L n="75"/><TLN n="1049"/>When that I say the city woman bears
<L n="76"/><TLN n="1050"/>The cost of princes on unworthy shoulders?
<L n="77"/><TLN n="1051"/>Who can come in and say that I mean her,
<L n="78"/><TLN n="1052"/>When such a one as she, such is her neighbor?
<L n="79"/><TLN n="1053"/>Or what is he of basest function
<L n="80"/><TLN n="1054"/>That says his bravery is not on my cost,
<L n="81"/><TLN n="1055"/>Thinking that I mean him, but therein suits
<L n="82"/><TLN n="1056"/>His folly to the mettle of my speech?
<L n="83"/><TLN n="1057"/>There then, how then? What then? Let me see wherein
<L n="84"/><TLN n="1058"/>My tongue hath wronged him: if it do him right,
<L n="85"/><TLN n="1059"/>Then he hath wronged himself; if he be free,
<L n="86"/><TLN n="1060"/>Why then my taxing like a wild goose flies,
<L n="87"/><TLN n="1061"/>Unclaimed of any man. But who come here?</S>

<TLN n="1062"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Orlando [with his sword drawn].</SD>

<L n="88"/><TLN n="1063"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Forbear, and eat no more!</S>

<L n="89"/><TLN n="1064"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Why, I have eat none yet.</S>

<L n="90"/><TLN n="1065"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Nor shalt not, till necessity be served.</S>

<L n="91"/><TLN n="1066"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Of what kind should this cock come of?</S>

<L n="92"/><TLN n="1067"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando]</SD>
Art thou thus boldened, man, by thy distress?
<L n="93"/><TLN n="1068"/>Or else a rude despiser of good manners,
<L n="94"/><TLN n="1069"/>That in civility thou seem'st so empty?</S>

<L n="95"/><TLN n="1070"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
You touched my vein at first. The thorny point
<L n="96"/><TLN n="1071"/>Of bare distress hath ta'en from me the show
<L n="97"/><TLN n="1072"/>Of smooth civility; yet am I inland bred,
<L n="98"/><TLN n="1073"/>And know some nurture. But forbear, I say.
<L n="99"/><TLN n="1074"/>He dies that touches any of this fruit
<L n="100"/><TLN n="1075"/>Till I and my affairs are answer{`e}d.</S>

<L n="101"/><TLN n="1076"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
An you will not be answered with reason, <TLN n="1077"/>I must die.</S>

<L n="102"/><TLN n="1078"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
What would you have? <TLN n="1079"/>Your gentleness shall force
<L n="103"/>More than your force <TLN n="1080"/>move us to gentleness.</S>

<L n="104"/><TLN n="1081"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I almost die for food, and let me have it!</S>

<L n="105"/><TLN n="1082"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Sit down and feed, and welcome to our table.</S>

<L n="106"/><TLN n="1083"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Speak you so gently? Pardon me, I pray you.
<L n="107"/><TLN n="1084"/>I thought that all things had been savage here,
<L n="108"/><TLN n="1085"/>And therefore put I on the countenance
<L n="109"/><TLN n="1086"/>Of stern commandment. But whate'er you are
<L n="110"/><TLN n="1087"/>That in this desert inaccessible,
<L n="111"/><TLN n="1088"/>Under the shade of melancholy boughs,
<L n="112"/><TLN n="1089"/>Lose and neglect the creeping hours of time;
<L n="113"/><TLN n="1090"/>If ever you have looked on better days,
<L n="114"/><TLN n="1091"/>If ever been where bells have knolled to church,
<L n="115"/><TLN n="1092"/>If ever sat at any good man's feast,
<L n="116"/><TLN n="1093"/>If ever from your eyelids wiped a tear,
<L n="117"/><TLN n="1094"/>And know what 'tis to pity and be pitied,
<L n="118"/><TLN n="1095"/>Let gentleness my strong enforcement be;
<L n="119"/><TLN n="1096"/>In the which hope I blush, and hide my sword.</S>
<SD t="action">[He sheathes his sword.]</SD>

<L n="120"/><TLN n="1097"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
True is it that we have seen better days,
<L n="121"/><TLN n="1098"/>And have with holy bell been knolled to church,
<L n="122"/><TLN n="1099"/>And sat at good men's feasts, and wiped our eyes
<L n="123"/><TLN n="1100"/>Of drops that sacred pity hath engendered;
<L n="124"/><TLN n="1101"/>And therefore sit you down in gentleness,
<L n="125"/><TLN n="1102"/>And take upon command what help we have
<L n="126"/><TLN n="1103"/>That to your wanting may be ministered.</S>

<L n="127"/><TLN n="1104"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Then but forbear your food a little while,
<L n="128"/><TLN n="1105"/>Whiles, like a doe, I go to find my fawn,
<L n="129"/><TLN n="1106"/>And give it food. There is an old poor man
<L n="130"/><TLN n="1107"/>Who after me hath many a weary step
<L n="131"/><TLN n="1108"/>Limped in pure love. Till he be first sufficed,
<L n="132"/><TLN n="1109"/>Oppressed with two weak evils, age and hunger,
<L n="133" part="i"/><TLN n="1110"/>I will not touch a bit.</S>

<L n="133" part="f"/><TLN n="1111"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Go find him out,
<L n="134"/><TLN n="1112"/>And we will nothing waste till you return.</S>

<L n="135"/><TLN n="1113"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I thank ye; and be blest for your good comfort!</S>
<SD t="exit">[Exit.]</SD>

<L n="136"/><TLN n="1114"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Thou see'st we are not all alone unhappy:
<L n="137"/><TLN n="1115"/>This wide and universal theater
<L n="138"/><TLN n="1116"/>Presents more woeful pageants than the scene
<L n="139" part="i"/><TLN n="1117"/>Wherein we play in.</S>

<L n="139" part="f"/><TLN n="1118"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
All the world's a stage,
<L n="140"/><TLN n="1119"/>And all the men and women merely players.
<L n="141"/><TLN n="1120"/>They have their exits and their entrances,
<L n="142"/><TLN n="1121"/>And one man in his time plays many parts,
<L n="143"/><TLN n="1122"/>His acts being seven ages. At first the infant,
<L n="144"/><TLN n="1123"/>Mewling and puking in the nurse's arms.
<L n="145"/><TLN n="1124"/>Then the whining schoolboy, with his satchel
<L n="146"/><TLN n="1125"/>And shining morning face, creeping like snail
<L n="147"/><TLN n="1126"/>Unwillingly to school. And then the lover,
<L n="148"/><TLN n="1127"/>Sighing like furnace, with a woeful ballad
<L n="149"/><TLN n="1128"/>Made to his mistress' eyebrow. Then a soldier,
<L n="150"/><TLN n="1129"/>Full of strange oaths, and bearded like the pard,
<L n="151"/><TLN n="1130"/>Jealous in honor, sudden, and quick in quarrel,
<L n="152"/><TLN n="1131"/>Seeking the bubble reputation
<L n="153"/><TLN n="1132"/>Even in the cannon's mouth. And then the justice,
<L n="154"/><TLN n="1133"/>In fair round belly with good capon lined,
<L n="155"/><TLN n="1134"/>With eyes severe and beard of formal cut,
<L n="156"/><TLN n="1135"/>Full of wise saws and modern instances;
<L n="157"/><TLN n="1136"/>And so he plays his part. The sixth age shifts
<L n="158"/><TLN n="1137"/>Into the lean and slippered pantaloon,
<L n="159"/><TLN n="1138"/>With spectacles on nose and pouch on side,
<L n="160"/><TLN n="1139"/>His youthful hose, well saved, a world too wide
<L n="161"/><TLN n="1140"/>For his shrunk shank; and his big manly voice,
<L n="162"/><TLN n="1141"/>Turning again toward childish treble, pipes
<L n="163"/><TLN n="1142"/>And whistles in his sound. Last scene of all,
<L n="164"/><TLN n="1143"/>That ends this strange eventful history,
<L n="165"/><TLN n="1144"/>Is second childishness and mere oblivion,
<L n="166"/><TLN n="1145"/>Sans teeth, sans eyes, sans taste, sans everything.</S>

<TLN n="1146"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Orlando with Adam.</SD>

<L n="167"/><TLN n="1147"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Welcome. Set down your venerable burden,
<L n="168"/><TLN n="1148"/>And let him feed.</S>

<L n="169"/><TLN n="1149"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I thank you most for him.</S>

<L n="170"/><TLN n="1150"/><S><SP>Adam</SP>
So had you need;
<L n="171"/><TLN n="1151"/>I scarce can speak to thank you for myself.</S>

<L n="172"/><TLN n="1152"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Welcome. Fall to. I will not trouble you
<L n="173"/><TLN n="1153"/>As yet to question you about your fortunes. --
<L n="174"/><TLN n="1154"/>Give us some music; and, good cousin, sing.</S>

<TLN n="1155"/><LD>Song</LD>

<L n="175"/><TLN n="1156"/><S><SP>Amiens</SP>
<SD t="sound">[Sings]</SD>
<VERSEQUOTE>
<STANZA n="1">
Blow, blow, thou winter wind,
<L n="176"/><TLN n="1157"/>Thou art not so unkind
<L n="177"/><SPACE n="3"/>As man's ingratitude.
<L n="178"/><TLN n="1158"/>Thy tooth is not so keen,
<L n="179"/>Because thou art not seen,
<L n="180"/><TLN n="1159"/><SPACE n="3"/>Although thy breath be rude.
<L n="181"/><TLN n="1160"/>Heigh-ho! Sing heigh-ho! unto the green holly.
<L n="182"/><TLN n="1161"/>Most friendship is feigning, most loving mere folly.
<L n="183"/><TLN n="1162"/>Then, heigh-ho, the holly!
<L n="184"/><TLN n="1163"/>This life is most jolly.
</STANZA>
<STANZA n="2">
<L n="185"/><TLN n="1164"/>Freeze, freeze, thou bitter sky,
<L n="186"/>That dost not bite so nigh
<L n="187"/><TLN n="1165"/><SPACE n="3"/>As benefits forgot;
<L n="188"/><TLN n="1166"/>Though thou the waters warp,
<L n="189"/>Thy sting is not so sharp
<L n="190"/><TLN n="1167"/><SPACE n="3"/>As friend remembered not.
<L n="191"/><TLN n="1168"/>Heigh-ho! Sing heigh-ho! unto the green holly.
<L n="192"/>Most friendship is feigning, most loving mere folly.
<L n="193"/>Then, heigh-ho, the holly!
<L n="194"/>This life is most jolly.
</STANZA>
</S>
</VERSEQUOTE>

<L n="195"/><TLN n="1169"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
If that you were the good Sir Rowland's son,
<L n="196"/><TLN n="1170"/>As you have whispered faithfully you were,
<L n="197"/><TLN n="1171"/>And as mine eye doth his effigies witness
<L n="198"/><TLN n="1172"/>Most truly limned and living in your face,
<L n="199"/><TLN n="1173"/>Be truly welcome hither. I am the Duke
<L n="200"/><TLN n="1174"/>That loved your father. The residue of your fortune,
<L n="201"/><TLN n="1175"/>Go to my cave and tell me. <SD t="whoto">[To Adam]</SD> Good old man,
<L n="202"/><TLN n="1176"/>Thou art right welcome as thy master is. <SD t="whoto">[To the others]</SD>
<L n="203"/><TLN n="1177"/>Support him by the arm.<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando]</SD> Give me your hand,
<L n="204"/><TLN n="1178"/>And let me all your fortunes understand.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>

</SCENE>
</ACT>
<ACT n="3">
<SCENE n="1">
<H2><TLN n="1179"/>[3.1]</H2>
<TLN n="1180"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Duke [Frederick], Lords, and Oliver.</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="1181"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
"Not see him since?" Sir, sir, that cannot be.
<L n="2"/><TLN n="1182"/>But were I not the better part made mercy,
<L n="3"/><TLN n="1183"/>I should not seek an absent argument
<L n="4"/><TLN n="1184"/>Of my revenge, thou present. But look to it:
<L n="5"/><TLN n="1185"/>Find out thy brother wheresoe'er he is;
<L n="6"/><TLN n="1186"/>Seek him with candle. Bring him dead or living
<L n="7"/><TLN n="1187"/>Within this twelvemonth, or turn thou no more
<L n="8"/><TLN n="1188"/>To seek a living in our territory.
<L n="9"/><TLN n="1189"/>Thy lands and all things that thou dost call thine
<L n="10"/><TLN n="1190"/>Worth seizure do we seize into our hands,
<L n="11"/><TLN n="1191"/>Till thou canst quit thee by thy brother's mouth
<L n="12"/><TLN n="1192"/>Of what we think against thee.</S>

<L n="13"/><TLN n="1193"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Oh. that Your Highness knew my heart in this!
<L n="14"/><TLN n="1194"/>I never loved my brother in my life.</S>

<L n="15"/><TLN n="1195"/><S><SP>Duke Frederick</SP>
More villain thou. -- Well, push him out of doors,
<L n="16"/><TLN n="1196"/>And let my officers of such a nature
<L n="17"/><TLN n="1197"/>Make an extent upon his house and lands.
<L n="18"/><TLN n="1198"/>Do this expediently, and turn him going.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="2">
<H2><TLN n="1199"/>[3.2]</H2>
<TLN n="1200"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Orlando [with a paper].</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="1201"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
<VERSEQUOTE> Hang there, my verse, in witness of my love;
<L n="2"/><TLN n="1202"/><SPACE n="3"/>And thou, thrice-crown{`e}d Queen of Night, survey
<L n="3"/><TLN n="1203"/>With thy chaste eye, from thy pale sphere above,
<L n="4"/><TLN n="1204"/><SPACE n="3"/>Thy huntress' name that my full life doth sway.
<L n="5"/><TLN n="1205"/>O Rosalind! These trees shall be my books,
<L n="6"/><TLN n="1206"/><SPACE n="3"/>And in their barks my thoughts I'll character,
<L n="7"/><TLN n="1207"/>That every eye which in this forest looks
<L n="8"/><TLN n="1208"/><SPACE n="3"/>Shall see thy virtue witnessed everywhere.
<L n="9"/><TLN n="1209"/>Run, run, Orlando, carve on every tree
<L n="10"/><TLN n="1210"/>The fair, the chaste, and unexpressive she.</S>
</VERSEQUOTE>
<SD t="exit">Exit</SD>
</MODE>

<TLN n="1211"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Corin and Clown [Touchstone].</SD>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="11"/><TLN n="1212"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
And how like you this shepherd's life, Master Touchstone?</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="1213"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Truly, shepherd, in respect of itself, it is a <TLN n="1214"/>good life; but in respect that it is a shepherd's life, it is <TLN n="1215"/>naught. In respect that it is solitary, I like it very well; <TLN n="1216"/>but in respect that it is private, it is a very vile life. Now <TLN n="1217"/>in respect it is in the fields, it pleaseth me well; but in respect <TLN n="1218"/>it is not in the court, it is tedious. As it is a spare <TLN n="1219"/>life, look you, it fits my humor well; but as there is no <TLN n="1220"/>more plenty in it, it goes much against my stomach. <TLN n="1221"/>Hast any philosophy in thee, shepherd?</S>

<L n="13"/><TLN n="1222"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
No more but that I know the more one sickens <TLN n="1223"/>the worse at ease he is; and that he that wants money, <TLN n="1224"/>means, and content is without three good friends; that <TLN n="1225"/>the property of rain is to wet, and fire to burn; that <TLN n="1226"/>good pasture makes fat sheep, and that a great cause of <TLN n="1227"/>the night is lack of the sun; that he that hath learned <TLN n="1228"/>no wit by nature nor art may complain of good <TLN n="1229"/>breeding, or comes of a very dull kindred.</S>

<L n="14"/><TLN n="1230"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Such a one is a natural philosopher. <TLN n="1231"/>Wast ever in court, shepherd?</S>

<L n="15"/><TLN n="1232"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
No, truly.</S>

<L n="16"/><TLN n="1233"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Then thou art damned.</S>

<L n="17"/><TLN n="1234"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Nay, I hope.</S>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="1235"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Truly, thou art damned, like an ill-roasted egg, <TLN n="1236"/>all on one side.</S>

<L n="19"/><TLN n="1237"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
For not being at court? Your reason.</S>

<L n="20"/><TLN n="1238"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Why, if thou never wast at court, thou never <TLN n="1239"/>saw'st good manners; if thou never saw'st good manners, <TLN n="1240"/>then thy manners must be wicked; and wickedness is sin, <TLN n="1241"/>and sin is damnation. Thou art in a parlous state, <TLN n="1242"/>shepherd.</S>

<L n="21"/><TLN n="1243"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Not a whit, Touchstone. Those that are good manners <TLN n="1244"/>at the court are as ridiculous in the country as <TLN n="1245"/>the behavior of the country is most mockable at the <TLN n="1246"/>court. You told me you salute not at the court but <TLN n="1247"/>you kiss your hands; that courtesy would be uncleanly <TLN n="1248"/>if courtiers were shepherds.</S>

<L n="22"/><TLN n="1249"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Instance, briefly; come, instance.</S>

<L n="23"/><TLN n="1250"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Why, we are still handling our ewes, and their <TLN n="1251"/>fells, you know, are greasy.</S>

<L n="24"/><TLN n="1252"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Why, do not your courtier's hands sweat? And <TLN n="1253"/>is not the grease of a mutton as wholesome as the sweat <TLN n="1254"/>of a man? Shallow, shallow. A better instance, I say. <TLN n="1255"/>Come.</S>

<L n="25"/><TLN n="1256"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Besides, our hands are hard.</S>

<L n="26"/><TLN n="1257"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Your lips will feel them the sooner. Shallow again. <TLN n="1258"/>A more sounder instance. Come.</S>

<L n="27"/><TLN n="1259"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
And they are often tarred over with the surgery <TLN n="1260"/>of our sheep; and would you have us kiss tar? The <TLN n="1261"/>courtier's hands are perfumed with civet.</S>

<L n="28"/><TLN n="1262"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Most shallow man! Thou worm's meat in respect <TLN n="1263"/>of a good piece of flesh indeed! Learn of the wise, <TLN n="1264"/>and perpend: civet is of a baser birth than tar, the <TLN n="1265"/>very uncleanly flux of a cat. Mend the instance, <TLN n="1266"/>shepherd.</S>

<L n="29"/><TLN n="1267"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
You have too courtly a wit for me. I'll rest.</S>

<L n="30"/><TLN n="1268"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Wilt thou rest damned? God help thee, shallow<TLN n="1269"/> man! God make incision in thee! Thou art raw.</S>

<L n="31"/><TLN n="1270"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Sir, I am a true laborer: I earn that I eat, get <TLN n="1271"/>that I wear, owe no man hate, envy no man's happiness, <TLN n="1272"/>glad of other men's good, content with my harm, <TLN n="1273"/>and the greatest of my pride is to see my ewes graze and <TLN n="1274"/>my lambs suck.</S>

<L n="32"/><TLN n="1275"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
That is another simple sin in you, to bring the <TLN n="1276"/>ewes and the rams together and to offer to get your <TLN n="1277"/>living by the copulation of cattle; to be bawd to a bellwether, <TLN n="1278"/>and to betray a she-lamb of a twelvemonth <TLN n="1279"/>to crooked-pated old cuckoldly ram, out of all <TLN n="1280"/>reasonable match. If thou beest not damned for this, <TLN n="1281"/>the devil himself will have no shepherds; I cannot see else <TLN n="1282"/>how thou shouldst scape.</S>

<L n="33"/><TLN n="1283"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Here comes young Master Ganymede, my new mistress's <TLN n="1284"/>brother.</S>

<TLN n="1285"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Rosalind [reading a paper].</SD>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">
<VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="34"/><TLN n="1286"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
"From the east to western Ind,
<L n="35"/><TLN n="1287"/>No jewel is like Rosalind.
<L n="36"/><TLN n="1288"/>Her worth, being mounted on the wind,
<L n="37"/><TLN n="1289"/>Through all the world bears Rosalind.
<L n="38"/><TLN n="1290"/>All the pictures fairest lined
<L n="39"/><TLN n="1291"/>Are but black to Rosalind.
<L n="40"/><TLN n="1292"/>Let no face be kept in mind
<L n="41"/><TLN n="1293"/>But the fair of Rosalind."</S>
</VERSEQUOTE>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="42"/><TLN n="1294"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
I'll rhyme you so eight years together, dinners, <TLN n="1295"/>and suppers, and sleeping hours, excepted. It is the right <TLN n="1296"/>butter-women's rank to market.</S>

<L n="43"/><TLN n="1297"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Out, fool!</S>

<L n="44"/><TLN n="1298"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
For a taste:
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">
<VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="45"/><TLN n="1299"/>If a hart do lack a hind,
<L n="46"/><TLN n="1300"/>Let him seek out Rosalind.
<L n="47"/><TLN n="1301"/>If the cat will after kind,
<L n="48"/><TLN n="1302"/>So be sure will Rosalind.
<L n="49"/><TLN n="1303"/>Wintered garments must be lined,
<L n="50"/><TLN n="1304"/>So must slender Rosalind.
<L n="51"/><TLN n="1305"/>They that reap must sheaf and bind,
<L n="52"/><TLN n="1306"/>Then to cart with Rosalind.
<L n="53"/><TLN n="1307"/>Sweetest nut hath sourest rind,
<L n="54"/><TLN n="1308"/>Such a nut is Rosalind.
<L n="55"/><TLN n="1309"/>He that sweetest rose will find
<L n="56"/><TLN n="1310"/>Must find love's prick and Rosalind.
</VERSEQUOTE>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">
<L n="57"/><TLN n="1311"/>This is the very false gallop of verses. Why do you infect <TLN n="1312"/>yourself with them?</S>

<L n="58"/><TLN n="1313"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Peace, you dull fool! I found them on a tree.</S>

<L n="59"/><TLN n="1314"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Truly, the tree yields bad fruit.</S>

<L n="60"/><TLN n="1315"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I'll graft it with you, and then I shall graft it <TLN n="1316"/>with a medlar. Then it will be the earliest fruit i'th' country; <TLN n="1317"/>for you'll be rotten ere you be half ripe, and that's <TLN n="1318"/>the right virtue of the medlar.</S>

<L n="61"/><TLN n="1319"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
You have said; but whether wisely or no, let the <TLN n="1320"/>forest judge.</S>

<TLN n="1321"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Celia, with a writing.</SD>

<L n="62"/><TLN n="1322"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Peace! Here comes my sister, reading. Stand aside.</S>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">
<VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="63"/><TLN n="1323"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
"Why should this a desert be?
<L n="64"/><TLN n="1324"/><SPACE n="3"/>For it is unpeopled? No.
<L n="65"/><TLN n="1325"/>Tongues I'll hang on every tree
<L n="66"/><TLN n="1326"/><SPACE n="3"/>That shall civil sayings show:
<L n="67"/><TLN n="1327"/>Some, how brief the life of man
<L n="68"/><TLN n="1328"/><SPACE n="3"/>Runs his erring pilgrimage,
<L n="69"/><TLN n="1329"/>That the stretching of a span
<L n="70"/><TLN n="1330"/><SPACE n="3"/>Buckles in his sum of age;
<L n="71"/><TLN n="1331"/>Some, of violated vows
<L n="72"/><TLN n="1332"/><SPACE n="3"/>'Twixt the souls of friend and friend;
<L n="73"/><TLN n="1333"/>But upon the fairest boughs,
<L n="74"/><TLN n="1334"/><SPACE n="3"/>Or at every sentence end,
<L n="75"/><TLN n="1335"/>Will I "Rosalinda" write,
<L n="76"/><TLN n="1336"/><SPACE n="3"/>Teaching all that read to know
<L n="77"/><TLN n="1337"/>The quintessence of every sprite
<L n="78"/><TLN n="1338"/><SPACE n="3"/>Heaven would in little show.
<L n="79"/><TLN n="1339"/>Therefore heaven Nature charged
<L n="80"/><TLN n="1340"/><SPACE n="3"/>That one body should be filled
<L n="81"/><TLN n="1341"/>With all graces wide-enlarged.
<L n="82"/><TLN n="1342"/><SPACE n="3"/>Nature presently distilled
<L n="83"/><TLN n="1343"/>Helen's cheek, but not her heart,
<L n="84"/><TLN n="1344"/><SPACE n="3"/>Cleopatra's majesty,
<L n="85"/><TLN n="1345"/>Atalanta's better part,
<L n="86"/><TLN n="1346"/><SPACE n="3"/>Sad Lucretia's modesty.
<L n="87"/><TLN n="1347"/>Thus Rosalind of many parts
<L n="88"/><TLN n="1348"/><SPACE n="3"/>By heavenly synod was devised
<L n="89"/><TLN n="1349"/>Of many faces, eyes, and hearts
<L n="90"/><TLN n="1350"/><SPACE n="3"/>To have the touches dearest prized.
<L n="91"/><TLN n="1351"/>Heaven would that she these gifts should have,
<L n="92"/><TLN n="1352"/>And I to live and die her slave."</S>
</VERSEQUOTE>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="93"/><TLN n="1353"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
O most gentle Jupiter, what tedious homily of <TLN n="1354"/>love have you wearied your parishioners withal, and <TLN n="1355"/>never cried "Have patience, good people!"</S>

<L n="94"/><TLN n="1356"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
How now? Back, friends. Shepherd, go off a little.<TLN n="1357"/><SD t="whoto">[To Touchstone]</SD>Go with him, sirrah.</S>

<L n="95"/><TLN n="1358"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Corin]</SD>
Come, shepherd, let us make an honorable retreat, <TLN n="1359"/>though not with bag and baggage, yet with <TLN n="1360"/>scrip and scrippage.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exit [with Corin].</SD>

<L n="96"/><TLN n="1361"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Didst thou hear these verses?</S>

<L n="97"/><TLN n="1362"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Oh, yes, I heard them all, and more too, for some <TLN n="1363"/>of them had in them more feet than the verses would <TLN n="1364"/>bear.</S>

<L n="98"/><TLN n="1365"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
That's no matter; the feet might bear the verses.</S>

<L n="99"/><TLN n="1366"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Ay, but the feet were lame, and could not bear <TLN n="1367"/>themselves without the verse, and therefore stood lamely <TLN n="1368"/>in the verse.</S>

<L n="100"/><TLN n="1369"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
But didst thou hear without wondering how <TLN n="1370"/>thy name should be hanged and carved upon these trees?</S>

<L n="101"/><TLN n="1371"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I was seven of the nine days out of the wonder <TLN n="1372"/>before you came; for look here what I found on a <TLN n="1373"/>palm tree. I was never so berhymed since Pythagoras' <TLN n="1374"/>time that I was an Irish rat, which I can hardly remember.</S>
<SD t="action">[Rosalind shows Celia the verse she found.]</SD>

<L n="102"/><TLN n="1375"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Trow you who hath done this?</S>

<L n="103"/><TLN n="1376"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Is it a man?</S>

<L n="104"/><TLN n="1377"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
And a chain that you once wore about his neck. <TLN n="1378"/>Change you color?</S>

<L n="105"/><TLN n="1379"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I prithee, who?</S>

<L n="106"/><TLN n="1380"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Oh, Lord, Lord, it is a hard matter for friends to <TLN n="1381"/>meet; but mountains may be removed with earthquakes, <TLN n="1382"/>and so encounter.</S>

<L n="107"/><TLN n="1383"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Nay, but who is it?</S>

<L n="108"/><TLN n="1384"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Is it possible?</S>

<L n="109"/><TLN n="1385"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Nay, I prithee now, with most petitionary vehemence, <TLN n="1386"/>tell me who it is.</S>

<L n="110"/><TLN n="1387"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Oh, wonderful, wonderful, most wonderful <TLN n="1388"/>wonderful, and yet again wonderful, and after that, <!--TLN moved -1 --><TLN n="1389"/>out of all hooping!</S>

<L n="111"/><TLN n="1390"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Good my complexion! Dost thou think, though <TLN n="1391"/>I am caparisoned like a man, I have a doublet and hose in <TLN n="1392"/>my disposition? One inch of delay more is a South Sea of discovery<TLN n="1393"/><!--TLN moved +2 -->. I prithee tell me who is it quickly, and <TLN n="1394"/>speak apace. I would thou couldst stammer, that thou <TLN n="1395"/>mightst pour this concealed man out of thy mouth as <TLN n="1396"/>wine comes out of narrow-mouthed bottle -- either too <TLN n="1397"/>much at once or none at all. I prithee take the cork <TLN n="1398"/>out of thy mouth, that I may drink thy tidings.</S>

<L n="112"/><TLN n="1399"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
So you may put a man in your belly.</S>

<L n="113"/><TLN n="1400"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Is he of God's making? What manner of man? <TLN n="1401"/>Is his head worth a hat, or his chin worth a beard?</S>

<L n="114"/><TLN n="1402"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Nay, he hath but a little beard.</S>

<L n="115"/><TLN n="1403"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Why, God will send more, if the man will be <TLN n="1404"/>thankful. Let me stay the growth of his beard, if thou <TLN n="1405"/>delay me not the knowledge of his chin.</S>

<L n="116"/><TLN n="1406"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
It is young Orlando, that tripped up the wrestler's <TLN n="1407"/>heels and your heart both in an instant.</S>

<L n="117"/><TLN n="1408"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Nay, but the devil take mocking! Speak sad <TLN n="1409"/>brow and true maid.</S>

<L n="118"/><TLN n="1410"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
I' faith, coz, 'tis he.</S>

<L n="119"/><TLN n="1411"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Orlando?</S>

<L n="120"/><TLN n="1412"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Orlando.</S>

<L n="121"/><TLN n="1413"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Alas the day, what shall I do with my doublet and <TLN n="1414"/>hose? What did he when thou saw'st him? What said <TLN n="1415"/>he? How looked he? Wherein went he? What makes he here? <TLN n="1416"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->Did he ask for me? Where remains he? How <TLN n="1417"/>parted he with thee? And when shalt thou see him again? <TLN n="1418"/>Answer me in one word.</S>

<L n="122"/><TLN n="1419"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
You must borrow me Gargantua's mouth first; <TLN n="1420"/>'tis a word too great for any mouth of this age's size. <TLN n="1421"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->To say ay and no to these particulars is more than to answer <TLN n="1422"/>in a catechism.</S>

<L n="123"/><TLN n="1423"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
But doth he know that I am in this forest, and <TLN n="1424"/>in man's apparel? Looks he as freshly as he did the day <TLN n="1425"/>he wrestled?</S>

<L n="124"/><TLN n="1426"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
It is as easy to count atomies as to resolve the propositions <TLN n="1427"/><!--TLN moved +1 -->of a lover. But take a taste of my finding <TLN n="1428"/>him, and relish it with good observance. I found him <TLN n="1429"/>under a tree, like a dropped acorn.</S>

<L n="125"/><TLN n="1430"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
It may well be called Jove's tree, when it <TLN n="1431"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->drops forth such fruit.</S>

<L n="126"/><TLN n="1432"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Give me audience, good madam.</S>

<L n="127"/><TLN n="1433"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Proceed.</S>

<L n="128"/><TLN n="1434"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
There lay he, stretched along like a wounded <TLN n="1435"/>knight.</S>

<L n="129"/><TLN n="1436"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Though it be pity to see such a sight, it well <TLN n="1437"/>becomes the ground.</S>

<L n="130"/><TLN n="1438"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Cry "Holla" to thy tongue, I prithee; it curvets <TLN n="1439"/>unseasonably. He was furnished like a hunter.</S>

<L n="131"/><TLN n="1440"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Oh, ominous! He comes to kill my heart.</S>

<L n="132"/><TLN n="1441"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
I would sing my song without a burden. <TLN n="1442"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->Thou bring'st me out of tune.</S>

<L n="133"/><TLN n="1443"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Do you not know I am a woman? When I think, <TLN n="1444"/>I must speak. Sweet, say on.</S>

<TLN n="1445"/><SD t="enter">Enter Orlando and Jaques.</SD>

<L n="134"/><TLN n="1446"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
You bring me out. -- Soft, comes he not here?</S>

<L n="135"/><TLN n="1447"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
'Tis he. Slink by, and note him.</S>
<SD t="action">[Rosalind and Celia stand aside and listen.]</SD>

<L n="136"/><TLN n="1448"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando]</SD>
I thank you for your company, but, good faith, <TLN n="1449"/>I had as lief have been myself alone.</S>

</MODE><MODE t="verse">
<L n="137"/><TLN n="1450"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
And so had I; but yet, for fashion sake, 
<L n="138"/><TLN n="1451"/>I thank you too for your society.</S>

</MODE><MODE t="prose">
<L n="139"/><TLN n="1452"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
God b'wi' you. Let's meet as little as we can.</S>

<L n="140"/><TLN n="1453"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I do desire we may be better strangers.</S>

<L n="141"/><TLN n="1454"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
I pray you, mar no more trees with writing <TLN n="1455"/>love songs in their barks.</S>

<L n="142"/><TLN n="1456"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I pray you, mar no more of my verses with reading <TLN n="1457"/>them ill-favoredly.</S>

<L n="143"/><TLN n="1458"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Rosalind is your love's name?</S>

<L n="144"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Yes, just.</S>

<L n="145"/><TLN n="1459"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
I do not like her name.</S>

<L n="146"/><TLN n="1460"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
There was no thought of pleasing you when she <TLN n="1461"/>was christened.</S>

<L n="147"/><TLN n="1462"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
What stature is she of?</S>

<L n="148"/><TLN n="1463"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Just as high as my heart.</S>

<L n="149"/><TLN n="1464"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
You are full of pretty answers. Have you not been acquainted <TLN n="1465"/>with goldsmiths' wives, and conned them out of rings?</S>

<L n="150"/><TLN n="1466"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Not so; but I answer you right painted cloth, <TLN n="1467"/>from whence you have studied your questions.</S>

<L n="151"/><TLN n="1468"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
You have a nimble wit; I think 'twas made of <TLN n="1469"/>Atalanta's heels. Will you sit down with me? And <TLN n="1470"/>we two will rail against our mistress the world, and all <TLN n="1471"/>our misery.</S>

<L n="152"/><TLN n="1472"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I will chide no breather in the world but myself, <TLN n="1473"/>against whom I know most faults.</S>

<L n="153"/><TLN n="1474"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
The worst fault you have is to be in love.</S>

<L n="154"/><TLN n="1475"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
'Tis a fault I will not change for your best virtue. <TLN n="1476"/>I am weary of you.</S>

<L n="155"/><TLN n="1477"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
By my troth, I was seeking for a fool when I <TLN n="1478"/>found you.</S>

<L n="156"/><TLN n="1479"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
He is drowned in the brook. Look but in, and <TLN n="1480"/>you shall see him.</S>

<L n="157"/><TLN n="1481"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
There I shall see mine own figure.</S>

<L n="158"/><TLN n="1482"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Which I take to be either a fool or a cipher.</S>

<L n="159"/><TLN n="1483"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
I'll tarry no longer with you. Farewell, good Signior <TLN n="1484"/>Love.</S>

<L n="160"/><TLN n="1485"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I am glad of your departure. Adieu, good Monsieur <TLN n="1486"/>Melancholy.</S>
<SD t="exit">[Exit Jaques.]</SD>

<L n="161"/><TLN n="1487"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[Aside to Celia]</SD>
I will speak to him like a saucy lackey, and <TLN n="1488"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->under that habit play the knave with him. -- Do you hear, forester?</S>

<L n="162"/><TLN n="1489"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Very well. What would you?</S>

<L n="133"/><TLN n="1490"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I pray you, what is't o'clock?</S>

<L n="164"/><TLN n="1491"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
You should ask me what time o' day. There's no <TLN n="1492"/>clock in the forest.</S>

<L n="165"/><TLN n="1493"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Then there is no true lover in the forest, else <TLN n="1494"/>sighing every minute and groaning every hour would <TLN n="1495"/>detect the lazy foot of Time as well as a clock.</S>

<L n="166"/><TLN n="1496"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
And why not the swift foot of Time? Had not <TLN n="1497"/>that been as proper?</S>

<L n="167"/><TLN n="1498"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
By no means, sir. Time travels in divers paces <TLN n="1499"/>with divers persons. I'll tell you who Time ambles withal, <TLN n="1500"/>who Time trots withal, who Time gallops withal, <TLN n="1501"/>and who he stands still withal.</S>

<L n="168"/><TLN n="1502"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I prithee, who doth he trot withal?</S>

<L n="169"/><TLN n="1503"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Marry, he trots hard with a young maid between <TLN n="1504"/>the contract of her marriage and the day it is solemnized. <TLN n="1505"/>If the interim be but a se'nnight, Time's pace is so hard <TLN n="1506"/>that it seems the length of seven year.</S>

<L n="170"/><TLN n="1507"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Who ambles Time withal?</S>

<L n="171"/><TLN n="1508"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
With a priest that lacks Latin and a rich man <TLN n="1509"/>that hath not the gout, for the one sleeps easily because <TLN n="1510"/>he cannot study, and the other lives merrily because <TLN n="1511"/>he feels no pain; the one lacking the burden of <TLN n="1512"/>lean and wasteful learning, the other knowing no burden <TLN n="1513"/>of heavy tedious penury. These Time <TLN n="1514"/><!--moved -1-->ambles withal.</S>

<L n="172"/><TLN n="1515"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Who doth he gallop withal?</S>

<L n="173"/><TLN n="1516"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
With a thief to the gallows, for though he <TLN n="1517"/>go as softly as foot can fall, he thinks himself too soon <TLN n="1518"/>there.</S>

<L n="174"/><TLN n="1519"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Who stays it still withal?</S>

<L n="175"/><TLN n="1520"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
With lawyers in the vacation; for they sleep <TLN n="1521"/>between term and term, and then they perceive not <TLN n="1522"/>how Time moves.</S>

<L n="176"/><TLN n="1523"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Where dwell you, pretty youth?</S>

<L n="177"/><TLN n="1524"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
With this shepherdess, my sister, here in the <TLN n="1525"/>skirts of the forest, like fringe upon a petticoat.</S>

<L n="178"/><TLN n="1526"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Are you native of this place?</S>

<L n="179"/><TLN n="1527"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
As the coney that you see dwell where she is <TLN n="1528"/>kindled.</S>

<L n="180"/><TLN n="1529"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Your accent is something finer than you could <TLN n="1530"/>purchase in so removed a dwelling.</S>

<L n="181"/><TLN n="1531"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I have been told so of many. But indeed an old <TLN n="1532"/>religious uncle of mine taught me to speak, who was <TLN n="1533"/>in his youth an inland man, one that knew courtship too <TLN n="1534"/>well, for there he fell in love. I have heard him read many lectures <TLN n="1535"/><!--TLN moved +1 -->against it; and I thank God I am not a woman, <TLN n="1536"/>to be touched with so many giddy offences as he <TLN n="1537"/>hath generally taxed their whole sex withal.</S>

<L n="182"/><TLN n="1538"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Can you remember any of the principal evils <TLN n="1539"/>that he laid to the charge of women?</S>

<L n="183"/><TLN n="1540"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
There were none principal; they were all like <TLN n="1541"/>one another as halfpence are, every one fault seeming <TLN n="1542"/>monstrous till his fellow-fault came to match it.</S>

<L n="184"/><TLN n="1543"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I prithee, recount some of them.</S>

<L n="185"/><TLN n="1544"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
No; I will not cast away my physic but on those <TLN n="1545"/>that are sick. There is a man haunts the forest that abuses <TLN n="1546"/>our young plants with carving "Rosalind" on their <TLN n="1547"/>barks, hangs odes upon hawthorns and elegies on <TLN n="1548"/>brambles, all, forsooth, deifying the name of Rosalind. <TLN n="1549"/>If I could meet that fancy-monger, I would give him <TLN n="1550"/>some good counsel, for he seems to have the quotidian <TLN n="1551"/>of love upon him.</S>

<L n="186"/><TLN n="1552"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I am he that is so love-shaked. I pray you, tell <TLN n="1553"/>me your remedy.</S>

<L n="187"/><TLN n="1554"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
There is none of my uncle's marks upon you. <TLN n="1555"/>He taught me how to know a man in love, in which <TLN n="1556"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->cage of rushes I am sure you are not prisoner.</S>

<L n="188"/><TLN n="1557"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
What were his marks?</S>

<L n="189"/><TLN n="1558"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
A lean cheek, which you have not; a blue eye <TLN n="1559"/>and sunken, which you have not; an unquestionable spirit, <TLN n="1560"/>which you have not; a beard neglected, which you <TLN n="1561"/>have not -- but I pardon you for that, for simply your having <TLN n="1562"/>in beard is a younger brother's revenue. Then your <TLN n="1563"/>hose should be ungartered, your bonnet unbanded, your <TLN n="1564"/>sleeve unbuttoned, your shoe untied, and everything <TLN n="1565"/>about you demonstrating a careless desolation. But you <TLN n="1566"/>are no such man. You are rather point-device in your accoutrements, <TLN n="1567"/>as loving yourself, than seeming the lover <TLN n="1568"/>of any other.</S>

<L n="190"/><TLN n="1569"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Fair youth, I would I could make thee believe I love.</S>

<L n="191"/><TLN n="1570"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Me believe it? You may as soon make her that <TLN n="1571"/>you love believe it -- which, I warrant, she is apter to do <TLN n="1572"/>than to confess she does. That is one of the points in the <TLN n="1573"/>which women still give the lie to their consciences. But, <TLN n="1574"/>in good sooth, are you he that hangs the verses on the <TLN n="1575"/>trees wherein Rosalind is so admired?</S>

<L n="192"/><TLN n="1576"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I swear to thee, youth, by the white hand of <TLN n="1577"/>Rosalind, I am that he, that unfortunate he.</S>

<L n="193"/><TLN n="1578"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
But are you so much in love as your rhymes speak?</S>

<L n="194"/><TLN n="1579"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Neither rhyme nor reason can express how much.</S>

<L n="195"/><TLN n="1580"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Love is merely a madness, and, I tell you, deserves <TLN n="1581"/>as well a dark house and a whip as madmen do; <TLN n="1582"/>and the reason why they are not so punished and cured is <TLN n="1583"/>that the lunacy is so ordinary that the whippers are in <TLN n="1584"/>love too. Yet I profess curing it by counsel.</S>

<L n="196"/><TLN n="1585"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Did you ever cure any so?</S>

<L n="197"/><TLN n="1586"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Yes, one, and in this manner. He was to imagine <TLN n="1587"/>me his love, his mistress, and I set him every day <TLN n="1588"/>to woo me. At which time would I, being but a moonish <TLN n="1589"/>youth, grieve, be effeminate, changeable, longing and <TLN n="1590"/>liking, proud, fantastical, apish, shallow, inconstant, full <TLN n="1591"/>of tears, full of smiles; for every passion something and <TLN n="1592"/>for no passion truly anything, as boys and women are <TLN n="1593"/>for the most part cattle of this color; would now like <TLN n="1594"/>him, now loathe him; then entertain him, then forswear him; <TLN n="1595"/><!--TLN moved +1 -->now weep for him, then spit at him; that I drave <TLN n="1596"/>my suitor from his mad humor of love to a living <TLN n="1597"/>humor of madness, which was to forswear the full stream of the world <TLN n="1598"/>and to live in a nook, merely monastic. And thus I cured <TLN n="1599"/>him; and this way will I take upon me to wash your liver <TLN n="1600"/>as clean as a sound sheep's heart, that there shall not <TLN n="1601"/>be one spot of love in't.</S>

<L n="198"/><TLN n="1602"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I would not be cured, youth.</S>

<L n="199"/><TLN n="1603"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I would cure you, if you would but call me Rosalind, <TLN n="1604"/>and come every day to my cote and woo me.</S>

<L n="200"/><TLN n="1605"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Now, by the faith of my love, I will. Tell me <TLN n="1606"/>where it is.</S>

<L n="201"/><TLN n="1607"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Go with me to it, and I'll show it you; and by <TLN n="1608"/>the way you shall tell me where in the forest you live. <TLN n="1609"/>Will you go?</S>

<L n="202"/><TLN n="1610"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
With all my heart, good youth.</S>

<L n="203"/><TLN n="1611"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Nay, you must call me Rosalind. -- Come, sister, <TLN n="1612"/>will you go?</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="3">
<H2><TLN n="1613"/>[3.3]</H2>
<TLN n="1614"/><SD t="entrance">Enter [Touchstone the] Clown, Audrey, and Jaques [behind].</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="1615"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Come apace, good Audrey. I will fetch up your <TLN n="1616"/>goats, Audrey. And how, Audrey, am I the man yet? <TLN n="1617"/>Doth my simple feature content you?</S>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="1618"/><S><SP>Audrey</SP>
Your features! Lord warrant us, what features?</S>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="1619"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
I am here with thee and thy goats, as the most <TLN n="1620"/>capricious poet, honest Ovid, was among the Goths.</S>

<L n="4"/><TLN n="1621"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[Aside]</SD>
Oh, knowledge ill-inhabited, worse than <!--TLN moved -2 --><TLN n="1622"/>Jove in a thatched house!</S>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="1623"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
When a man's verses cannot be understood, nor <TLN n="1624"/>a man's good wit seconded with the forward child, understanding, <TLN n="1625"/>it strikes a man more dead than a great reckoning <TLN n="1626"/>in a little room. Truly, I would the gods had <TLN n="1627"/>made thee poetical.</S>

<L n="6"/><TLN n="1628"/><S><SP>Audrey</SP>
I do not know what "poetical" is. Is it honest in <TLN n="1629"/>deed and word? Is it a true thing?</S>

<L n="7"/><TLN n="1630"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
No, truly; for the truest poetry is the most feigning, <TLN n="1631"/>and lovers are given to poetry, and what they <TLN n="1632"/>swear in poetry it may be said as lovers they do feign.</S>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="1633"/><S><SP>Audrey</SP>
Do you wish, then, that the gods had made me <TLN n="1634"/>poetical?</S>

<L n="9"/><TLN n="1635"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
I do, truly; for thou swear'st to me thou art honest. <TLN n="1636"/>Now, if thou wert a poet, I might have some hope <TLN n="1637"/>thou didst feign.</S>

<L n="10"/><TLN n="1638"/><S><SP>Audrey</SP>
Would you not have me honest?</S>

<L n="11"/><TLN n="1639"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
No, truly, unless thou wert hard-favored; for <TLN n="1640"/>honesty coupled to beauty is to have honey a sauce to <TLN n="1641"/>sugar.</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="1642"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[Aside]</SD>
A material fool!</S>

<L n="13"/><TLN n="1643"/><S><SP>Audrey</SP>
Well, I am not fair, and therefore I pray the <TLN n="1644"/>gods make me honest.</S>

<L n="14"/><TLN n="1645"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Truly, and to cast away honesty upon a foul <TLN n="1646"/>slut were to put good meat into an unclean dish.</S>

<L n="15"/><TLN n="1647"/><S><SP>Audrey</SP>
I am not a slut, though I thank the gods I <TLN n="1648"/>am foul.</S>

<L n="16"/><TLN n="1649"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Well, praised be the gods for thy foulness! Sluttishness <TLN n="1650"/>may come hereafter. But be it as it may be, <TLN n="1651"/>I will marry thee; and to that end I have been with Sir <TLN n="1652"/>Oliver Mar-text, the vicar of the next village, who hath <TLN n="1653"/>promised to meet me in this place of the forest, and to <TLN n="1654"/>couple us.</S>

<L n="17"/><TLN n="1655"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[Aside]</SD>
I would fain see this meeting.</S>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="1656"/><S><SP>Audrey</SP>
Well, the gods give us joy!</S>

<L n="19"/><TLN n="1657"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Amen. A man may, if he were of a fearful heart, <TLN n="1658"/>stagger in this attempt; for here we have no temple <TLN n="1659"/>but the wood, no assembly but horn-beasts. But <TLN n="1660"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->what though? Courage! As horns are odious, they are necessary. <TLN n="1661"/>It is said, "Many a man knows no end of his goods." <TLN n="1662"/>Right! Many a man has good horns and knows no end of them. <TLN n="1663"/><!--TLN moved +2 -->Well, that is the dowry of his wife; 'tis none <TLN n="1664"/>of his own getting. Horns? Even so. Poor men alone? <TLN n="1665"/>No, no, the noblest deer hath them as huge as the rascal. <TLN n="1666"/>Is the single man therefore blessed? No. As a walled <TLN n="1667"/>town is more worthier than a village, so is the forehead <TLN n="1668"/>of a married man more honorable than the bare <TLN n="1669"/>brow of a bachelor; and by how much defense is better <TLN n="1670"/>than no skill, by so much is a horn more precious <TLN n="1671"/>than to want.

<TLN n="1672"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Sir Oliver Mar-text.</SD>

<TLN n="1673"/>Here comes Sir Oliver. -- Sir Oliver Mar-text, you are <TLN n="1674"/>well met. Will you dispatch us here under this tree, or <TLN n="1675"/>shall we go with you to your chapel?</S>

<L n="20"/><TLN n="1676"/><S><SP>Sir Oliver Mar-text</SP>
Is there none here to give the woman?</S>

<L n="21"/><TLN n="1677"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
I will not take her on gift of any man.</S>

<L n="22"/><TLN n="1678"/><S><SP>Sir Oliver Mar-text</SP>
Truly, she must be given, or the marriage is not <TLN n="1679"/>lawful.</S>

<L n="23"/><TLN n="1680"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
<SD t="action">[Coming forward]</SD>
Proceed, proceed. I'll give her.</S>

<L n="24"/><TLN n="1681"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Good even, good Master What-ye-call't. How do you, <TLN n="1682"/>sir? You are very well met. God 'ild you for your last company. <TLN n="1683"/><!--TLN moved +1 -->I am very glad to see you. Even a toy in hand <TLN n="1684"/>here, sir. -- Nay, pray be covered.</S>

<L n="25"/><TLN n="1685"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Will you be married, motley?</S>

<L n="26"/><TLN n="1686"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
As the ox hath his bow, sir, the horse his curb, <TLN n="1687"/>and the falcon her bells, so man hath his desires; and as <TLN n="1688"/>pigeons bill, so wedlock would be nibbling.</S>

<L n="27"/><TLN n="1689"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
And will you, being a man of your breeding, be <TLN n="1690"/>married under a bush like a beggar? Get you to church, <TLN n="1691"/>and have a good priest that can tell you what marriage is. <TLN n="1692"/>This fellow will but join you together as they <TLN n="1693"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->join wainscot; then one of you will prove a shrunk panel, <TLN n="1694"/>and, like green timber warp, warp.</S>

<L n="28"/><TLN n="1695"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
I am not in the mind but I were better to be <TLN n="1696"/>married of him than of another; for he is not like to marry <TLN n="1697"/>me well; and not being well married, it will be a good <TLN n="1698"/>excuse for me hereafter to leave my wife.</S>

<L n="29"/><TLN n="1699"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Go thou with me, <TLN n="1700"/>and let me counsel thee.</S>

<L n="30"/><TLN n="1701"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
</MODE><MODE t="verse">
Come, sweet Audrey.
<L n="31"/><TLN n="1702"/>We must be married or we must live in bawdry. --
</MODE><MODE t="prose">
<L n="32"/><TLN n="1703"/>Farewell, good Master Oliver. Not
</MODE><MODE t="verse">
<VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="33"/><SPACE n="3"/>"O sweet Oliver,
<L n="34"/><SPACE n="3"/>O brave <TLN n="1704"/>Oliver,
<L n="35"/><TLN n="1704"/>Leave me not behind thee,"
</VERSEQUOTE>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">
<L n="36"/>but
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">
<VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="37"/><SPACE n="3"/>"Wind away,
<L n="38"/><SPACE n="3"/>Begone, <TLN n="1705"/>I say,
<L n="39"/>I will not to wedding with thee."</S>
</VERSEQUOTE>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">
<SD t="exit">[Exeunt Jaques, Touchstone, and Audrey.]</SD>

<L n="40"/><TLN n="1706"/><S><SP>Sir Oliver Mar-text</SP>
'Tis no matter. Ne'er a fantastical knave of them <TLN n="1707"/>all shall flout me out of my calling.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exit.</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="4">
<H2><TLN n="1708"/>[3.4]</H2>
<TLN n="1709"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Rosalind and Celia.</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="1710"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Never talk to me. I will weep.</S>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="1711"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Do, I prithee, but yet have the grace to consider <TLN n="1712"/>that tears do not become a man.</S>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="1713"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
But have I not cause to weep?</S>

<L n="4"/><TLN n="1714"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
As good cause as one would desire; <TLN n="1715"/>therefore weep.</S>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="1716"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
His very hair <TLN n="1717"/>is of the dissembling color.</S>

<L n="6"/><TLN n="1718"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Something browner than Judas's. <TLN n="1719"/>Marry, his kisses are Judas's own children.</S>

<L n="7"/><TLN n="1720"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I'faith, his hair is of a good color.</S>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="1721"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
An excellent color. <TLN n="1722"/>Your chestnut was ever the only color.</S>

<L n="9"/><TLN n="1723"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
And his kissing is as full of sanctity <TLN n="1724"/>as the touch of holy bread.</S>

<L n="10"/><TLN n="1725"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
He hath bought a pair of cast lips of Diana. A <TLN n="1726"/>nun of winter's sisterhood kisses not more religiously; <TLN n="1727"/>the very ice of chastity is in them.</S>

<L n="11"/><TLN n="1728"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
But why did he swear he would come this <TLN n="1729"/>morning, and comes not?</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="1730"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Nay, certainly, there is no truth in him.</S>

<L n="13"/><TLN n="1731"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Do you think so?</S>

<L n="14"/><TLN n="1732"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Yes. I think he is not a pickpurse nor a horse-stealer, <TLN n="1733"/>but for his verity in love, I do think him as <TLN n="1734"/>concave as a covered goblet or a worm-eaten nut.</S>

<L n="15"/><TLN n="1735"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Not true in love?</S>

<L n="16"/><TLN n="1736"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Yes, when he is in, but I think he is not in.</S>

<L n="17"/><TLN n="1737"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
You have heard him swear downright he was.</S>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="1738"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
"Was" is not "is." Besides, the oath of a lover is no <TLN n="1739"/>stronger than the word of a tapster; they are both the <TLN n="1740"/>confirmer of false reckonings. He attends here in the forest <TLN n="1741"/>on the Duke, your father.</S>

<L n="19"/><TLN n="1742"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I met the Duke yesterday, and had much question <TLN n="1743"/>with him. He asked me of what parentage I was. I <TLN n="1744"/>told him, of as good as he; so he laughed and let me go. <TLN n="1745"/>But what talk we of fathers, when there is such a man <TLN n="1746"/>as Orlando?</S>

<L n="20"/><TLN n="1747"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Oh, that's a brave man! He writes brave verses, <TLN n="1748"/>speaks brave words, swears brave oaths, and breaks <TLN n="1749"/>them bravely, quite traverse, athwart the heart of his lover, <TLN n="1750"/>as a puny tilter, that spurs his horse but on one side, <TLN n="1751"/>breaks his staff like a noble goose. But all's brave that <TLN n="1752"/>youth mounts and folly guides. Who comes here?</S>

<TLN n="1753"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Corin.</SD>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="21"/><TLN n="1754"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Mistress and master, you have oft inquired
<L n="22"/><TLN n="1755"/>After the shepherd that complained of love,
<L n="23"/><TLN n="1756"/>Who you saw sitting by me on the turf,
<L n="24"/><TLN n="1757"/>Praising the proud disdainful shepherdess
<L n="25" part="i"/><TLN n="1758"/>That was his mistress.</S>

<L n="25" part="f"/><TLN n="1759"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Well, and what of him?</S>

<L n="26"/><TLN n="1760"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
If you will see a pageant truly played
<L n="27"/><TLN n="1761"/>Between the pale complexion of true love
<L n="28"/><TLN n="1762"/>And the red glow of scorn and proud disdain,
<L n="29"/><TLN n="1763"/>Go hence a little, and I shall conduct you,
<L n="30" part="i"/><TLN n="1764"/>If you will mark it.</S>

<L n="30" part="f"/><TLN n="1765"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Oh, come, let us remove!
<L n="31"/><TLN n="1766"/>The sight of lovers feedeth those in love.
<L n="32"/><TLN n="1767"/>Bring us to this sight, and you shall say
<L n="33"/><TLN n="1768"/>I'll prove a busy actor in their play.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="5">
<H2><TLN n="1769"/>[3.5]</H2>
<TLN n="1770"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Silvius and Phoebe.</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="1771"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
Sweet Phoebe, do not scorn me, do not, Phoebe!
<L n="2"/><TLN n="1772"/>Say that you love me not, but say not so
<L n="3"/><TLN n="1773"/>In bitterness. The common executioner,
<L n="4"/><TLN n="1774"/>Whose heart th'accustomed sight of death makes hard,
<L n="5"/><TLN n="1775"/>Falls not the ax upon the humbled neck
<L n="6"/><TLN n="1776"/>But first begs pardon. Will you sterner be
<L n="7"/><TLN n="1777"/>Than he that dies and lives by bloody drops?</S>

<SD t="1778">Enter Rosalind, Celia, and Corin, [at a distance].</SD>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="1779"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
I would not be thy executioner;
<L n="9"/><TLN n="1780"/>I fly thee, for I would not injure thee.
<L n="10"/><TLN n="1781"/>Thou tell'st me there is murder in mine eye.
<L n="11"/><TLN n="1782"/>'Tis pretty, sure, and very probable,
<L n="12"/><TLN n="1783"/>That eyes, that are the frail'st and softest things,
<L n="13"/><TLN n="1784"/>Who shut their coward gates on atomies,
<L n="14"/><TLN n="1785"/>Should be called tyrants, butchers, murderers!
<L n="15"/><TLN n="1786"/>Now I do frown on thee with all my heart,
<L n="16"/><TLN n="1787"/>And if mine eyes can wound, now let them kill thee.
<L n="17"/><TLN n="1788"/>Now counterfeit to swoon; why, now fall down,
<L n="18"/><TLN n="1789"/>Or, if thou canst not, oh, for shame, for shame,
<L n="19"/><TLN n="1790"/>Lie not, to say mine eyes are murderers!
<L n="20"/><TLN n="1791"/>Now show the wound mine eye hath made in thee.
<L n="21"/><TLN n="1792"/>Scratch thee but with a pin, and there remains
<L n="22"/><TLN n="1793"/>Some scar of it; lean upon a rush,
<L n="23"/><TLN n="1794"/>The cicatrice and capable impressure
<L n="24"/><TLN n="1795"/>Thy palm some moment keeps; but now mine eyes,
<L n="25"/><TLN n="1796"/>Which I have darted at thee, hurt thee not.
<L n="26"/><TLN n="1797"/>Nor, I am sure, there is no force in eyes
<L n="27"/><TLN n="1798"/>That can do hurt.</S>

<TLN n="1799"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
<L n="27"/>O dear Phoebe,
<L n="28"/><TLN n="1800"/>If ever -- as that "ever" may be near --
<L n="29"/><TLN n="1801"/>You meet in some fresh cheek the power of fancy,
<L n="30"/><TLN n="1802"/>Then shall you know the wounds invisible
<L n="31" part="i"/><TLN n="1803"/>That love's keen arrows make.</S>

<TLN n="1804"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
<L n="31" part="f"/>But till that time
<L n="32"/><TLN n="1805"/>Come not thou near me; and when that time comes,
<L n="33"/><TLN n="1806"/>Afflict me with thy mocks; pity me not,
<L n="34"/><TLN n="1807"/>As till that time I shall not pity thee.</S>

<L n="35"/><TLN n="1808"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<SD t="action">[Advancing]</SD>
And why, I pray you? Who might be your mother,
<L n="36"/><TLN n="1809"/>That you insult, exult, and all at once,
<L n="37"/><TLN n="1810"/>Over the wretched? What though you have no beauty --
<L n="38"/><TLN n="1811"/>As, by my faith, I see no more in you
<L n="39"/><TLN n="1812"/>Than without candle may go dark to bed --
<L n="40"/><TLN n="1813"/>Must you be therefore proud and pitiless?
<SD t="action">[Phoebe gazes intently at Rosalind.]</SD>
<L n="41"/><TLN n="1814"/>Why, what means this? Why do you look on me?
<L n="42"/><TLN n="1815"/>I see no more in you than in the ordinary
<L n="43"/><TLN n="1816"/>Of nature's sale-work. -- 'Od's my little life,
<L n="44"/><TLN n="1817"/>I think she means to tangle my eyes too! --
<L n="45"/><TLN n="1818"/>No faith, proud mistress, hope not after it.
<L n="46"/><TLN n="1819"/>'Tis not your inky brows, your black silk hair,
<L n="47"/><TLN n="1820"/>Your bugle eyeballs, nor your cheek of cream
<L n="48"/><TLN n="1821"/>That can entame my spirits to your worship.
<SD t="whoto">[To Silvius]</SD>
<L n="49"/><TLN n="1822"/>You foolish shepherd, wherefore do you follow her,
<L n="50"/><TLN n="1823"/>Like foggy south, puffing with wind and rain?
<L n="51"/><TLN n="1824"/>You are a thousand times a properer man
<L n="52"/><TLN n="1825"/>Than she a woman. 'Tis such fools as you
<L n="53"/><TLN n="1826"/>That makes the world full of ill-favored children.
<L n="54"/><TLN n="1827"/>'Tis not her glass, but you, that flatters her,
<L n="55"/><TLN n="1828"/>And out of you she sees herself more proper
<L n="56"/><TLN n="1829"/>Than any of her lineaments can show her.
<SD t="whoto">[To Phoebe]</SD>
<L n="57"/><TLN n="1830"/>But, mistress, know yourself. Down on your knees,
<L n="58"/><TLN n="1831"/>And thank heaven, fasting, for a good man's love!
<L n="59"/><TLN n="1832"/>For I must tell you friendly in your ear:
<L n="60"/><TLN n="1833"/>Sell when you can; you are not for all markets.
<L n="61"/><TLN n="1834"/>Cry the man mercy, love him, take his offer;
<L n="62"/><TLN n="1835"/>Foul is most foul, being foul to be a scoffer.
<SD t="whoto">[To Silvius]</SD>
<L n="63"/><TLN n="1836"/>So take her to thee, shepherd. Fare you well.</S>

<L n="64"/><TLN n="1837"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
Sweet youth, I pray you chide a year together.
<L n="65"/><TLN n="1838"/>I had rather hear you chide than this man woo.</S>

<L n="66"/><TLN n="1839"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">
<SD t="whoto">[To Phoebe]</SD>
He's fallen in love with your foulness, <SD t="whoto">[To Silvius]</SD>and she'll <TLN n="1840"/>fall in love with my anger. If it be so, as fast <TLN n="1841"/>as she answers thee with frowning looks, I'll sauce <TLN n="1842"/>her with bitter words. <SD t="whoto">[To Phoebe]</SD>Why look you so upon me?</S>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="67"/><TLN n="1843"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
For no ill will I bear you.</S>

<L n="68"/><TLN n="1844"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I pray you, do not fall in love with me,
<L n="69"/><TLN n="1845"/>For I am falser than vows made in wine.
<L n="70"/><TLN n="1846"/>Besides, I like you not. <SD t="whoto">[To Silvius]</SD> If you will know my house,
<L n="71"/><TLN n="1847"/>'Tis at the tuft of olives here hard by. --
<L n="72"/><TLN n="1848"/>Will you go, sister? -- Shepherd, ply her hard. --
<L n="73"/><TLN n="1849"/>Come, sister. -- Shepherdess, look on him better,
<L n="74"/><TLN n="1850"/>And be not proud. Though all the world could see,
<L n="75"/><TLN n="1851"/>None could be so abused in sight as he. --
<L n="76"/><TLN n="1852"/>Come, to our flock.</S>
<SD t="exit"> Exit [with Celia and Corin].</SD>

<L n="77"/><TLN n="1853"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
Dead shepherd, now I find thy saw of might:
<L n="78"/><TLN n="1854"/>"Who ever loved that loved not at first sight?"</S>

<L n="79" part="i"/><TLN n="1855"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
Sweet Phoebe -- </S>

<TLN n="1856"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
<L n="79" part="f"/>Ha! What say'st thou, Silvius?</S>

<L n="80"/><TLN n="1857"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
Sweet Phoebe, pity me.</S>

<L n="81"/><TLN n="1858"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
Why, I am sorry for thee, gentle Silvius.</S>

<L n="82"/><TLN n="1859"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
Wherever sorrow is, relief would be.
<L n="83"/><TLN n="1860"/>If you do sorrow at my grief in love,
<L n="84"/><TLN n="1861"/>By giving love, your sorrow and my grief
<L n="85"/><TLN n="1862"/>Were both extermined.</S>

<L n="86"/><TLN n="1863"/><S><SP>Phebe</SP>
Thou hast my love. Is not that neighborly?</S>

<L n="87" part="i"/><TLN n="1864"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
I would have you.</S>

<TLN n="1865"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
<L n="87" part="f"/>Why, that were covetousness.
<L n="88"/><TLN n="1866"/>Silvius, the time was that I hated thee,
<L n="89"/><TLN n="1867"/>And yet it is not that I bear thee love;
<L n="90"/><TLN n="1868"/>But since that thou canst talk of love so well,
<L n="91"/><TLN n="1869"/>Thy company, which erst was irksome to me,
<L n="92"/><TLN n="1870"/>I will endure; and I'll employ thee too.
<L n="93"/><TLN n="1871"/>But do not look for further recompense
<L n="94"/><TLN n="1872"/>Than thine own gladness that thou art employed.</S>

<L n="95"/><TLN n="1873"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
So holy and so perfect is my love,
<L n="96"/><TLN n="1874"/>And I in such a poverty of grace,
<L n="97"/><TLN n="1875"/>That I shall think it a most plenteous crop
<L n="98"/><TLN n="1876"/>To glean the broken ears after the man
<L n="99"/><TLN n="1877"/>That the main harvest reaps. Loose now and then
<L n="100"/><TLN n="1878"/>A scattered smile, and that I'll live upon.</S>

<L n="101"/><TLN n="1879"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
Know'st thou the youth that spoke to me erewhile?</S>

<L n="102"/><TLN n="1880"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
Not very well, but I have met him oft,
<L n="103"/><TLN n="1881"/>And he hath bought the cottage and the bounds
<L n="104"/><TLN n="1882"/>That the old carlot once was master of.</S>

<L n="105"/><TLN n="1883"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
Think not I love him, though I ask for him.
<L n="106"/><TLN n="1884"/>'Tis but a peevish boy; yet he talks well.
<L n="107"/><TLN n="1885"/>But what care I for words? Yet words do well
<L n="108"/><TLN n="1886"/>When he that speaks them pleases those that hear.
<L n="109"/><TLN n="1887"/>It is a pretty youth -- not very pretty;
<L n="110"/><TLN n="1888"/>But, sure, he's proud; and yet his pride becomes him.
<L n="111"/><TLN n="1889"/>He'll make a proper man. The best thing in him
<L n="112"/><TLN n="1890"/>Is his complexion; and faster than his tongue
<L n="113"/><TLN n="1891"/>Did make offense, his eye did heal it up.
<L n="114"/><TLN n="1892"/>He is not very tall; yet for his years he's tall;
<L n="115"/><TLN n="1893"/>His leg is but so-so; and yet 'tis well.
<L n="116"/><TLN n="1894"/>There was a pretty redness in his lip,
<L n="117"/><TLN n="1895"/>A little riper and more lusty red
<L n="118"/><TLN n="1896"/>Than that mixed in his cheek; 'twas just the difference
<L n="119"/><TLN n="1897"/>Betwixt the constant red and mingled damask.
<L n="120"/><TLN n="1898"/>There be some women, Silvius, had they marked him
<L n="121"/><TLN n="1899"/>In parcels as I did, would have gone near
<L n="122"/><TLN n="1900"/>To fall in love with him; but, for my part,
<L n="123"/><TLN n="1901"/>I love him not, nor hate him not; and yet
<L n="124"/><TLN n="1902"/>I have more cause to hate him than to love him.
<L n="125"/><TLN n="1903"/>For what had he to do to chide at me?
<L n="126"/><TLN n="1904"/>He said mine eyes were black, and my hair black,
<L n="127"/><TLN n="1905"/>And, now I am remembered, scorned at me.
<L n="128"/><TLN n="1906"/>I marvel why I answered not again.
<L n="129"/><TLN n="1907"/>But that's all one; omittance is no quittance.
<L n="130"/><TLN n="1908"/>I'll write to him a very taunting letter,
<L n="131"/><TLN n="1909"/>And thou shalt bear it. Wilt thou, Silvius?</S>

<L n="132" part="i"/><TLN n="1910"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
Phoebe, with all my heart.</S>

<TLN n="1911"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
<L n="132" part="f"/>I'll write it straight;
<L n="133"/><TLN n="1912"/>The matter's in my head and in my heart.
<L n="134"/><TLN n="1913"/>I will be bitter with him and passing short.
<L n="135"/><TLN n="1914"/>Go with me, Silvius.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>
</MODE>
</SCENE>
</ACT>
<ACT n="4">
<SCENE n="1">

<H2><TLN n="1915"/>[4.1]</H2>
<MODE t="prose">

<TLN n="1916"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Rosalind, Celia, and Jaques.</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="1917"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
I prithee, pretty youth, let me be better acquainted <TLN n="1918"/>with thee.</S>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="1919"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
They say you are a melancholy fellow.</S>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="1920"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
I am so. I do love it better than laughing.</S>

<L n="4"/><TLN n="1921"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Those that are in extremity of either are abominable <TLN n="1922"/>fellows, and betray themselves to every modern <TLN n="1923"/>censure worse than drunkards.</S>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="1924"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Why, 'tis good to be sad and say nothing.</S>

<L n="6"/><TLN n="1925"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Why then, 'tis good to be a post.</S>

<L n="7"/><TLN n="1926"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
I have neither the scholar's melancholy, which <TLN n="1927"/>is emulation, nor the musician's, which is fantastical, <TLN n="1928"/>nor the courtier's, which is proud, nor the soldier's, <TLN n="1929"/>which is ambitious, nor the lawyer's, which is politic, <TLN n="1930"/>nor the lady's, which is nice, nor the lover's, which <TLN n="1931"/>is all these; but it is a melancholy of mine own, compounded <TLN n="1932"/>of many simples, extracted from many objects, <TLN n="1933"/>and indeed the sundry contemplation of my travels, in <TLN n="1934"/>which my often rumination wraps me in a most humorous <TLN n="1935"/>sadness.</S>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="1936"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
A traveler! By my faith, you have great reason <TLN n="1937"/>to be sad. I fear you have sold your own lands <TLN n="1938"/>to see other men's. Then to have seen much and to have <TLN n="1939"/>nothing is to have rich eyes and poor hands.</S>

<L n="9"/><TLN n="1940"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Yes, I have gained my experience.</S>

<TLN n="1941"/><SD t="enter">Enter Orlando.</SD>

<L n="10"/><TLN n="1942"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
And your experience makes you sad. I had rather <TLN n="1943"/>have a fool to make me merry than experience to <TLN n="1944"/>make me sad -- and to travel for it too!</S>

<L n="11"/><TLN n="1945"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Good day, and happiness, dear Rosalind!</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="1946"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Nay, then, God b'wi' you, an you talk in blank <TLN n="1947"/>verse.</S>

<L n="13"/><TLN n="1948"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Farewell, Monsieur Traveler. Look you lisp <TLN n="1949"/><!--TLN moved +1 -->and wear strange suits, disable all the benefits <TLN n="1950"/>of your own country, be out of love with <TLN n="1951"/><!--TLN moved +1 -->your nativity, <TLN n="1951"/> and almost chide God for making you that <TLN n="1952"/>countenance you are, or I will scarce think you have <TLN n="1953"/>swam in a gondola.
<SD t="exit">[Exit Jaques.]</SD>

Why, how now, Orlando, where <TLN n="1954"/>have you been all this while? You a lover? An you <TLN n="1955"/>serve me such another trick, never come in my sight <TLN n="1956"/>more.</S>

<L n="14"/><TLN n="1957"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
My fair Rosalind, I come within an hour of my <TLN n="1958"/>promise.</S>

<L n="15"/><TLN n="1959"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Break an hour's promise in love? He that <TLN n="1960"/>will divide a minute into a thousand parts and break <TLN n="1961"/>but a part of the thousand part of a minute in the affairs <TLN n="1962"/>of love, it may be said of him that Cupid hath clapped <TLN n="1963"/>him o'th' shoulder, but I'll warrant him heart-whole.</S>

<L n="16"/><TLN n="1964"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Pardon me, dear Rosalind.</S>

<L n="17"/><TLN n="1965"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Nay, an you be so tardy, come no more in my <TLN n="1966"/>sight. I had as lief be wooed of a snail.</S>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="1967"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Of a snail?</S>

<L n="19"/><TLN n="1968"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Ay, of a snail; for though he comes slowly, he <TLN n="1969"/>carries his house on his head -- a better jointure, I think, <TLN n="1970"/>than you make a woman. Besides, he brings his destiny <TLN n="1971"/>with him.</S>

<L n="20"/><TLN n="1972"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
What's that?</S>

<L n="21"/><TLN n="1973"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Why, horns, which such as you are fain to be beholding <TLN n="1974"/>to your wives for. But he comes armed in his fortune, <TLN n="1975"/><!--TLN moved +1 -->and prevents the slander of his wife.</S>

<L n="22"/><TLN n="1976"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Virtue is no horn-maker; and my Rosalind is <TLN n="1977"/>virtuous.</S>

<L n="23"/><TLN n="1978"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
And I am your Rosalind.</S>

<L n="24"/><TLN n="1979"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
It pleases him to call you so; but he hath a Rosalind <TLN n="1980"/> of a better leer than you.</S>

<L n="25"/><TLN n="1981"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Come, woo me, woo me, for now I am in a <TLN n="1982"/>holiday humor, and like enough to consent. What <TLN n="1983"/>would you say to me now, an I were your very very <TLN n="1984"/>Rosalind?</S>

<L n="26"/><TLN n="1985"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I would kiss before I spoke.</S>

<L n="27"/><TLN n="1986"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Nay, you were better speak first, and when you <TLN n="1987"/>were graveled for lack of matter, you might take occasion <TLN n="1988"/>to kiss. Very good orators, when they are out, <TLN n="1989"/>they will spit; and for lovers lacking -- God warn us! -- <TLN n="1990"/>matter, the cleanliest shift is to kiss.</S>

<L n="28"/><TLN n="1991"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
How if the kiss be denied?</S>

<L n="29"/><TLN n="1992"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Then she puts you to entreaty, and there begins <TLN n="1993"/>new matter.</S>

<L n="30"/><TLN n="1994"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Who could be out, being before his beloved <TLN n="1995"/>mistress?</S>

<L n="31"/><TLN n="1996"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Marry, that should you, if I were your mistress, <TLN n="1997"/>or I should think my honesty ranker than my wit.</S>

<L n="32"/><TLN n="1998"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
What, of my suit?</S>

<L n="33"/><TLN n="1999"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Not out of your apparel, and yet out of your <TLN n="2000"/>suit. <TLN n="2001"/>Am not I your Rosalind?</S>

<L n="34"/><TLN n="2002"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I take some joy to say you are, because I would <TLN n="2003"/>be talking of her.</S>

<L n="35"/><TLN n="2004"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Well, in her person, I say I will not have you.</S>

<L n="36"/><TLN n="2005"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Then, in mine own person, I die.</S>

<L n="37"/><TLN n="2006"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
No, faith, die by attorney. The poor world is <TLN n="2007"/>almost six thousand years old, and in all this time there <TLN n="2008"/>was not any man died in his own person, videlicet, in <TLN n="2009"/>a love-cause. Troilus had his brains dashed out with a <TLN n="2010"/>Grecian club, yet he did what he could to die before, <TLN n="2011"/>and he is one of the patterns of love. Leander, he would <TLN n="2012"/>have lived many a fair year though Hero had turned <TLN n="2013"/>nun, if it had not been for a hot midsummer night; for, <TLN n="2014"/>good youth, he went but forth to wash him in the Hellespont, <TLN n="2015"/>and, being taken with the cramp, was drowned; <TLN n="2016"/>and the foolish chroniclers of that age found it was -- <TLN n="2017"/>Hero of Sestos. But these are all lies. Men have died <TLN n="2018"/>from time to time, and worms have eaten them, but not <TLN n="2019"/>for love.</S>

<L n="38"/><TLN n="2020"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I would not have my right Rosalind of this mind, <TLN n="2021"/>for, I protest, her frown might kill me.</S>

<L n="39"/><TLN n="2022"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
By this hand, it will not kill a fly. But come, <TLN n="2023"/>now I will be your Rosalind in a more coming-on disposition; <TLN n="2024"/>and ask me what you will, I will grant it.</S>

<L n="40"/><TLN n="2025"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Then love me, Rosalind.</S>

<L n="41"/><TLN n="2026"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Yes, faith, will I, Fridays and Saturdays and all.</S>

<L n="42"/><TLN n="2027"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
And wilt thou have me?</S>

<L n="43"/><TLN n="2028"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Ay, and twenty such.</S>

<L n="44"/><TLN n="2029"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
What sayest thou?</S>

<L n="45"/><TLN n="2030"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Are you not good?</S>

<L n="46"/><TLN n="2031"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I hope so.</S>

<L n="47"/><TLN n="2032"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Why then, can one desire too much of a <TLN n="2033"/>good thing? -- Come, sister, you shall be the priest, <TLN n="2034"/>and marry us. -- Give me your hand, Orlando. -- What do you <TLN n="2035"/>say, sister?</S>

<L n="48"/><TLN n="2036"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Pray thee, marry us.</S>

<L n="49"/><TLN n="2037"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
I cannot say the words.</S>

<L n="50"/><TLN n="2038"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
You must begin "Will you, Orlando --"</S>

<L n="51"/><TLN n="2039"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Go to. -- Will you, Orlando, have to wife this <TLN n="2040"/>Rosalind?</S>

<L n="52"/><TLN n="2041"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I will.</S>

<L n="53"/><TLN n="2042"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Ay, but when?</S>

<L n="54"/><TLN n="2043"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Why, now, as fast as she can marry us.</S>

<L n="55"/><TLN n="2044"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Then you must say, "I take thee, Rosalind, for <TLN n="2045"/>wife."</S>

<L n="56"/><TLN n="2046"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I take thee, Rosalind, for wife.</S>

<L n="57"/><TLN n="2047"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I might ask you for your commission; <TLN n="2048"/>but I do take thee, Orlando, for my husband. There's a <TLN n="2049"/>girl goes before the priest; and, certainly, a woman's <TLN n="2050"/>thought runs before her actions.</S>

<L n="58"/><TLN n="2051"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
So do all thoughts; they are winged.</S>

<L n="59"/><TLN n="2052"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Now tell me how long you would have her, after <TLN n="2053"/>you have possessed her.</S>

<L n="60"/><TLN n="2054"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
For ever and a day.</S>

<L n="61"/><TLN n="2055"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Say "a day" without the "ever." No, no, Orlando, men <TLN n="2056"/>are April when they woo, December when they wed; <TLN n="2057"/>maids are May when they are maids, but the sky changes <TLN n="2058"/>when they are wives. I will be more jealous of <TLN n="2059"/>thee than a Barbary cock-pigeon over his hen, more clamorous <TLN n="2060"/><!--TLN moved +1 -->than a parrot against rain, more newfangled <TLN n="2061"/>than an ape, more giddy in my desires than a monkey. <TLN n="2062"/>I will weep for nothing, like Diana in the fountain, <TLN n="2063"/>and I will do that when you are disposed to be merry; <TLN n="2064"/>I will laugh like a hyena, and that when thou art inclined <TLN n="2065"/>to sleep.</S>

<L n="62"/><TLN n="2066"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
But will my Rosalind do so?</S>

<L n="63"/><TLN n="2067"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
By my life, she will do as I do.</S>

<L n="64"/><TLN n="2068"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Oh, but she is wise.</S>

<L n="65"/><TLN n="2069"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Or else she could not have the wit to do this. <TLN n="2070"/>The wiser, the waywarder. Make the doors upon a woman's <TLN n="2071"/>wit, and it will out at the casement; shut that, and <TLN n="2072"/>'twill out at the key-hole; stop that, 'twill fly with the <TLN n="2073"/>smoke out at the chimney.</S>

<L n="66"/><TLN n="2074"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
A man that had a wife with such a wit, he might <TLN n="2075"/>say, "Wit, whither wilt?'"</S>

<L n="67"/><TLN n="2076"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Nay, you might keep that check for it till you <TLN n="2077"/>met your wife's wit going to your neighbor's bed.</S>

<L n="68"/><TLN n="2078"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
And what wit could wit have to excuse that?</S>

<L n="69"/><TLN n="2079"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Marry, to say she came to seek you there. You <TLN n="2080"/>shall never take her without her answer, unless you take her<TLN n="2081"/><!--moved +1--> without her tongue. Oh, that woman that cannot <TLN n="2082"/>make her fault her husband's occasion, let her never nurse <TLN n="2083"/>her child herself, for she will breed it like a fool!</S>

<L n="70"/><TLN n="2084"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
For these two hours, Rosalind, I will leave thee.</S>

<L n="71"/><TLN n="2085"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Alas, dear love, I cannot lack thee two hours!</S>

<L n="72"/><TLN n="2086"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I must attend the Duke at dinner. By two o'clock <TLN n="2087"/>I will be with thee again.</S>

<L n="73"/><TLN n="2088"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Ay, go your ways, go your ways. I knew what <TLN n="2089"/>you would prove; my friends told me as much, and I <TLN n="2090"/>thought no less. That flattering tongue of yours won <TLN n="2091"/>me. 'Tis but one cast away, and so, come death! Two o'clock <TLN n="2092"/>is your hour?</S>

<L n="74"/><TLN n="2093"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Ay, sweet Rosalind.</S>

<L n="75"/><TLN n="2094"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
By my troth, and in good earnest, and <TLN n="2095"/><!--TLN moved -2 -->so God mend me, and by all pretty oaths that are not dangerous, <TLN n="2096"/>if you break one jot of your promise, or come one <TLN n="2097"/>minute behind your hour, I will think you the most <TLN n="2098"/>pathetical break-promise, and the most hollow lover, <TLN n="2099"/>and the most unworthy of her you call Rosalind, that <TLN n="2100"/>may be chosen out of the gross band of the unfaithful. <TLN n="2101"/>Therefore beware my censure, and keep your <TLN n="2102"/>promise.</S>

<L n="76"/><TLN n="2103"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
With no less religion than if thou wert indeed <TLN n="2104"/>my Rosalind. So, adieu.</S>

<L n="77"/><TLN n="2105"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Well, Time is the old justice that examines all <TLN n="2106"/>such offenders, and let Time try. Adieu.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exit [Orlando].</SD>

<L n="78"/><TLN n="2107"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
You have simply misused our sex in your love-prate. <TLN n="2108"/>We must have your doublet and hose plucked over <TLN n="2109"/>your head, and show the world what the bird hath done <TLN n="2110"/>to her own nest.</S>

<L n="79"/><TLN n="2111"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Oh, coz, coz, coz, my pretty little coz, that thou <TLN n="2112"/>didst know how many fathom deep I am in love! But <TLN n="2113"/>it cannot be sounded; my affection hath an unknown <TLN n="2114"/>bottom, like the Bay of Portugal.</S>

<L n="80"/><TLN n="2115"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Or rather, bottomless, that as fast as you pour <TLN n="2116"/>affection in, it runs out.</S>

<L n="81"/><TLN n="2117"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
No, that same wicked bastard of Venus, that was <TLN n="2118"/>begot of thought, conceived of spleen, and born of <TLN n="2119"/>madness, that blind rascally boy that abuses everyone's <TLN n="2120"/>eyes because his own are out, let him be judge <TLN n="2121"/>how deep I am in love. I'll tell thee, Aliena, I cannot be <TLN n="2122"/>out of the sight of Orlando. I'll go find a shadow, and <TLN n="2123"/>sigh till he come.</S>

<L n="82"/><TLN n="2124"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
And I'll sleep.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="2">
<H2><TLN n="2125"/>[4.2]</H2>
<TLN n="2126"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Jaques and Lords, [outfitted as] foresters.</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="2127"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Which is he that killed the deer?</S>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="2128"/><S><SP>First Lord</SP>
Sir, it was I.</S>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="2129"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Let's present him to the Duke, like a Roman conqueror; <TLN n="2130"/><!--TLN moved +1 -->and it would do well to set the deer's <TLN n="2131"/>horns upon his head for a branch of victory. Have you <TLN n="2132"/>no song, forester, for this purpose?</S>

<L n="4"/><TLN n="2133"/><S><SP>Second Lord</SP>
Yes, sir.</S>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="2134"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Sing it. 'Tis no matter how it be in tune, so it <TLN n="2135"/>make noise enough.</S>
<TLN n="2136"/><SD t="sound">Music.</SD>

<LD>SONG.</LD>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">
<VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="6"/><TLN n="2137"/><S><SP>Second Lord</SP>
<SD t="sound">[Sings]</SD>
What shall he have that killed the deer?
<L n="7"/><TLN n="2138"/>His leather skin and horns to wear.
<L n="8"/><TLN n="2139"/><SPACE n="3"/>Then sing him home.
<SD t="sound">(The rest shall bear this burden:)</SD>
<L n="9"/><TLN n="2140"/>Take thou no scorn to wear the horn;
<L n="10"/><TLN n="2141"/>It was a crest ere thou wast born.

<L n="11"/><TLN n="2142"/><SPACE n="3"/>Thy father's father wore it;
<L n="12"/><TLN n="2143"/><SPACE n="3"/>And thy father bore it.
<SD t="sound">(The rest shall bear this burden:)</SD>
<L n="13"/><TLN n="2144"/>The horn, the horn, the lusty horn,
<L n="14"/><TLN n="2145"/>Is not a thing to laugh to scorn.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>
</VERSEQUOTE>
</MODE>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="3">
<H2><TLN n="2146"/>[4.3]</H2>
<TLN n="2147"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Rosalind and Celia.</SD>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="1"/><TLN n="2148"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
How say you now? Is it not past two o'clock? <TLN n="2149"/>And here much Orlando!</S>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="2150"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
I warrant you, with pure love and troubled brain

<TLN n="2151"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Silvius [with a letter].</SD>

<TLN n="2152"/>he hath ta'en his bow and arrows and is gone forth -- <TLN n="2153"/>to sleep. Look who comes here.</S>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="3"/><TLN n="2154"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Rosalind]</SD>
My errand is to you, fair youth.
<L n="4"/><TLN n="2155"/>My gentle Phoebe did bid me give you this.
<SD t="action">[He gives the letter.]</SD>
<L n="5"/><TLN n="2156"/>I know not the contents, but, as I guess,
<L n="6"/><TLN n="2157"/>By the stern brow and waspish action
<L n="7"/><TLN n="2158"/>Which she did use as she was writing of it,
<L n="8"/><TLN n="2159"/>It bears an angry tenor. Pardon me,
<L n="9"/><TLN n="2160"/>I am but as a guiltless messenger.</S>

<L n="10"/><TLN n="2161"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<SD t="action">[Examining the letter]</SD>
Patience herself would startle at this letter
<L n="11"/><TLN n="2162"/>And play the swaggerer. Bear this, bear all!
<L n="12"/><TLN n="2163"/>She says I am not fair, that I lack manners;
<L n="13"/><TLN n="2164"/>She calls me proud, and that she could not love me
<L n="14"/><TLN n="2165"/>Were man as rare as Phoenix. 'Od's my will!
<L n="15"/><TLN n="2166"/>Her love is not the hare that I do hunt.
<L n="16"/><TLN n="2167"/>Why writes she so to me? Well, shepherd, well,
<L n="17"/><TLN n="2168"/>This is a letter of your own device.</S>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="2169"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
No, I protest, I know not the contents.
<L n="19" part="i"/><TLN n="2170"/>Phoebe did write it.</S>

<TLN n="2171"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<L n="19" part="f"/>Come, come, you are a fool,
<L n="20"/><TLN n="2172"/>And turned into the extremity of love.
<L n="21"/><TLN n="2173"/>I saw her hand; she has a leathern hand,
<L n="22"/><TLN n="2174"/>A freestone-colored hand. I verily did think
<L n="23"/><TLN n="2175"/>That her old gloves were on, but 'twas her hands;
<L n="24"/><TLN n="2176"/>She has a huswife's hand -- but that's no matter.
<L n="25"/><TLN n="2177"/>I say she never did invent this letter;
<L n="26"/><TLN n="2178"/>This is a man's invention, and his hand.</S>

<L n="27"/><TLN n="2179"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
Sure it is hers.</S>

<L n="28"/><TLN n="2180"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Why, 'tis a boisterous and a cruel style,
<L n="29"/><TLN n="2181"/>A style for challengers. Why, she defies me,
<L n="30"/><TLN n="2182"/>Like Turk to Christian. Women's gentle brain
<L n="31"/><TLN n="2183"/>Could not drop forth such giant-rude invention,
<L n="32"/><TLN n="2184"/>Such Ethiop words, blacker in their effect
<L n="33"/><TLN n="2185"/>Than in their countenance. Will you hear the letter?</S>

<L n="34"/><TLN n="2186"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
So please you, for I never heard it yet;
<L n="35"/><TLN n="2187"/>Yet heard too much of Phoebe's cruelty.</S>

<L n="36"/><TLN n="2188"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
She Phoebes me. Mark how the tyrant writes.
<SD t="action">(Read)</SD>
<VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="37"/><TLN n="2189"/>"Art thou god to shepherd turned,
<L n="38"/><TLN n="2190"/>That a maiden's heart hath burned?"
</VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="39"/><TLN n="2191"/>Can a woman rail thus?</S>

<L n="40"/><TLN n="2192"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
Call you this railing?</S>
<L n="41"/><TLN n="2193"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<SD t="action">(Read)</SD>
<VERSEQUOTE>
"Why, thy godhead laid apart,
<L n="42"/><TLN n="2194"/>Warr'st thou with a woman's heart?"
</VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="43"/><TLN n="2195"/>Did you ever hear such railing?
<VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="44"/><TLN n="2196"/>"Whiles the eye of man did woo me,
<L n="45"/><TLN n="2197"/>That could do no vengeance to me."
</VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="46"/><TLN n="2198"/>Meaning me a beast.
<VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="47"/><TLN n="2199"/>"If the scorn of your bright eyne
<L n="48"/><TLN n="2200"/>Have power to raise such love in mine,
<L n="49"/><TLN n="2201"/>Alack, in me what strange effect
<L n="50"/><TLN n="2202"/>Would they work in mild aspect!
<L n="51"/><TLN n="2203"/>Whiles you chid me, I did love;
<L n="52"/><TLN n="2204"/>How then might your prayers move!
<L n="53"/><TLN n="2205"/>He that brings this love to thee
<L n="54"/><TLN n="2206"/>Little knows this love in me;
<L n="55"/><TLN n="2207"/>And by him seal up thy mind,
<L n="56"/><TLN n="2208"/>Whether that thy youth and kind
<L n="57"/><TLN n="2209"/>Will the faithful offer take
<L n="58"/><TLN n="2210"/>Of me and all that I can make;
<L n="59"/><TLN n="2211"/>Or else by him my love deny,
<L n="60"/><TLN n="2212"/>And then I'll study how to die."</S>
</VERSEQUOTE>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="61"/><TLN n="2213"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
Call you this chiding?</S>

<L n="62"/><TLN n="2214"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Alas, poor shepherd!</S>

<L n="63"/><TLN n="2215"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Do you pity him? No, he deserves no pity. <TLN n="2216"/>Wilt thou love such a woman? What, to make thee an instrument, <TLN n="2217"/>and play false strains upon thee! Not to be endured! <TLN n="2218"/>Well, go your way to her, for I see love hath <TLN n="2219"/>made thee a tame snake, and say this to her: that if she <TLN n="2220"/>love me, I charge her to love thee; if she will not, I will <TLN n="2221"/>never have her unless thou entreat for her. If you be a <TLN n="2222"/>true lover, hence, and not a word; for here comes more <TLN n="2223"/>company.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exit Silvius.</SD>

<TLN n="2224"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Oliver.</SD>
</MODE> 
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="64"/><TLN n="2225"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Good morrow, fair ones. Pray you, if you know,
<L n="65"/><TLN n="2226"/>Where in the purlieus of this forest stands
<L n="66"/><TLN n="2227"/>A sheepcote fenced about with olive trees?</S>

<L n="67"/><TLN n="2228"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
West of this place, down in the neighbor bottom,
<L n="68"/><TLN n="2229"/>The rank of osiers by the murmuring stream
<L n="69"/><TLN n="2230"/>Left on your right hand brings you to the place.
<L n="70"/><TLN n="2231"/>But at this hour the house doth keep itself;
<L n="71"/><TLN n="2232"/>There's none within.</S>

<L n="72"/><TLN n="2233"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
If that an eye may profit by a tongue,
<L n="73"/><TLN n="2234"/>Then should I know you by description,
<L n="74"/><TLN n="2235"/>Such garments, and such years: "The boy is fair,
<L n="75"/><TLN n="2236"/>Of female favor, and bestows himself
<L n="76"/><TLN n="2237"/>Like a ripe sister; the woman, low
<L n="77"/><TLN n="2238"/>And browner than her brother." Are not you
<L n="78"/><TLN n="2239"/>The owner of the house I did inquire for?</S>

<L n="79"/><TLN n="2240"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
It is no boast, being asked, to say we are.</S>

<L n="80"/><TLN n="2241"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Orlando doth commend him to you both,
<L n="81"/><TLN n="2242"/>And to that youth he calls his Rosalind
<L n="82"/><TLN n="2243"/>He sends this bloody napkin. Are you he?</S>
<SD t="action">[He produces a bloody handkerchief.]</SD>

<L n="83"/><TLN n="2244"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I am. What must we understand by this?</S>

<L n="84"/><TLN n="2245"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Some of my shame, if you will know of me
<L n="85"/><TLN n="2246"/>What man I am, and how, and why, and where
<L n="86" part="i"/><TLN n="2247"/>This handkerchief was stained.</S>

<TLN n="2248"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
<L n="86" part="f"/>I pray you, tell it.</S>

<L n="87"/><TLN n="2249"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
When last the young Orlando parted from you,
<L n="88"/><TLN n="2250"/>He left a promise to return again
<L n="89"/><TLN n="2251"/>Within an hour; and, pacing through the forest,
<L n="90"/><TLN n="2252"/>Chewing the food of sweet and bitter fancy,
<L n="91"/><TLN n="2253"/>Lo, what befell! He threw his eye aside,
<L n="92"/><TLN n="2254"/>And mark what object did present itself.
<L n="93"/><TLN n="2255"/>Under an old oak, whose boughs were mossed with age
<L n="94"/><TLN n="2256"/>And high top bald with dry antiquity,
<L n="95"/><TLN n="2257"/>A wretched ragged man, o'ergrown with hair,
<L n="96"/><TLN n="2258"/>Lay sleeping on his back. About his neck
<L n="97"/><TLN n="2259"/>A green and gilded snake had wreathed itself,
<L n="98"/><TLN n="2260"/>Who with her head, nimble in threats, approached
<L n="99"/><TLN n="2261"/>The opening of his mouth; but suddenly,
<L n="100"/><TLN n="2262"/>Seeing Orlando, it unlinked itself
<L n="101"/><TLN n="2263"/>And with indented glides did slip away
<L n="102"/><TLN n="2264"/>Into a bush, under which bush's shade
<L n="103"/><TLN n="2265"/>A lioness, with udders all drawn dry,
<L n="104"/><TLN n="2266"/>Lay couching, head on ground, with catlike watch,
<L n="105"/><TLN n="2267"/>When that the sleeping man should stir; for 'tis
<L n="106"/><TLN n="2268"/>The royal disposition of that beast
<L n="107"/><TLN n="2269"/>To prey on nothing that doth seem as dead.
<L n="108"/><TLN n="2270"/>This seen, Orlando did approach the man,
<L n="109"/><TLN n="2271"/>And found it was his brother, his elder brother.</S>

<L n="110"/><TLN n="2272"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Oh, I have heard him speak of that same brother,
<L n="111"/><TLN n="2273"/>And he did render him the most unnatural
<L n="112" part="i"/><TLN n="2274"/>That lived amongst men.</S>

<TLN n="2275"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
<L n="112" part="f"/>And well he might so do,
<L n="113"/><TLN n="2276"/>For well I know he was unnatural.</S>

<L n="114"/><TLN n="2277"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
But to Orlando: did he leave him there,
<L n="115"/><TLN n="2278"/>Food to the sucked and hungry lioness?</S>

<L n="116"/><TLN n="2279"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Twice did he turn his back, and purposed so;
<L n="117"/><TLN n="2280"/>But kindness, nobler ever than revenge,
<L n="118"/><TLN n="2281"/>And nature, stronger than his just occasion,
<L n="119"/><TLN n="2282"/>Made him give battle to the lioness,
<L n="120"/><TLN n="2283"/>Who quickly fell before him; in which hurtling
<L n="121"/><TLN n="2284"/>From miserable slumber I awaked.</S>

<L n="122" part="i"/><TLN n="2285"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Are you his brother?</S>

<TLN n="2286"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<L n="122" part="f"/>Was't you he rescued?</S>

<L n="123"/><TLN n="2287"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Was't you that did so oft contrive to kill him?</S>

<L n="124"/><TLN n="2288"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
'Twas I; but 'tis not I. I do not shame
<L n="125"/><TLN n="2289"/>To tell you what I was, since my conversion
<L n="126"/><TLN n="2290"/>So sweetly tastes, being the thing I am.</S>

<L n="127" part="i"/><TLN n="2291"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
But for the bloody napkin?</S>

<L n="127" part="f"/><TLN n="2292"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
By and by.
<L n="128"/><TLN n="2293"/>When from the first to last, betwixt us two,
<L n="129"/><TLN n="2294"/>Tears our recountments had most kindly bathed,
<L n="130"/><TLN n="2295"/>As how I came into that desert place,
<L n="131"/><TLN n="2296"/>In brief, he led me to the gentle Duke,
<L n="132"/><TLN n="2297"/>Who gave me fresh array and entertainment,
<L n="133"/><TLN n="2298"/>Committing me unto my brother's love;
<L n="134"/><TLN n="2299"/>Who led me instantly unto his cave,
<L n="135"/><TLN n="2300"/>There stripped himself, and here upon his arm
<L n="136"/><TLN n="2301"/>The lioness had torn some flesh away,
<L n="137"/><TLN n="2302"/>Which all this while had bled; and now he fainted,
<L n="138"/><TLN n="2303"/>And cried, in fainting, upon Rosalind.
<L n="139"/><TLN n="2304"/>Brief, I recovered him, bound up his wound,
<L n="140"/><TLN n="2305"/>And after some small space, being strong at heart,
<L n="141"/><TLN n="2306"/>He sent me hither, stranger as I am,
<L n="142"/><TLN n="2307"/>To tell this story, that you might excuse
<L n="143"/><TLN n="2308"/>His broken promise, and to give this napkin,
<L n="144"/><TLN n="2309"/>Dyed in this blood, unto the shepherd youth
<L n="145"/><TLN n="2310"/>That he in sport doth call his Rosalind.</S>
<SD t="action">[Rosalind swoons.]</SD>

<L n="146"/><TLN n="2311"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Why, how now, Ganymede, sweet Ganymede!</S>

<L n="147"/><TLN n="2312"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Many will swoon when they do look on blood.</S>

<L n="148"/><TLN n="2313"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
There is more in it. -- Cousin Ganymede!</S>

<L n="149"/><TLN n="2314"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Look, he recovers.</S>

<L n="150"/><TLN n="2315"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I would I were at home.</S>

<L n="151"/><TLN n="2316"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
We'll lead you thither. --
<L n="152"/><TLN n="2317"/>I pray you, will you take him by the arm?</S>
<SD t="action">[They help Rosalind up.]</SD>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="153"/><TLN n="2318"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Be of good cheer, youth. You a man? <TLN n="2319"/>You lack a man's heart.</S>

<L n="154"/><TLN n="2320"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I do so, I confess it. <TLN n="2321"/>Ah, sirrah, a body would think this was well counterfeited. <TLN n="2322"/>I pray you tell your brother how well I counterfeited. <TLN n="2323"/>Heigh-ho!</S>

<L n="155"/><TLN n="2324"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
This was not counterfeit. There is too great testimony <TLN n="2325"/>in your complexion that it was a passion of earnest.<TLN n="2326"/><!--TLN moved +1 --></S>

<L n="156"/><TLN n="2327"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Counterfeit, I assure you.</S>

<L n="157"/><TLN n="2328"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Well then, take a good heart and counterfeit to <TLN n="2329"/>be a man.</S>

<L n="158"/><TLN n="2330"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
So I do; but, i'faith, I should have been a <TLN n="2331"/>woman by right.</S>

<L n="159"/><TLN n="2332"/><S><SP>Celia</SP>
Come, you look paler and paler. Pray you, draw <TLN n="2333"/>homewards. -- Good sir, go with us.</S>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="160"/><TLN n="2334"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
That will I, for I must bear answer back
<TLN n="2335"/>How you excuse my brother, Rosalind.</S>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="161"/><TLN n="2336"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I shall devise something. But, I pray you, commend <TLN n="2337"/>my counterfeiting to him. Will you go?</S>
<TLN n="2338"/><SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>

</SCENE>
</ACT>
<ACT n="5">
<SCENE n="1">
<H2><TLN n="2339"/>[5.1]</H2>
<TLN n="2340"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Touchstone and Audrey.</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="2341"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
We shall find a time, Audrey. Patience, gentle <TLN n="2342"/>Audrey.</S>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="2343"/><S><SP>Audrey</SP>
Faith, the priest was good enough, for all <TLN n="2344"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->the old gentleman's saying.</S>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="2345"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
A most wicked Sir Oliver, Audrey, a most vile <TLN n="2346"/>Mar-text. But Audrey, there is a youth here in the <TLN n="2347"/>forest lays claim to you.</S>

<L n="4"/><TLN n="2348"/><S><SP>Audrey</SP>
Ay, I know who 'tis. He hath no interest in me <TLN n="2349"/>in the world. Here comes the man you mean.</S>

<TLN n="2350"/><SD t="entrance">Enter William.</SD>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="2351"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
It is meat and drink to me to see a clown. By <TLN n="2352"/>my troth, we that have good wits have much to answer <TLN n="2353"/>for. We shall be flouting; we cannot hold.</S>

<L n="6"/><TLN n="2354"/><S><SP>William</SP>
Good ev'n, Audrey.</S>

<L n="7"/><TLN n="2355"/><S><SP>Audrey</SP>
God ye good ev'n, William.</S>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="2356"/><S><SP>William</SP>
And good ev'n to you, sir.</S>
<SD t="action">[He removes his hat.]</SD>

<L n="9"/><TLN n="2357"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Good ev'n, gentle friend. Cover thy head, cover <TLN n="2358"/>thy head. Nay, prithee be covered. How old are you, <TLN n="2359"/>friend?</S>

<L n="10"/><TLN n="2360"/><S><SP>William</SP>
Five-and-twenty, sir.</S>

<L n="11"/><TLN n="2361"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
A ripe age. Is thy name William?</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="2362"/><S><SP>William</SP>
William, sir.</S>

<L n="13"/><TLN n="2363"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
A fair name. Wast born i'th'forest here?</S>

<L n="14"/><TLN n="2364"/><S><SP>William</SP>
Ay, sir, I thank God.</S>

<L n="15"/><TLN n="2365"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
"Thank God" -- a good answer. <TLN n="2366"/>Art rich?</S>

<L n="16"/><TLN n="2367"/><S><SP>William</SP>
Faith, sir, so-so.</S>

<L n="17"/><TLN n="2368"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
"So-so" is good, very good, very excellent good; <TLN n="2369"/>and yet it is not; it is but so-so. <TLN n="2370"/>Art thou wise?</S>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="2371"/><S><SP>William</SP>
Ay, sir, I have a pretty wit.</S>

<L n="19"/><TLN n="2372"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Why, thou say'st well. I do now remember a saying: <TLN n="2373"/>"The fool doth think he is wise, but the wise man <TLN n="2374"/>knows himself to be a fool." The heathen philosopher, <TLN n="2375"/>when he had a desire to eat a grape, would open <TLN n="2376"/>his lips when he put it into his mouth, meaning thereby <TLN n="2377"/>that grapes were made to eat and lips to open. <TLN n="2378"/>You do love this maid?</S>

<L n="20"/><TLN n="2379"/><S><SP>William</SP>
I do, sir.</S>

<L n="21"/><TLN n="2380"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Give me your hand. Art thou learned?</S>

<L n="22"/><TLN n="2381"/><S><SP>William</SP>
No, sir.</S>

<L n="23"/><TLN n="2382"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Then learn this of me: to have is to have. For <TLN n="2383"/>it is a figure in rhetoric that drink, being poured out <TLN n="2384"/>of a cup into a glass, by filling the one doth empty the <TLN n="2385"/>other; for all your writers do consent that ipse is he. <TLN n="2386"/>Now, you are not ipse, for I am he.</S>

<L n="24"/><TLN n="2387"/><S><SP>William</SP>
Which he, sir?</S>

<L n="25"/><TLN n="2388"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
He, sir, that must marry this woman. Therefore, <TLN n="2389"/>you clown, abandon -- which is in the vulgar "leave" -- the <TLN n="2390"/>society -- which in the boorish is "company" -- of this female -- <TLN n="2391"/>which in the common is "woman"; which together <TLN n="2392"/>is: abandon the society of this female, or, clown, <TLN n="2393"/>thou perishest; or, to thy better understanding, diest; or, <TLN n="2394"/>to wit, I kill thee, make thee away, translate thy life into <TLN n="2395"/>death, thy liberty into bondage. I will deal in poison <TLN n="2396"/>with thee, or in bastinado, or in steel; I will bandy <TLN n="2397"/>with thee in faction, I will o'er-run thee with policy; I <TLN n="2398"/>will kill thee a hundred and fifty ways. Therefore tremble <TLN n="2399"/>and depart.</S>

<L n="26"/><TLN n="2400"/><S><SP>Audrey</SP>
Do, good William.</S>

<L n="27"/><TLN n="2401"/><S><SP>William</SP>
God rest you merry, sir.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exit.</SD>

<TLN n="2402"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Corin.</SD>

<L n="28"/><TLN n="2403"/><S><SP>Corin</SP>
Our master and mistress seeks you. Come away, <TLN n="2404"/>away!</S>

<L n="29"/><TLN n="2405"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Trip, Audrey, trip, Audrey! -- I attend, <TLN n="2406"/>I attend.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="2">
<H2><TLN n="2407"/>[5.2]</H2>
<TLN n="2408"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Orlando and Oliver.</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="2409"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Is't possible that on so little acquaintance you <TLN n="2410"/>should like her? That, but seeing, you should love her? <TLN n="2411"/>And loving, woo? And, wooing, she should grant? And <TLN n="2412"/>will you persevere to enjoy her?</S>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="2413"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
Neither call the giddiness of it in question, the <TLN n="2414"/>poverty of her, the small acquaintance, my sudden wooing, <TLN n="2415"/>nor her sudden consenting; but say with me, "I love <TLN n="2416"/>Aliena"; say with her that she loves me; consent with both <TLN n="2417"/>that we may enjoy each other. It shall be to your <TLN n="2418"/>good; for my father's house and all the revenue that <TLN n="2419"/>was old Sir Rowland's will I estate upon you, and here <TLN n="2420"/>live and die a shepherd.</S>

<TLN n="2421"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Rosalind.</SD>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="2422"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
You have my consent. <TLN n="2423"/>Let your wedding be tomorrow. Thither will I <TLN n="2424"/>invite the Duke and all 's contented followers. <TLN n="2425"/>Go you and prepare Aliena; for, look you, <TLN n="2426"/>here comes my Rosalind.</S>

<L n="4"/><TLN n="2427"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
God save you, brother.</S>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="2428"/><S><SP>Oliver</SP>
And you, fair sister.</S>
<SD t="exit">[Exit.]</SD>

<L n="6"/><TLN n="2429"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
O my dear Orlando, how it grieves me to see <TLN n="2430"/>thee wear thy heart in a scarf!</S>

<L n="7"/><TLN n="2431"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
It is my arm.</S>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="2432"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I thought thy heart had been wounded with <TLN n="2433"/>the claws of a lion.</S>

<L n="9"/><TLN n="2434"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Wounded it is, but with the eyes of a lady.</S>

<L n="10"/><TLN n="2435"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Did your brother tell you how I counterfeited <TLN n="2436"/>to swoon when he showed me your handkerchief?</S>

<L n="11"/><TLN n="2437"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Ay, and greater wonders than that.</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="2438"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Oh, I know where you are. Nay, 'tis true. There <TLN n="2439"/>was never anything so sudden but the fight of two rams <TLN n="2440"/><!--TLN moved +1 -->and Caesar's thrasonical brag of "I came, saw, <TLN n="2441"/>and overcame." For your brother and my sister no sooner met <TLN n="2442"/>but they looked; no sooner looked but they <TLN n="2443"/>loved; no sooner loved but they sighed; no sooner sighed <TLN n="2444"/>but they asked one another the reason; no sooner knew <TLN n="2445"/>the reason but they sought the remedy; and in these <TLN n="2446"/>degrees have they made a pair of stairs to marriage, <TLN n="2447"/>which they will climb incontinent, or else be incontinent <TLN n="2448"/>before marriage. They are in the very wrath of <TLN n="2449"/>love, and they will together. Clubs cannot part <TLN n="2450"/>them.</S>

<L n="13"/><TLN n="2451"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
They shall be married tomorrow; and I will <TLN n="2452"/>bid the Duke to the nuptial. But, oh, how bitter a thing <TLN n="2453"/>it is to look into happiness through another man's eyes! <TLN n="2454"/>By so much the more shall I tomorrow be at the height <TLN n="2455"/>of heart-heaviness, by how much I shall think my brother <TLN n="2456"/>happy in having what he wishes for.</S>

<L n="14"/><TLN n="2457"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Why, then, tomorrow I cannot serve your turn <TLN n="2458"/>for Rosalind?</S>

<L n="15"/><TLN n="2459"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I can live no longer by thinking.</S>

<L n="16"/><TLN n="2460"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I will weary you, then, no longer with idle talking. <TLN n="2461"/>Know of me, then -- for now I speak to some purpose -- <TLN n="2462"/>that I know you are a gentleman of good conceit. <TLN n="2463"/>I speak not this that you should bear a good opinion <TLN n="2464"/>of my knowledge, insomuch I say I know you are; neither <TLN n="2465"/>do I labor for a greater esteem than may in some <TLN n="2466"/>little measure draw a belief from you to do yourself <TLN n="2467"/>good, and not to grace me. Believe then, if you please, <TLN n="2468"/>that I can do strange things. I have, since I was three <TLN n="2469"/>year old, conversed with a magician, most profound in <TLN n="2470"/>his art and yet not damnable. If you do love Rosalind <TLN n="2471"/>so near the heart as your gesture cries it out, when your <TLN n="2472"/>brother marries Aliena shall you marry her. I know into <TLN n="2473"/>what straits of fortune she is driven, and it is not impossible <TLN n="2474"/>to me, if it appear not inconvenient to you, <TLN n="2475"/>to set her before your eyes tomorrow, human as she is, <TLN n="2476"/>and without any danger.</S>

<L n="17"/><TLN n="2477"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Speak'st thou in sober meanings?</S>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="2478"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
By my life, I do, which I tender dearly, though <TLN n="2479"/>I say I am a magician. Therefore put you in your best array, <TLN n="2480"/>bid your friends; for if you will be married tomorrow, <TLN n="2481"/>you shall; and to Rosalind, if you will.

<TLN n="2482"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Silvius and Phoebe.</SD>

<TLN n="2483"/>Look, here comes a lover of mine, and a lover of hers.</S>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="19"/><TLN n="2484"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Rosalind]</SD>
Youth, you have done me much ungentleness
<L n="20"/><TLN n="2485"/>To show the letter that I writ to you.</S>

<L n="21"/><TLN n="2486"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I care not if I have. It is my study
<L n="22"/><TLN n="2487"/>To seem despiteful and ungentle to you.
<L n="23"/><TLN n="2488"/>You are there followed by a faithful shepherd;
<L n="24"/><TLN n="2489"/>Look upon him, love him; he worships you.</S>

<L n="25"/><TLN n="2490"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Silvius]</SD>
Good shepherd, tell this youth what 'tis to love.</S>

<L n="26"/><TLN n="2491"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
It is to be all made of sighs and tears;
<L n="27"/><TLN n="2492"/>And so am I for Phoebe.</S>

<L n="28"/><TLN n="2493"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
And I for Ganymede.</S>

<L n="29"/><TLN n="2494"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
And I for Rosalind.</S>

<L n="30"/><TLN n="2495"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
And I for no woman.</S>

<L n="31"/><TLN n="2496"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
It is to be all made of faith and service;
<L n="32"/><TLN n="2497"/>And so am I for Phoebe.</S>

<L n="33"/><TLN n="2498"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
And I for Ganymede.</S>

<L n="34"/><TLN n="2499"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
And I for Rosalind.</S>

<L n="35"/><TLN n="2500"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
And I for no woman.</S>

<L n="36"/><TLN n="2501"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
It is to be all made of fantasy,
<L n="37"/><TLN n="2502"/>All made of passion, and all made of wishes;
<L n="38"/><TLN n="2503"/>All adoration, duty, and observance,
<L n="39"/><TLN n="2504"/>All humbleness, all patience and impatience,
<L n="40"/><TLN n="2505"/>All purity, all trial, all obedience;
<L n="41"/><TLN n="2506"/>And so am I for Phoebe.</S>

<L n="42"/><TLN n="2507"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
And so am I for Ganymede.</S>

<L n="43"/><TLN n="2508"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
And so am I for Rosalind.</S>

<L n="44"/><TLN n="2509"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
And so am I for no woman.</S>

<L n="45"/><TLN n="2510"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Rosalind]</SD>
If this be so, why blame you me to love you?</S>

<L n="46"/><TLN n="2511"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Phoebe]</SD>
If this be so, why blame you me to love you?</S>

<L n="47"/><TLN n="2512"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
If this be so, why blame you me to love you?</S>

<L n="48"/><TLN n="2513"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Why do you speak too, "Why blame you me <TLN n="2514"/>to love you?"</S>

<L n="49"/><TLN n="2515"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
To her that is not here, nor doth not hear.</S>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="50"/><TLN n="2516"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Pray you, no more of this; 'tis like the howling <TLN n="2517"/>of Irish wolves against the moon.
<SD t="whoto">[To Silvius]</SD>I will help you <TLN n="2518"/>if I can.<SD t="whoto">[To Phoebe]</SD>I would love you if I could. -- Tomorrow meet <TLN n="2519"/>me all together.<SD t="whoto">[To Phoebe]</SD>I will marry you if ever I marry woman, <TLN n="2520"/>and I'll be married tomorrow.<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando]</SD>I will satisfy you <TLN n="2521"/>if ever I satisfied man, and you shall be married tomorrow.<TLN n="2522"/><SD t="whoto">[To Silvius]</SD>I will content you if what pleases you contents <TLN n="2523"/>you, and you shall be married tomorrow.<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando]</SD>As you love <TLN n="2524"/>Rosalind, meet.<SD t="whoto">[To Silvius]</SD>As you love Phoebe, meet. And as I love no <TLN n="2525"/>woman, I'll meet. So, fare you well. I have left you <TLN n="2526"/>commands.</S>

<L n="51"/><TLN n="2527"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
I'll not fail, if I live.</S>

<L n="52"/><TLN n="2528"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
Nor I.</S>

<L n="53"/><TLN n="2529"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
Nor I.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt.</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="3">
<H2><TLN n="2530"/>[5.3]</H2>
<TLN n="2531"/><SD t="entrance">Enter [Touchstone the] Clown and Audrey.</SD>

<L n="1"/><TLN n="2532"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Tomorrow is the joyful day, Audrey; tomorrow <TLN n="2533"/>will we be married.</S>

<L n="2"/><TLN n="2534"/><S><SP>Audrey</SP>
I do desire it with all my heart; and I hope it is <TLN n="2535"/>no dishonest desire to desire to be a woman of the world. <TLN n="2536"/>Here come two of the banished Duke's pages.</S>

<TLN n="2537"/><SD t="entrance">Enter two Pages.</SD>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="2538"/><S><SP>First Page</SP>
Well met, honest gentleman.</S>

<L n="4"/><TLN n="2539"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
By my troth, well met. Come sit, sit, and a song.</S>
<SD t="action">[They sit.]</SD>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="2540"/><S><SP>Second Page</SP>
We are for you. Sit i'th' middle.</S>

<L n="6"/><TLN n="2541"/><S><SP>First Page</SP>
Shall we clap into't roundly, without hawking, <TLN n="2542"/>or spitting, or saying we are hoarse, which are the only prologues to <TLN n="2543"/><!--TLN moved +2 -->a bad voice?</S>

<L n="7"/><TLN n="2544"/><S><SP>Second Page</SP>
I'faith, i'faith, and both in a tune, like two <TLN n="2545"/>gypsies on a horse.</S>

<TLN n="2546"/><SD t="sound">Song.</SD>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">
<L n="8"/><TLN n="2547"/><S><SP>Both Pages</SP>
<VERSEQUOTE>
<STANZA n="1">
It was a lover and his lass,
<L n="9"/><TLN n="2548"/><SPACE n="3"/>With a hey, and a ho, and a hey nonino,
<L n="10"/><TLN n="2549"/>That o'er the green corn-field did pass
<L n="11"/><TLN n="2550"/><SPACE n="3"/>In spring time, the only pretty ring time,
<L n="12"/><TLN n="2251"/>When birds do sing, hey ding a ding, ding.
<L n="13"/><TLN n="2552"/>Sweet lovers love the spring.
</STANZA>
<STANZA n="2">
<L n="14"/><TLN n="2557"/>Between the acres of the rye,
<L n="15"/><TLN n="2558"/><SPACE n="3"/>With a hey, and a ho, and a hey nonino,
<L n="16"/><TLN n="2559"/>These pretty country folks would lie,
<L n="17"/><TLN n="2560"/><SPACE n="3"/>In spring time, the only pretty ring time,
<L n="18"/>When birds do sing, hey ding a ding, ding.
<L n="19"/>Sweet lovers love the spring.
</STANZA>
<STANZA n="3">
<L n="20"/><TLN n="2561"/>This carol they began that hour,
<L n="21"/><TLN n="2562"/><SPACE n="3"/>With a hey, and a ho, and a hey nonino,
<L n="22"/><TLN n="2563"/>How that a life was but a flower,
<L n="23"/><TLN n="2564"/><SPACE n="3"/>In spring time, the only pretty ring time,
<L n="24"/>When birds do sing, hey ding a ding, ding.
<L n="25"/>Sweet lovers love the spring.
</STANZA>
<STANZA n="4">
<L n="26"/><TLN n="2553"/>And therefore take the present time,
<L n="27"/><TLN n="2554"/><SPACE n="3"/>With a hey, and a ho, and a hey nonino,
<L n="28"/><TLN n="2555"/>For love is crown{`e}d with the prime,
<L n="29"/><TLN n="2556"/><SPACE n="3"/>In spring time, the only pretty ring time,
<L n="30"/>When birds do sing, hey ding a ding, ding.
<L n="31"/>Sweet lovers love the spring. 
</STANZA></S>
</VERSEQUOTE>
</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="32"/><TLN n="2565"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Truly, young gentlemen, though there was no <TLN n="2566"/>great matter in the ditty, yet the note was very untuneable.</S>

<L n="33"/><TLN n="2567"/><S><SP>First Page</SP>
You are deceived, sir; we kept time, we lost not <TLN n="2568"/>our time.</S>

<L n="34"/><TLN n="2569"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
By my troth, yes; I count it but time lost to hear <TLN n="2570"/>such a foolish song. God b'wi' you, and God mend your <TLN n="2571"/>voices. -- Come, Audrey.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt [the Pages one way, Touchstone and Audrey another].</SD>

</SCENE>
<SCENE n="4">
<H2><TLN n="2572"/>[5.4]</H2>
<TLN n="2573"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Duke Senior, Amiens, Jaques, Orlando, <TLN n="2574"/>Oliver, [and] Celia.</SD>

</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="1"/><TLN n="2575"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Dost thou believe, Orlando, that the boy
<L n="2"/><TLN n="2576"/>Can do all this that he hath promised?</S>

<L n="3"/><TLN n="2577"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
I sometimes do believe and sometimes do not,
<L n="4"/><TLN n="2578"/>As those that fear they hope, and know they fear.</S>

<TLN n="2579"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Rosalind, Silvius, and Phoebe.</SD>

<L n="5"/><TLN n="2580"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
Patience once more, whiles our compact is urged.
<SD t="whoto">[To the Duke]</SD>
<L n="6"/><TLN n="2581"/>You say, if I bring in your Rosalind,
<L n="7"/><TLN n="2582"/>You will bestow her on Orlando here?</S>

<L n="8"/><TLN n="2583"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
That would I, had I kingdoms to give with her.</S>

<L n="9"/><TLN n="2584"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando]</SD>
And you say you will have her when I bring her?</S>

<L n="10"/><TLN n="2585"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
That would I, were I of all kingdoms king.</S>

<L n="11"/><TLN n="2586"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Phoebe]</SD>
You say you'll marry me, if I be willing?</S>

<L n="12"/><TLN n="2587"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
That will I, should I die the hour after.</S>

<L n="13"/><TLN n="2588"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
But if you do refuse to marry me,
<L n="14"/><TLN n="2589"/>You'll give yourself to this most faithful shepherd?</S>

<L n="15"/><TLN n="2590"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
So is the bargain.</S>

<L n="16"/><TLN n="2591"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Silvius]</SD>
You say that you'll have Phoebe if she will?</S>

<L n="17"/><TLN n="2592"/><S><SP>Silvius</SP>
Though to have her and death were both one <TLN n="2593"/>thing.</S>

<L n="18"/><TLN n="2594"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
I have promised to make all this matter even.
<L n="19"/><TLN n="2595"/>Keep you your word, O Duke, to give your daughter;
<L n="20"/><TLN n="2596"/>You yours, Orlando, to receive his daughter;
<L n="21"/><TLN n="2597"/>Keep you your word, Phoebe, that you'll marry me,
<L n="22"/><TLN n="2598"/>Or else, refusing me, to wed this shepherd;
<L n="23"/><TLN n="2599"/>Keep your word, Silvius, that you'll marry her
<L n="24"/><TLN n="2600"/>If she refuse me; and from hence I go,
<L n="25"/><TLN n="2601"/>To make these doubts all even.</S>
<SD t="exit">Exeunt Rosalind and Celia.</SD>

<L n="26"/><TLN n="2602"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
I do remember in this shepherd boy
<L n="27"/><TLN n="2603"/>Some lively touches of my daughter's favor.</S>

<L n="28"/><TLN n="2604"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
My lord, the first time that I ever saw him
<L n="29"/><TLN n="2605"/>Methought he was a brother to your daughter.
<L n="30"/><TLN n="2606"/>But, my good lord, this boy is forest-born,
<L n="31"/><TLN n="2607"/>And hath been tutored in the rudiments
<L n="32"/><TLN n="2608"/>Of many desperate studies by his uncle,
<L n="33"/><TLN n="2609"/>Whom he reports to be a great magician,

<TLN n="2610"/><SD t="entrance">Enter [Touchstone the] Clown and Audrey.</SD>

<L n="34"/><TLN n="2611"/>Obscur{`e}d in the circle of this forest.</S>

</MODE>
<MODE t="prose">

<L n="35"/><TLN n="2612"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
There is, sure, another flood toward, and these <TLN n="2613"/>couples are coming to the ark. Here comes a pair <TLN n="2614"/>of very strange beasts, which in all tongues are called <TLN n="2615"/>fools.</S>

<L n="36"/><TLN n="2616"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Salutation and greeting to you all!</S>

<L n="37"/><TLN n="2617"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To the Duke]</SD>
Good my lord, bid him welcome. This is the <TLN n="2618"/>motley-minded gentleman that I have so often met in <TLN n="2619"/>the forest. He hath been a courtier, he swears.</S>

<L n="38"/><TLN n="2620"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
If any man doubt that, let him put me to my <TLN n="2621"/>purgation. I have trod a measure; I have flattered a lady; <TLN n="2622"/>I have been politic with my friend, smooth with mine <TLN n="2623"/>enemy; I have undone three tailors; I have had four <TLN n="2624"/>quarrels, and like to have fought one.</S>

<L n="39"/><TLN n="2625"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
And how was that ta'en up?</S>

<L n="40"/><TLN n="2626"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Faith, we met, and found the quarrel was upon <TLN n="2627"/>the seventh cause.</S>

<L n="41"/><TLN n="2628"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
How seventh cause? -- Good my lord, like this <TLN n="2629"/>fellow.</S>

<L n="42"/><TLN n="2630"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
I like him very well.</S>

<L n="43"/><TLN n="2631"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
God 'ild you, sir, I desire you of the like. I press <TLN n="2632"/>in here, sir, amongst the rest of the country copulatives, <TLN n="2633"/>to swear and to forswear, according as marriage binds <TLN n="2634"/>and blood breaks. A poor virgin, sir, an ill-favored thing, <TLN n="2635"/>sir, but mine own; a poor humor of mine, sir, to take <TLN n="2636"/>that that no man else will. Rich honesty dwells like a miser, <TLN n="2637"/>sir, in a poor house, as your pearl in your foul <TLN n="2638"/>oyster.</S>

<L n="44"/><TLN n="2639"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
By my faith, he is very swift and sententious.</S>

<L n="45"/><TLN n="2640"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
According to the fool's bolt, sir, and such <TLN n="2641"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->dulcet diseases.</S>

<L n="46"/><TLN n="2642"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
But for the seventh cause. How did you find <TLN n="2643"/>the quarrel on the seventh cause?</S>

<L n="47"/><TLN n="2644"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Upon a lie seven times removed -- bear your <TLN n="2645"/>body more seeming, Audrey -- as thus, sir. I did dislike the <TLN n="2646"/>cut of a certain courtier's beard. He sent me word, if I <TLN n="2647"/>said his beard was not cut well, he was in the mind it <TLN n="2648"/>was. This is called the Retort Courteous. If I sent him <TLN n="2649"/>word again it was not well cut, he would send me word <TLN n="2650"/>he cut it to please himself. This is called the Quip Modest. <TLN n="2651"/>If again it was not well cut, he disabled my judgment. <TLN n="2652"/>This is called the Reply Churlish. If again it was not well <TLN n="2653"/>cut, he would answer I spake not true. This is called the <TLN n="2654"/>Reproof Valiant. If again it was not well cut, he would <TLN n="2655"/>say I lie. This is called the Countercheck Quarrelsome. <TLN n="2656"/>And so to the Lie Circumstantial and the Lie Direct.</S>

<L n="48"/><TLN n="2657"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
And how oft did you say his beard was not well <TLN n="2658"/>cut?</S>

<L n="49"/><TLN n="2659"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
I durst go no further than the Lie Circumstantial, <TLN n="2660"/>nor he durst not give me the Lie Direct; and so we <TLN n="2661"/><!--TLN moved -1 -->measured swords and parted.</S>

<L n="50"/><TLN n="2662"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Can you nominate in order now the degrees of <TLN n="2663"/>the lie?</S>

<L n="51"/><TLN n="2664"/><S><SP>Touchstone</SP>
Oh, sir, we quarrel in print, by the book, as you <TLN n="2665"/>have books for good manners. I will name you the degrees. <TLN n="2666"/>The first, the Retort Courteous; the second, the<TLN n="2667"/> Quip Modest; the third, the Reply Churlish; the fourth, <TLN n="2668"/>the Reproof Valiant; the fifth, the Countercheck Quarrelsome; <TLN n="2669"/>the sixth, the Lie with Circumstance; the seventh, <TLN n="2670"/>the Lie Direct. All these you may avoid but the <TLN n="2671"/>Lie Direct; and you may avoid that too, with an If. I <TLN n="2672"/>knew when seven justices could not take up a quarrel, but <TLN n="2673"/>when the parties were met themselves, one of them <TLN n="2674"/>thought but of an If, as: "If you said so, then I said so"; <TLN n="2675"/>and they shook hands, and swore brothers. Your If is <TLN n="2676"/>the only peace-maker; much virtue in If.</S>

<L n="52"/><TLN n="2677"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To the Duke]</SD>
Is not this a rare fellow, my lord? He's as good <TLN n="2678"/>at anything, and yet a fool.</S>

<L n="53"/><TLN n="2679"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
He uses his folly like a stalking-horse, and under <TLN n="2680"/>the presentation of that he shoots his wit.</S>

<TLN n="2681"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Hymen, Rosalind, and Celia.</SD><TLN n="2682"/><SD t="sound">Still music. [Rosalind and Celia are no longer disguised.]</SD>
</MODE>
<MODE t="verse">

<L n="54"/><TLN n="2683"/><S><SP>Hymen</SP>
<VERSEQUOTE>
Then is there mirth in heaven,
<L n="55"/><TLN n="2684"/>When earthly things made even
<L n="56"/><TLN n="2685"/><SPACE n="3"/>Atone together.
<L n="57"/><TLN n="2686"/>Good Duke, receive thy daughter;
<L n="58"/><TLN n="2687"/>Hymen from heaven brought her,
<L n="59"/><TLN n="2688"/><SPACE n="3"/>Yea, brought her hither,
<L n="60"/><TLN n="2689"/>That thou mightst join her hand with his,
<L n="61"/><TLN n="2690"/>Whose heart within his bosom is.</S>
</VERSEQUOTE>
<L n="62"/><TLN n="2691"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To the Duke]</SD>
To you I give myself, for I am yours.
<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando]</SD>
<L n="63"/><TLN n="2692"/>To you I give myself, for I am yours.</S>

<L n="64"/><TLN n="2693"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
If there be truth in sight, you are my daughter.</S>

<L n="65"/><TLN n="2694"/><S><SP>Orlando</SP>
If there be truth in sight, you are my Rosalind.</S>

<L n="66"/><TLN n="2695"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
If sight and shape be true,
<L n="67"/>Why then, my love adieu!</S>

<L n="68"/><TLN n="2696"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To the Duke]</SD>
I'll have no father, if you be not he;
<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando]</SD>
<L n="69"/><TLN n="2697"/>I'll have no husband, if you be not he;
<SD t="whoto">[To Phoebe]</SD>
<L n="70"/><TLN n="2698"/>Nor ne'er wed woman, if you be not she.</S>

<L n="71"/><TLN n="2699"/><S><SP>Hymen</SP>
<VERSEQUOTE>
Peace, ho! I bar confusion.
<L n="72"/><TLN n="2700"/>'Tis I must make conclusion
<L n="73"/><TLN n="2701"/><SPACE n="3"/>Of these most strange events.
<L n="74"/><TLN n="2702"/>Here's eight that must take hands
<L n="75"/><TLN n="2703"/>To join in Hymen's bands,
<L n="76"/><TLN n="2704"/><SPACE n="3"/>If truth holds true contents.
<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando and Rosalind]</SD>
<L n="77"/><TLN n="2705"/>You and you no cross shall part.
<SD t="whoto">[To Oliver and Celia]</SD>
<L n="78"/><TLN n="2706"/>You and you are heart in heart.
<SD t="whoto">[To Phoebe]</SD>
<L n="79"/><TLN n="2707"/>You to his love must accord,
<L n="80"/><TLN n="2708"/>Or have a woman to your lord.
<SD t="whoto">[To Touchstone and Audrey]</SD>
<L n="81"/><TLN n="2709"/>You and you are sure together,
<L n="82"/><TLN n="2710"/>As the winter to foul weather.
<SD t="whoto">[To All]</SD>
<L n="83"/><TLN n="2711"/>Whiles a wedlock hymn we sing,
<L n="84"/><TLN n="2712"/>Feed yourselves with questioning,
<L n="85"/><TLN n="2713"/>That reason wonder may diminish,
<L n="86"/><TLN n="2714"/>How thus we met, and these things finish.

<TLN n="2715"/><SD t="sound">SONG.</SD>

<L n="87"/><TLN n="2716"/>Wedding is great Juno's crown,
<L n="88"/><TLN n="2717"/><SPACE n="3"/>O bless{`e}d bond of board and bed!
<L n="89"/><TLN n="2718"/>'Tis Hymen peoples every town;
<L n="90"/><TLN n="2719"/><SPACE n="3"/>High wedlock then be honor{`e}d.
<L n="91"/><TLN n="2720"/>Honor, high honor and renown
<L n="92"/><TLN n="2721"/><SPACE n="3"/>To Hymen, god of every town!</S>
</VERSEQUOTE>

<L n="93"/><TLN n="2722"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Celia]</SD>
O my dear niece, welcome thou art to me!
<L n="94"/><TLN n="2723"/>Even daughter, welcome, in no less degree.</S>

<L n="95"/><TLN n="2724"/><S><SP>Phoebe</SP>
<SD t="whoto">[To Silvius]</SD>
I will not eat my word, now thou art mine;
<L n="96"/><TLN n="2725"/>Thy faith my fancy to thee doth combine.</S>

<TLN n="2726"/><SD t="entrance">Enter Second Brother [Jaques de Boys].</SD>

<L n="97"/><TLN n="2727"/><S><SP>Jaques de Boys</SP>
Let me have audience for a word or two.
<L n="98"/><TLN n="2728"/>I am the second son of old Sir Rowland,
<L n="99"/><TLN n="2729"/>That bring these tidings to this fair assembly.
<L n="100"/><TLN n="2730"/>Duke Frederick, hearing how that every day
<L n="101"/><TLN n="2731"/>Men of great worth resorted to this forest,
<L n="102"/><TLN n="2732"/>Addressed a mighty power, which were on foot
<L n="103"/><TLN n="2733"/>In his own conduct, purposely to take
<L n="104"/><TLN n="2734"/>His brother here, and put him to the sword;
<L n="105"/><TLN n="2735"/>And to the skirts of this wild wood he came,
<L n="106"/><TLN n="2736"/>Where, meeting with an old religious man,
<L n="107"/><TLN n="2737"/>After some question with him, was converted
<L n="108"/><TLN n="2738"/>Both from his enterprise and from the world,
<L n="109"/><TLN n="2739"/>His crown bequeathing to his banished brother,
<L n="110"/><TLN n="2740"/>And all their lands restored to them again
<L n="111"/><TLN n="2741"/>That were with him exiled. This to be true
<L n="112" part="i"/><TLN n="2742"/>I do engage my life.</S>

<TLN n="2743"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
<L n="112" part="f"/>Welcome, young man.
<L n="113"/><TLN n="2744"/>Thou offer'st fairly to thy brothers' wedding:
<L n="114"/><TLN n="2745"/>To one his lands withheld, and to the other
<L n="115"/><TLN n="2746"/>A land itself at large, a potent dukedom.
<L n="116"/><TLN n="2747"/>First, in this forest let us do those ends
<L n="117"/><TLN n="2748"/>That here were well begun and well begot;
<L n="118"/><TLN n="2749"/>And after, every of this happy number
<L n="119"/><TLN n="2750"/>That have endured shrewd days and nights with us
<L n="120"/><TLN n="2751"/>Shall share the good of our return{`e}d fortune,
<L n="121"/><TLN n="2752"/>According to the measure of their states.
<L n="122"/><TLN n="2753"/>Meantime, forget this new-fall'n dignity,
<L n="123"/><TLN n="2754"/>And fall into our rustic revelry.
<L n="124"/><TLN n="2755"/>Play, music! And you brides and bridegrooms all,
<L n="125"/><TLN n="2756"/>With measure heaped in joy, to th' measures fall.</S>

<L n="126"/><TLN n="2757"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
Sir, by your patience. <SD t="whoto">[To Jaques de Boys]</SD> If I heard you rightly,
<L n="127"/><TLN n="2758"/>The Duke hath put on a religious life,
<L n="128"/><TLN n="2759"/>And thrown into neglect the pompous court.</S>

<L n="129"/><TLN n="2760"/><S><SP>Jaques de Boys</SP>
He hath.</S>

<L n="130"/><TLN n="2761"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
To him will I. Out of these convertites
<L n="131"/><TLN n="2762"/>There is much matter to be heard and learned.
<SD t="whoto">[To the Duke]</SD>
<L n="132"/><TLN n="2763"/>You to your former honor I bequeath;
<L n="133"/><TLN n="2764"/>Your patience and your virtue well deserves it.
<SD t="whoto">[To Orlando]</SD>
<L n="134"/><TLN n="2765"/>You to a love that your true faith doth merit;
<SD t="whoto">[To Oliver]</SD>
<L n="135"/><TLN n="2766"/>You to your land and love and great allies;
<SD t="whoto">[To Silvius]</SD>
<L n="136"/><TLN n="2767"/>You to a long and well-deserv{`e}d bed;
<SD t="whoto">[To Touchstone]</SD>
<L n="137"/><TLN n="2768"/>And you to wrangling, for thy loving voyage
<L n="138"/><TLN n="2769"/>Is but for two months victualled. -- So to your pleasures;
<L n="139"/><TLN n="2770"/>I am for other than for dancing measures.</S>

<L n="140"/><TLN n="2771"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Stay, Jaques, stay!</S>

<L n="141"/><TLN n="2772"/><S><SP>Jaques</SP>
To see no pastime, I. What you would have
<L n="142"/><TLN n="2773"/>I'll stay to know at your abandoned cave. </S>
<SD t="exit">Exit.</SD>

<L n="143"/><TLN n="2774"/><S><SP>Duke Senior</SP>
Proceed, proceed. We'll begin these rites,
<L n="144"/><TLN n="2775"/>As we do trust they'll end, in true delights.</S>
<SD t="action, exit">[They dance.] Exeunt [all but Rosalind].</SD>
</MODE>
</SCENE>
</ACT>

<BACKMATTER>
<DIV name="Epilogue">
<MODE t="prose">
<L n="1"/><TLN n="2776"/><S><SP>Rosalind</SP>
It is not the fashion to see the lady the epilogue; <TLN n="2777"/>but it is no more unhandsome than to see the <TLN n="2778"/>lord the prologue. If it be true that good wine needs <TLN n="2779"/>no bush, 'tis true that a good play needs no epilogue. <TLN n="2780"/>Yet to good wine they do use good bushes, and good <TLN n="2781"/>plays prove the better by the help of good epilogues. <TLN n="2782"/>What a case am I in then, that am neither a good epilogue, <TLN n="2783"/>nor cannot insinuate with you in the behalf of a <TLN n="2784"/>good play! I am not furnished like a beggar; therefore <TLN n="2785"/>to beg will not become me. My way is to conjure <TLN n="2786"/>you, and I'll begin with the women. I charge you, O <TLN n="2787"/>women, for the love you bear to men, to like as much <TLN n="2788"/>of this play as please you; and I charge you, O men, <TLN n="2789"/>for the love you bear to women -- as I perceive by your <TLN n="2790"/>simpering, none of you hates them -- that between you <TLN n="2791"/>and the women the play may please. If I were a woman, <TLN n="2792"/>I would kiss as many of you as had beards that <TLN n="2793"/>pleased me, complexions that liked me, and breaths that <TLN n="2794"/>I defied not; and, I am sure, as many as have good <TLN n="2795"/>beards, or good faces, or sweet breaths, will, for my kind <TLN n="2796"/>offer, when I make curtsy, bid me farewell.</S>
</MODE>
<SD t="exit">Exit.</SD>
</DIV>
</BACKMATTER>
</WORK>
